<script src="//archive.org/includes/analytics.js?v=cf34f82" type="text/javascript"></script>
<script type="text/javascript">window.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded',function(){var v=archive_analytics.values;v.service='wb';v.server_name='wwwb-app23.us.archive.org';v.server_ms=803;archive_analytics.send_pageview({});});</script><script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/wbhack.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<script type="text/javascript">
__wbhack.init('https://web.archive.org/web');
</script>
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/banner-styles.css?v=1531166943.0" />
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/iconochive.css?v=1531166943.0" />

<!-- End Wayback Rewrite JS Include --><!-- BEGIN WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT -->
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/timestamp.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/graph-calc.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/auto-complete.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/toolbar.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<style type="text/css">
body {
  margin-top:0 !important;
  padding-top:0 !important;
  /*min-width:800px !important;*/
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestions {
    text-align: left; cursor: default; border: 1px solid #ccc; border-top: 0; background: #fff; box-shadow: -1px 1px 3px rgba(0,0,0,.1);
    position: absolute; display: none; z-index: 2147483647; max-height: 254px; overflow: hidden; overflow-y: auto; box-sizing: border-box;
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion { position: relative; padding: 0 .6em; line-height: 23px; white-space: nowrap; overflow: hidden; text-overflow: ellipsis; font-size: 1.02em; color: #333; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion b { font-weight: bold; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion.selected { background: #f0f0f0; }
</style>
<div id="wm-ipp" lang="en" style="display:none;direction:ltr;">
<div style="position:fixed;left:0;top:0;right:0;">
<div id="wm-ipp-inside">
  <div style="position:relative;">
    <div id="wm-logo" style="float:left;width:130px;padding-top:10px;">
      <a href="/web/" title="Wayback Machine home page"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wayback-toolbar-logo.png" alt="Wayback Machine" width="110" height="39" border="0" /></a>
    </div>
    <div class="r" style="float:right;">
      <div id="wm-btns" style="text-align:right;height:25px;">
                  <div id="wm-save-snapshot-success">success</div>
          <div id="wm-save-snapshot-fail">fail</div>
          <a href="#"
             onclick="__wm.saveSnapshot('https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9917?contentType=xml', '20180713022048')"
             title="Share via My Web Archive"
             id="wm-save-snapshot-open"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-web"></span>
          </a>
          <a href="https://archive.org/account/login.php"
             title="Sign In"
             id="wm-sign-in"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-person"></span>
          </a>
          <span id="wm-save-snapshot-in-progress" class="iconochive-web"></span>
        	<a href="http://faq.web.archive.org/" title="Get some help using the Wayback Machine" style="top:-6px;"><span class="iconochive-question" style="color:rgb(87,186,244);font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a id="wm-tb-close" href="#close" onclick="__wm.h(event);return false;" style="top:-2px;" title="Close the toolbar"><span class="iconochive-remove-circle" style="color:#888888;font-size:240%;"></span></a>
      </div>
      <div id="wm-share" style="text-align:right;">
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://web.archive.org/web/20180713022048/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9917?contentType=xml', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Facebook" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-facebook" style="color:#3b5998;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=https://web.archive.org/web/20180713022048/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9917?contentType=xml&amp;via=internetarchive', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Twitter" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-twitter" style="color:#1dcaff;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
      </div>
    </div>
    <table class="c" style="">
      <tbody>
	<tr>
	  <td class="u" colspan="2">
	    <form target="_top" method="get" action="/web/submit" name="wmtb" id="wmtb"><input type="text" name="url" id="wmtbURL" value="https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9917?contentType=xml" onfocus="this.focus();this.select();" /><input type="hidden" name="type" value="replay" /><input type="hidden" name="date" value="20180713022048" /><input type="submit" value="Go" /></form>
	  </td>
	  <td class="n" rowspan="2" style="width:110px;">
	    <table>
	      <tbody>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV MONTH NAV AND MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="m">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180610053739/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9917?contentType=xml" title="10 Jun 2018"><strong>Jun</strong></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayMonthEl" title="You are here: 02:20:48 Jul 13, 2018">JUL</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">Aug</td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV CAPTURE NAV AND DAY OF MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="d">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180610053739/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9917?contentType=xml" title="05:37:39 Jun 10, 2018"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_prv_on.png" alt="Previous capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayDayEl" style="width:34px;font-size:24px;white-space:nowrap;" title="You are here: 02:20:48 Jul 13, 2018">13</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_nxt_off.png" alt="Next capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV YEAR NAV AND YEAR INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="y">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160930190328/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9917?contentType=xml" title="30 Sep 2016"><strong>2016</strong></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayYearEl" title="You are here: 02:20:48 Jul 13, 2018">2018</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">2019</td>
		</tr>
	      </tbody>
	    </table>
	  </td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td class="s">
	    	    <div id="wm-nav-captures">
	      	      <a class="t" href="/web/20180713022048*/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9917?contentType=xml" title="See a list of every capture for this URL">6 captures</a>
	      <div class="r" title="Timespan for captures of this URL">30 Sep 2016 - 13 Jul 2018</div>
	      </div>
	  </td>
	  <td class="k">
	    <a href="" id="wm-graph-anchor">
	      <div id="wm-ipp-sparkline" title="Explore captures for this URL" style="position: relative">
		<canvas id="wm-sparkline-canvas" width="575" height="27" border="0"></canvas>
	      </div>
	    </a>
	  </td>
	</tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <div style="position:absolute;bottom:0;right:2px;text-align:right;">
      <a id="wm-expand" class="wm-btn wm-closed" href="#expand" onclick="__wm.ex(event);return false;"><span id="wm-expand-icon" class="iconochive-down-solid"></span> <span style="font-size:80%">About this capture</span></a>
    </div>
  </div>
    <div id="wm-capinfo" style="border-top:1px solid #777;display:none; overflow: hidden">
            <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center">COLLECTED BY</div>
    <div style="padding:3px;position:relative" id="wm-collected-by-content">
            <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:50%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/archiveteam);"></span>
		Organization: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/archiveteam" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">Archive Team</span></a>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  <img align=right src="http://archiveteam.org/images/e/e6/Archiveteam.jpg" width=200> Formed in 2009, the Archive Team (not to be confused with the archive.org Archive-It Team) is a rogue archivist collective dedicated to saving copies of rapidly dying or deleted websites for the sake of history and digital heritage. The group is 100% composed of volunteers and interested parties, and has expanded into a large amount of related projects for saving online and digital history.
<p>
History is littered with hundreds of conflicts over the future of a community, group, location or business that were "resolved" when one of the parties stepped ahead and destroyed what was there. With the original point of contention destroyed, the debates would fall to the wayside. Archive Team believes that by duplicated condemned data, the conversation and debate can continue, as well as the richness and insight gained by keeping the materials. Our projects have ranged in size from a single volunteer downloading the data to a small-but-critical site, to over 100 volunteers stepping forward to acquire terabytes of user-created data to save for future generations.
<p>
The main site for Archive Team is at <a href="http://www.archiveteam.org">archiveteam.org</a> and contains up to the date information on various projects, manifestos, plans and walkthroughs.
<p>
This collection contains the output of many Archive Team projects, both ongoing and completed. Thanks to the generous providing of disk space by the Internet Archive, multi-terabyte datasets can be made available, as well as in use by the <a href="http://archive.org/web/web.php">Wayback Machine</a>, providing a path back to lost websites and work. 
<p>
Our collection has grown to the point of having sub-collections for the type of data we acquire. If you are seeking to browse the contents of these collections, the Wayback Machine is the best first stop. Otherwise, you are free to dig into the stacks to see what you may find.
<p>
<b>The Archive Team Panic Downloads</b> are full pulldowns of currently extant websites, meant to serve as emergency backups for needed sites that are in danger of closing, or which will be missed dearly if suddenly lost due to hard drive crashes or server failures. 
<p>
	</div>
	      </div>
      <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:49%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/archivebot)"></span>
		<div>Collection: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/archivebot" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">ArchiveBot: The Archive Team Crowdsourced Crawler</span></a></div>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  ArchiveBot is an IRC bot designed to automate the archival of smaller websites (e.g. up to a few hundred thousand URLs). You give it a URL to start at, and it grabs all content under that URL, records it in a WARC, and then uploads that WARC to ArchiveTeam servers for eventual injection into the Internet Archive (or other archive sites).
<p>
To use ArchiveBot, drop by #archivebot on EFNet. To interact with ArchiveBot, you issue commands by typing it into the channel. Note you will need channel operator permissions in order to issue archiving jobs. The dashboard shows the sites being downloaded currently.
<p>
There is a dashboard running for the archivebot process at <a href="http://www.archivebot.com">http://www.archivebot.com</a>.
<p>
ArchiveBot's source code can be found at <a href="https://github.com/ArchiveTeam/ArchiveBot">https://github.com/ArchiveTeam/ArchiveBot</a>.
	</div>
	      </div>
    </div>
    <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center" title="Timestamps for the elements of this page">TIMESTAMPS</div>
    <div>
      <div id="wm-capresources" style="margin:0 5px 5px 5px;max-height:250px;overflow-y:scroll !important"></div>
      <div id="wm-capresources-loading" style="text-align:left;margin:0 20px 5px 5px;display:none"><img src="/static/images/loading.gif" alt="loading" /></div>
    </div>
  </div></div></div></div><script type="text/javascript">
__wm.bt(575,27,25,2,"web","https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9917?contentType=xml","2018-07-13",1996);
</script>
<!-- END WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT --><version>
  <xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource>
  <section secid="390" ordby="100" name="General">
    <field fieldid="161" ordby="105" id="391" name="Guideline Title" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_title&quot;>Follow-up for clinically localized renal neoplasms: AUA guideline.</div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="110" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Donat SM, Diaz M, Bishoff JT, Coleman JA, Dahm P, Derweesh IH, Herrell SD III, Hilton S, Jonasch E, Lin DW, Reuter VE, Chang SS. Follow-up for clinically localized renal neoplasms: AUA guideline. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc.; 2013 Apr. 33 p.  [135 references]</td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="115" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="420" ordby="300" name="Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="151" ordby="310" id="421" name="Major Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Definitions for the body of evidence strength (<strong>grade A, B, </strong>or<strong> C</strong>), the strength of the recommendations (<strong>Standard, Recommendation, Option</strong>), and for statements labeled as <strong>Clinical Principle</strong> and <strong>Expert Opinion</strong> are provided at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Guideline Statements</span></strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;>
    <li>Patients undergoing follow-up for treated or observed renal masses should undergo a history and physical examination directed at detecting signs and symptoms of metastatic spread or local recurrence. (<em>Clinical Principle</em>) </li>
    <li>Patients undergoing follow-up for treated or observed renal masses should undergo basic laboratory testing to include blood urea nitrogen (BUN)/creatinine, urine analysis (UA) and estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR). Other laboratory evaluations, including complete blood count (CBC), lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), liver function tests (LFTs), alkaline phosphatase (ALP) and calcium level, may be used at the discretion of the clinician. (<em>Expert Opinion</em>) </li>
    <li>Patients with progressive renal insufficiency on follow-up laboratory evaluation should be referred to nephrology. (<em>Expert Opinion</em>) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends a bone scan in patients with an elevated ALP, clinical symptoms such as bone pain, and/or if radiographic findings are suggestive of a bony neoplasm. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends against the performance of a bone scan in the absence of an elevated ALP or clinical symptoms, such as bone pain, or radiographic findings suggestive of a bony neoplasm. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>Patients with a history of a renal neoplasm presenting with acute neurological signs or symptoms must undergo prompt neurologic cross-sectional computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scanning of the head or spine based on localization of symptomatology. (<em>Standard</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade A) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends against the routine use of molecular markers, such Ki-67, p-53 and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), as benefits remain unproven at this time. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Surgery: Low Risk Patients (pT1, N0, Nx)</strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;8&quot;>
    <li>Patients should undergo a baseline abdominal scan (CT or MRI) for nephron sparing surgery and abdominal imaging (ultrasound [US], CT or MRI) for radical nephrectomy within three to twelve months following renal surgery. (<em>Expert Opinion</em>) </li>
    <li>Additional abdominal imaging (US, CT or MRI) may be performed in patients with low risk (pT1, N0, Nx) disease following a radical nephrectomy if the initial postoperative baseline image is negative. (<em>Option</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>Abdominal imaging (US, CT, or MRI) may be performed yearly for three years in patients with low risk (pT1, N0, Nx) disease following a partial nephrectomy based on individual risk factors if the initial postoperative scan is negative. (<em>Option</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends that patients with a history of low risk (pT1, N0, Nx) renal cell carcinoma undergo yearly chest x-ray (CXR) to assess for pulmonary metastases for three years and only as clinically indicated beyond that time period. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Surgery: Moderate to High Risk Patients (pT2-4N0 Nx or Any Stage N+)</strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;12&quot;>
    <li>The Panel recommends that moderate to high risk patients undergo baseline chest and abdominal scan (CT or MRI) within three to six months following surgery with continued imaging (US, CXR, CT or MRI) every six months for at least three years and annually thereafter to year five. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends site-specific imaging as warranted by clinical symptoms suggestive of recurrence or metastatic spread. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>Imaging (US, CXR, CT or MRI) beyond five years may be performed at the discretion of the clinician for moderate to high risk patients. (<em>Option</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>Routine fludeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) scan is not indicated in the follow-up for renal cancer. (<em>Expert Opinion</em>) </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Active Surveillance</strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;16&quot;>
    <li>Percutaneous biopsy may be considered in patients planning to undergo active surveillance. (<em>Option</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends that patients undergo cross-sectional abdominal scanning (CT or MRI) within six months of active surveillance initiation to establish a growth rate. The Panel further recommends continued imaging (US, CT or MRI) at least annually thereafter. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends that patients on active surveillance with biopsy proven renal cell carcinoma or a tumor with oncocytic features undergo an annual CXR to assess for pulmonary metastases. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Ablation</strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;19&quot;>
    <li>A urologist should be involved in the clinical management of all patients undergoing renal ablative procedures including percutaneous ablation. (<em>Expert Opinion</em>) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends that all patients undergoing ablation procedures for a renal mass undergo a pretreatment diagnostic biopsy. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>The standardized definition of &quot;treatment failure or local recurrence&quot; suggested in the Clinical T1 Guideline document should be adopted by clinicians. This should be further clarified to include a visually enlarging neoplasm or new nodularity in the same area of treatment whether determined by enhancement of the neoplasm on post-treatment contrast imaging, or failure of regression in size of the treated lesion over time, new satellite or port site soft tissue nodules, or biopsy proven recurrence. (<em>Clinical Principle</em>) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends that patients undergo cross-sectional scanning (CT or MRI) with and without intravenous (IV) contrast unless otherwise contraindicated at three and six months following ablative therapy to assess treatment success. This should be followed by annual abdominal scans (CT or MRI) thereafter for five years. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>Patients may undergo further scanning (CT or MRI) beyond five years based on individual patient risk factors. (<em>Option</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>Patients undergoing ablative procedures who have either biopsy proven low risk renal cell carcinoma, oncocytoma, a tumor with oncocytic features, nondiagnostic biopsies or no prior biopsy, should undergo annual CXR to assess for pulmonary metastases for five years. Imaging beyond five years is optional based on individual patient risk factors and the determination of treatment success. (<em>Expert Opinion</em>) </li>
    <li>The Panel recommends against further radiologic scanning in patients who underwent an ablative procedure with pathological confirmation of benign histology at or before treatment and who have radiographic confirmation of treatment success and no evidence of treatment related complications requiring further imaging. (<em>Recommendation</em>; Evidence Strength: Grade C) </li>
    <li>The alternatives of observation, repeat treatment and surgical intervention should be discussed, and repeat biopsy should be performed if there is radiographic evidence of treatment failure within six months if the patient is a treatment candidate. (<em>Expert Opinion</em>) </li>
    <li>A progressive increase in size of an ablated neoplasm, with or without contrast enhancement, new nodularity in or around the treated zone, failure of the treated lesion to regress in size over time, satellite or port side lesions, should prompt lesion biopsy. (<em>Expert Opinion</em>) </li>
</ol>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Definitions</span></strong>:</p>
<p><strong>Body of Evidence Strength</strong></p>
<p>Overall quality scores together with study design and consistency of estimates across studies were used to grade the strength of the evidence into three levels: <strong>A (high)</strong>,<strong> B (moderate)</strong> or<strong> C (low)</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>American Urological Association (AUA) Nomenclature Linking Statement Type to Evidence Strength</strong></p>
<p><strong>Standard</strong>: Directive statement that an action should (benefits outweigh risks/burdens) or should not (risks/burdens outweigh benefits) be taken based on Grade A or B evidence</p>
<p><strong>Recommendation</strong>: Directive statement that an action should (benefits outweigh risks/burdens) or should not (risks/burdens outweigh benefits) be taken based on Grade C evidence</p>
<p><strong>Option</strong>: Non-directive statement that leaves the decision regarding an action up to the individual clinician and patient because the balance between benefits and risks/burdens appears equal or appears uncertain based on Grade A, B, or C evidence</p>
<p><strong>Clinical Principle</strong>: A statement about a component of clinical care that is widely agreed upon by urologists or other clinicians for which there may or may not be evidence in the medical literature</p>
<p><strong>Expert Opinion</strong>: A statement, achieved by consensus of the Panel, that is based on members' clinical training, experience, knowledge, and judgment for which there is no evidence</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="138" ordby="330" id="423" name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>None provided</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="396" ordby="400" name="Scope">
    <field fieldid="140" ordby="405" id="397" name="Disease/Condition(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Localized renal neoplasms</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="103" ordby="410" id="398" name="Guideline Category" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Diagnosis"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Evaluation"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Management"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Treatment"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="113" ordby="415" id="399" name="Clinical Specialty" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Family Practice"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Nephrology"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Oncology"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Radiology"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Urology"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="114" ordby="420" id="400" name="Intended Users" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Physicians"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="129" ordby="425" id="401" name="Guideline Objective(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>To create evidence-based guidelines for the follow-up and surveillance of clinically localized renal cancers treated with surgery or renal ablative procedures, biopsy-proven untreated clinically localized renal cancers followed on surveillance and radiographically suspicious but biopsy-unproven renal neoplasms either treated with renal ablative procedures or followed on active surveillance</p>
<p class=&quot;Note&quot;><strong>Note</strong>: These guidelines are not meant to address hereditary or pediatric kidney cancers, although they must take into account that a proportion of adult patients may harbor a yet unrecognized hereditary form of renal cancer.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="132" ordby="430" id="402" name="Target Population" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Adults with of one of the following:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Clinically localized renal cancers treated with surgery or renal ablative procedures </li>
    <li>Biopsy-proven untreated clinically localized renal cancers followed on surveillance </li>
    <li>Radiographically suspicious but biopsy-unproven renal neoplasms either treated with renal ablative procedures or followed on active surveillance </li>
</ul></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="133" ordby="435" id="403" name="Interventions and Practices Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;>
    <li>Patient history and physical examination </li>
    <li>Laboratory testing
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Blood urea nitrogen (BUN)/creatinine </li>
        <li>Urine analysis (UA) </li>
        <li>Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) </li>
        <li>Complete blood count (CBC) </li>
        <li>Lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) </li>
        <li>Liver function tests (LFTs) </li>
        <li>Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) </li>
        <li>Calcium level </li>
    </ul>
    <p class=&quot;Note&quot;><strong>Note</strong>: Routine use of molecular markers, such as Ki-67, p-53, and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), was considered but not recommended</p>
    </li>
    <li>Referral to nephrology </li>
    <li>Imaging
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Abdominal computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), ultrasound (US) </li>
        <li>Bone scan </li>
        <li>Neurologic cross-sectional CT or MRI scanning of the head or spine, as indicated </li>
        <li>Chest x-ray (CXR) </li>
        <li>Site specific imaging (as indicated) </li>
    </ul>
    <p class=&quot;Note&quot;><strong>Note</strong>: The routine use of fludeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) is not recommended in the follow-up for renal cancer.</p>
    </li>
    <li>Percutaneous biopsy </li>
    <li>Surgery (nephron sparing, radical nephrectomy) </li>
    <li>Renal ablative procedures including percutaneous ablation </li>
</ol>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="134" ordby="440" id="404" name="Major Outcomes Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Sensitivity, specificity, and accuracy of diagnostic tests </li>
    <li>Incidence and rate of tumor growth </li>
    <li>Incidence and severity of renal impairment </li>
    <li>Incidence of:
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Local recurrence </li>
        <li>Secondary tumor </li>
    </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Metastasis </li>
    <li>Mortality </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="405" ordby="500" name="Methodology">
    <field fieldid="109" ordby="505" id="406" name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Searches of Electronic Databases"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="135" ordby="510" id="407" name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>A systematic review was conducted to identify published articles relevant to key questions specified by the Panel (see Appendix B [see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field]) related to kidney neoplasms and their follow-up (imaging, renal function, markers, biopsy, prognosis). The search of the PubMed, Embase and Cochrane databases covered articles in English published between January 1999 and 2011. An updated query was later conducted to include studies published through August 2012. Study designs consisting of clinical trials (randomized or not), observational studies (cohort, case-control, case series) and systematic reviews were included. All other study types were excluded. Studies with full-text publication available were included, but studies in abstract form only were excluded.</p>
<p>This literature included studies that focused on patients diagnosed with clinically localized, histologically proven renal cell carcinoma; clinically localized oncocytoma or cystic nephroma; radiographically suspicious, solid neoplasms or suspicious/complex cystic neoplasms without biopsy and neoplasms radiographically consistent with angiomyolipoma. Patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma, transitional cell carcinoma and hereditary syndromes as well as those treated with radiation or systemic therapy were excluded. Additionally, studies involving pediatric patients or those in which outcomes among qualifying index cases could not be separated from other cases or other malignancies were excluded as well. Management strategies considered include active surveillance, surgery (partial or radical nephrectomy) and ablative procedures (cryoablation or radiofrequency ablation). In terms of interventions, inclusion criteria incorporated studies involving follow-up regimens evaluating oncologic and functional outcomes using imaging and/or lab measurements and/or physical examination and/or biopsy. All other management strategies or treatment itself were excluded. Studies with less than 30 patients were excluded given the unreliability of the statistical estimates and conclusions that can be derived from them.</p>
<p>Articles with abstracts fulfilling the outlined inclusion criteria that addressed one or more of the posed questions were retrieved in full text for further review. Reason for exclusion of rejected articles was recorded. Studies reported within multiple publications were scrutinized in order to retrieve the most recent, non-redundant and inclusive data. Related references contained in each article were perused to ensure the inclusion of all pertinent material.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="136" ordby="515" id="408" name="Number of Source Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not stated</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="115" ordby="520" id="409" name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Expert Consensus (Delphi Method)"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="149" ordby="525" id="410" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>Body of Evidence Strength</strong></p>
<p>Overall quality scores together with study design and consistency of estimates across studies were used to grade the strength of the evidence into three levels: <strong>A (high)</strong>, <strong>B (moderate)</strong> or <strong>C (low)</strong>.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="116" ordby="530" id="411" name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Meta-Analysis"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Systematic Review"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="150" ordby="535" id="412" name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Accepted articles were extracted using customized forms. Given the pool size of eligible articles, independent double extraction was not possible for most articles. Instead, the methodologist reviewed the work of the extractors and searched for inconsistencies and missing information in the data extracted with emphasis on outcomes.</p>
<p>The methodological quality of the studies was evaluated using the Quality Assessment of Diagnostic Accuracy Studies (QUADAS) tool for questions framed in the context of a &quot;diagnostic&quot; problem. Many studies included retrospective cohorts reporting on the follow-up of patients. For these studies, the framework proposed by Hayden et al. was used to assess their methodological quality. This framework evaluates potential sources of bias within six domains: sample representativity, attrition, adequate measurement of prognostic factors, adequate measurement of outcomes, assessment and control of potential confounders and appropriate statistical analysis. This framework's implementation was adapted to the question context. Overall quality scores together with study design and consistency of estimates across studies were used to grade the strength of the evidence into three levels: A (strong), B (moderate) and C (weak).</p>
<p>Descriptive statistics of study characteristics were calculated to identify potential study outliers that could signal data extraction problems and/or influential studies. These were also used to identify factors that could explain heterogeneity of estimates, if found. Meta-analyses were performed on questions in which at least four studies were available. These estimates were based on DerSimonian-Laird random effects. Meta-regression was performed when heterogeneity was encountered and enough studies were available to examine at least one predictor at a time. Heterogeneity was considered present if the inconsistency I<sup>2</sup> statistic was above 25% or when the forest plot showed a potential mixture of outcomes if a small number of studies were available. Analyses were performed in the R platform version 2.12.0 for Windows and the code <em>meta</em>.</p>
<p>For most outcomes, a meta-analysis of proportions was performed. For these, raw counts for numerator and denominator were extracted from each study. The other meta-analyses were performed on the hazard rate (survival after surgery), hazard ratio (from multivariable Cox regression models) and area under the characteristic (AUC) curve and their corresponding standard error.</p>
<p>Hazard rates were obtained from survival rates at a minimum of five years, assuming that the curve exhibited an exponential distribution. The assumption of an exponential distribution could be confirmed graphically from a group of articles that provided corresponding survival curves. The resulting overall hazard rate was used to build a cumulative incidence function that covered five years of follow-up. The proportion of events in quarters for the first two years and biannually for the following three years were determined in order to guide the selection of an appropriate follow-up frequency for cases of clinically localized renal mass undergoing curative surgery without adjuvant or salvage treatment. Since partial and radical nephrectomy have been considered equivalent in terms of cancer control outcomes for T1 disease, these were included in the same analysis to increase the number of studies available.</p>
<p>The standard error was estimated from available data when it was not provided directly by the individual studies. In the case of survival curves, Kaplan-Meier curves with number of individuals at risk were transformed to their corresponding standard error. In the case of the AUC, actual numbers of individuals diseased and non-diseased and numbers of individuals labeled as diseased and non-diseased by a threshold were used for determining the standard error as proposed by Hanley and McNeil. AUC was used for assessing kidney function, and disease refers to patients with kidney insufficiency. When standard error was not available or could not be estimated the study was excluded from analysis.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="112" ordby="540" id="413" name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Expert Consensus"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Expert Consensus (Delphi)"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="145" ordby="545" id="414" name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The Follow-up for Clinically Localized Renal Neoplasms Panel was created by the American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA). The Practice Guidelines Committee (PGC) of the AUA selected the Panel Chair and Vice Chair who in turn appointed the additional panel members, all of whom have demonstrated a specific expertise with regard to the guideline subject. For some clinical issues, there was little or no evidence from which to construct evidence-based statements. Where gaps in the evidence existed, the Panel provides guidance in the form of Clinical Principles or Expert Opinions with consensus achieved using a modified Delphi technique if differences of opinion existed among Panel members.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="146" ordby="550" id="415" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>American Urological Association (AUA) Nomenclature Linking Statement Type to Evidence Strength</strong></p>
<p><strong>Standard</strong>: Directive statement that an action should (benefits outweigh risks/burdens) or should not (risks/burdens outweigh benefits) be taken based on Grade A or B evidence</p>
<p><strong>Recommendation</strong>: Directive statement that an action should (benefits outweigh risks/burdens) or should not (risks/burdens outweigh benefits) be taken based on Grade C evidence</p>
<p><strong>Option</strong>: Non-directive statement that leaves the decision regarding an action up to the individual clinician and patient because the balance between benefits and risks/burdens appears equal or appears uncertain based on Grade A, B, or C evidence</p>
<p><strong>Clinical Principle</strong>: A statement about a component of clinical care that is widely agreed upon by urologists or other clinicians for which there may or may not be evidence in the medical literature</p>
<p><strong>Expert Opinion</strong>: A statement, achieved by consensus of the Panel, that is based on members' clinical training, experience, knowledge, and judgment for which there is no evidence</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="148" ordby="565" id="417" name="Cost Analysis" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="104" ordby="570" id="418" name="Method of Guideline Validation" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Peer Review"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="130" ordby="575" id="419" name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA) conducted an extensive peer review process. The initial draft of this Guideline was distributed to 67 peer reviewers; 39 responded with comments. The Panel reviewed and discussed all submitted comments and revised the draft as needed. Once finalized, the Guideline was submitted for approval to the Practice Guidelines Committee (PGC). It was then submitted to the AUA Board of Directors for final approval.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="424" ordby="600" name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="139" ordby="610" id="426" name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The type of supporting evidence is identified and graded for most treatment recommendations (see the &quot;Major Recommendation&quot; field). Where evidence was lacking, recommendations are supported by expert opinion or consensus.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="427" ordby="700" name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="152" ordby="705" id="428" name="Potential Benefits" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Appropriate management of patients with clinically localized renal neoplasms</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="153" ordby="710" id="429" name="Potential Harms" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Despite the advantages of computed tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), the potential adverse effects and cost should also be kept in mind. Recent attention has been paid to the cumulative radiation exposure of the population attributable to the widespread and increasing use of CT scanning. There is some indirect evidence linking exposure to low-level ionizing radiation at doses used in CT to subsequent development of cancer. </li>
    <li>Although the true risk of cancer development from exposure to diagnostic radiation for a given individual from CT is not known, it is prudent to limit use of CT to those clinical indications in which the benefit is felt to outweigh the risk. In addition, risks related to administration of iodinated intravenous (IV) contrast for CT, including contrast hypersensitivity and contrast-induced renal failure, should also be kept in mind when considering the use of CT in the workup and follow-up of renal cancer. </li>
    <li>For MRI, which does not involve the use of ionizing radiation, the prime adverse effect to consider is the development of nephrogenic systemic fibrosis (NSF) due to IV gadolinium administration. </li>
    <li>Unless the diagnostic information is essential and not available with MRI performed without IV contrast, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) currently recommends against the use of gadolinium-based contrast agents in patients with acute or chronic renal insufficiency, with a glomerular filtration rate (GFR) less than 30 mL per minute per 1.73 m<sup>2</sup> or with any acute renal failure caused by the hepatorenal syndrome or perioperative liver transplantation. </li>
    <li>Patients should be counseled about the small but potential risk of cancer progression while on active surveillance, the potential loss of a window of opportunity for nephron-sparing surgery, the lack of curative salvage therapies if metastases develop and the deficiencies of the current data used to support this approach. </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="430" ordby="800" name="Contraindications">
    <field fieldid="144" ordby="805" id="431" name="Contraindications" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>In circumstances of declining renal function, contrast enhanced studies are contraindicated.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="432" ordby="900" name="Qualifying Statements">
    <field fieldid="137" ordby="905" id="433" name="Qualifying Statements" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>While these guidelines do not necessarily establish the standard of care, the American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA) seeks to recommend and to encourage compliance by practitioners with current best practices related to the condition being treated. As medical knowledge expands and technology advances, the guidelines will change. Today these evidence-based guidelines statements represent not absolute mandates but provisional proposals for treatment under the specific conditions described in each document. For all these reasons, the guidelines do not pre-empt physician judgment in individual cases. </li>
    <li>Treating physicians must take into account variations in resources, and patient tolerances, needs, and preferences. Conformance with any clinical guideline does not guarantee a successful outcome. The guideline text may include information or recommendations about certain drug uses (&quot;off label&quot;) that are not approved by the U. S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA), or about medications or substances not subject to the FDA approval process. AUA urges strict compliance with all government regulations and protocols for prescription and use of these substances. The physician is encouraged to carefully follow all available prescribing information about indications, contraindications, precautions and warnings. These guidelines and best practice statements are not in-tended to provide legal advice about use and misuse of these substances. </li>
    <li>Although guidelines are intended to encourage best practices and potentially encompass available technologies with sufficient data as of close of the literature review, they are necessarily time-limited. Guidelines cannot include evaluation of all data on emerging technologies or management, including those that are FDA-approved, which may immediately come to represent accepted clinical practices. </li>
    <li>For this reason, the AUA does not regard technologies or management which are too new to be addressed by this guideline as necessarily experimental or investigational. </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="434" ordby="1000" name="Implementation of the Guideline">
    <field fieldid="131" ordby="1010" id="436" name="Description of Implementation Strategy" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>An implementation strategy was not provided.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="117" ordby="1015" id="437" name="Implementation Tools" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Resources"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="439" ordby="1100" name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories">
    <field fieldid="50" ordby="1105" id="440" name="IOM Care Need" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Getting Better"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Living with Illness"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="51" ordby="1110" id="441" name="IOM Domain" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Effectiveness"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="442" ordby="1200" name="Identifying Information and Availability">
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="1201" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Donat SM, Diaz M, Bishoff JT, Coleman JA, Dahm P, Derweesh IH, Herrell SD III, Hilton S, Jonasch E, Lin DW, Reuter VE, Chang SS. Follow-up for clinically localized renal neoplasms: AUA guideline. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc.; 2013 Apr. 33 p.  [135 references]</td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="124" ordby="1205" id="443" name="Adaptation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="128" ordby="1215" id="445" name="Date Released" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="2013 Apr"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="158" ordby="1225" id="447" name="Guideline Developer(s)" type="orglist-p">
      <fieldvalue value="American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. - Medical Specialty Society"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="125" ordby="1235" id="449" name="Source(s) of Funding" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA)</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="126" ordby="1240" id="450" name="Guideline Committee" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Follow-up for Clinically Localized Renal Neoplasms Panel</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="127" ordby="1245" id="451" name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><em>Panel Members</em>: Sherri Machele Donat, MD, (<em>Chair</em>) Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, New York, NY; Sam S. Chang, MD, (<em>Vice-Chair</em>), Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, TN; Jay Todd Bishoff, MD, Intermountain Medical Group, Salt Lake City, UT; Jonathan A. Coleman, MD, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, New York, NY; Philipp Dahm MD, MHSc, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL; Ithaar H. Derweesh, MD, UCSD Moores Cancer, La Jolla, CA; S. Duke Herrell III, MD, Vanderbilt University Medical Center Nashville, TN; Susan Hilton, MD, Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania Philadelphia, PA; Eric Jonasch, MD; University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX; Daniel Wei Lin, MD, University of Washington, Seattle, WA; Victor Edward Reuter, MD, Memorial Sloan-Kettering&amp;ndash;Pathology, New York, NY</p>
<p><em>Consultants to the AUA</em>: Mieya Diaz, PhD</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="147" ordby="1250" id="452" name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Committee members received no remuneration for their work. All panel members completed conflict of interest (COI) disclosures. Relationships that have expired (more than one year old) since the panel's initial meeting, are listed. Those marked with (C) indicate that compensation was received; relationships designated by (U) indicate no compensation was received.</p>
<p><strong>Board Member, Officer or Trustee</strong>: <strong>Victor E. Reuter</strong>, United States and Canadian Academy of Pathology (U) (Expired)</p>
<p><strong>Consultant/Advisor</strong>: <strong>Sam S. Chang</strong>, Allergan (C) (Expired), Amgen (C) (Expired), Astellas (C), Centocor Ortho Biotech (C) (Expired), Dendreon (C), ENDO (C) (Expired), GE Health Services (C) (Expired), Predictive Biosciences (C), Sanofi-Aventis (C) (Expired), Janssen (C) (Expired); <strong>Jay Todd Bishoff</strong>, Perc Systems (C) (Expired); <strong>Jonathan Coleman</strong>, Endocare (C) (Expired); <strong>Ithaar H. Derweesh</strong>, Angiodynamics, Inc. (C) (Expired), Covidien, Inc. (C) (Expired), Cryolife, Inc. (C) (Expired), Ethicon Endo-Surgery, Inc. (C) (Expired), GlaxoSmithKline, Inc. (U); <strong>S. Duke Herrell</strong>, Aesculap Inc. (C), Covidien Surgical Devices (C) (Expired); <strong>Eric Jonasch</strong>, Aveo (C), Bayer Pharmaceuticals (C), Bristol Myers Squibb (C), Genentech (C), Glaxo Smith Kline (C), Novartis (C), Pfizer (C), Wyeth (C) (Expired); <strong>Daniel Lin</strong>, Caris Life Sciences (U) (Expired), Dendreon Corporation (C), GenProbe (U), Myriad (C), Pfizer (C)</p>
<p><strong>Meeting Participant or Lecturer</strong>: <strong>Sam S. Chang</strong>, Janssen (C); <strong>Jay Todd Bishoff</strong>, Pfizer (C) (Expired); <strong>Daniel Lin</strong>, Dendreon Corporation (C), Myriad (C)</p>
<p><strong>Investment Interest</strong>: <strong>S. Duke Herrell</strong>, Veran Medical Technologies (U)</p>
<p><strong>Scientific Study or Trial</strong>: <strong>Jay Todd Bishoff</strong>, Pfizer (C); <strong>Jonathan Coleman</strong>, Steba (U); <strong>Philipp Dahm</strong>, CureVac (C) (Expired); <strong>S. Duke Herrell</strong>, Galil Medical (C), Wilex (C) (Expired); <strong>Eric Jonasch</strong>, Aveo (C), Bristol Myers Squibb (C), Glaxo Smith Kline (C), Novartis (C), Pfizer (C) (Expired); <strong>Daniel Lin</strong>, Department of Defense (C), GenProbe (U), NIH/NCI (C), Veteran's Affairs (U)</p>
<p><strong>Other, Employee</strong>: <strong>Mireya Diaz</strong>, Henry Ford Hospital - Vattikuti Urology Institute (C)</p>
<p><strong>Other, Speaker's Bureau</strong>: <strong>Eric Jonasch</strong>, LWyeth (C) (Expired); Pfizer (C) (Expired)</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="1256" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="118" ordby="1260" id="454" name="Guideline Availability" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.auanet.org/guidelines/follow-up-for-clinically-localized-renal-neoplasms-(2013)&quot; title=&quot;American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA) Web site&quot;>American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA) Web site</a>.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="119" ordby="1265" id="455" name="Availability of Companion Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The following are available:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Follow-up for clinically localized renal neoplasms: AUA guideline. Appendix A: Follow-up Protocol Summary. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc.; 2013. 3 p. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.auanet.org/Documents/education/clinical-guidance/Renal-Cancer-Followup-Appendix-A.pdf&quot; title=&quot;American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA) Web site&quot;>American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA) Web site</a>. </li>
    <li>Follow-up for clinically localized renal neoplasms: AUA guideline. Appendices B-G. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc.; 2013. 13 p. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.auanet.org/Documents/education/clinical-guidance/Renal-Cancer-Followup-Appendix-B-G.pdf&quot; title=&quot;AUA Web site&quot;>AUA Web site</a>. </li>
</ul></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="143" ordby="1275" id="457" name="Patient Resources" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>None available</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="142" ordby="1280" id="458" name="NGC Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on August 15, 2013. The information was verified by the guideline developer on August 21, 2013.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="141" ordby="1290" id="460" name="Copyright Statement" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is copyrighted by the American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA).</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="99999" ordby="99999" name="Disclaimer">
    <field fieldid="99999" ordby="99999" id="99999" name="NGC Disclaimer" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<p>The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.</p> 
<p>All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.</p> 
<p>Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the <a href=&quot;/help-and-about/summaries/inclusion-criteria&quot;>NGC Inclusion Criteria</a>.</p> 
<p>NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.</p> 
<p>Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.</p>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
</version><!--
     FILE ARCHIVED ON 02:20:48 Jul 13, 2018 AND RETRIEVED FROM THE
     INTERNET ARCHIVE ON 00:57:13 Jul 16, 2018.
     JAVASCRIPT APPENDED BY WAYBACK MACHINE, COPYRIGHT INTERNET ARCHIVE.

     ALL OTHER CONTENT MAY ALSO BE PROTECTED BY COPYRIGHT (17 U.S.C.
     SECTION 108(a)(3)).
-->
<!--
playback timings (ms):
  LoadShardBlock: 133.702 (3)
  esindex: 0.01
  captures_list: 151.492
  CDXLines.iter: 13.032 (3)
  PetaboxLoader3.datanode: 145.887 (4)
  exclusion.robots: 0.396
  exclusion.robots.policy: 0.38
  RedisCDXSource: 0.718
  PetaboxLoader3.resolve: 148.37
  load_resource: 627.206
-->