<script src="//archive.org/includes/analytics.js?v=cf34f82" type="text/javascript"></script>
<script type="text/javascript">window.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded',function(){var v=archive_analytics.values;v.service='wb';v.server_name='wwwb-app17.us.archive.org';v.server_ms=440;archive_analytics.send_pageview({});});</script><script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/wbhack.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<script type="text/javascript">
__wbhack.init('https://web.archive.org/web');
</script>
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/banner-styles.css?v=1531166943.0" />
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/iconochive.css?v=1531166943.0" />

<!-- End Wayback Rewrite JS Include --><!-- BEGIN WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT -->
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/timestamp.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/graph-calc.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/auto-complete.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/toolbar.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<style type="text/css">
body {
  margin-top:0 !important;
  padding-top:0 !important;
  /*min-width:800px !important;*/
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestions {
    text-align: left; cursor: default; border: 1px solid #ccc; border-top: 0; background: #fff; box-shadow: -1px 1px 3px rgba(0,0,0,.1);
    position: absolute; display: none; z-index: 2147483647; max-height: 254px; overflow: hidden; overflow-y: auto; box-sizing: border-box;
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion { position: relative; padding: 0 .6em; line-height: 23px; white-space: nowrap; overflow: hidden; text-overflow: ellipsis; font-size: 1.02em; color: #333; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion b { font-weight: bold; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion.selected { background: #f0f0f0; }
</style>
<div id="wm-ipp" lang="en" style="display:none;direction:ltr;">
<div style="position:fixed;left:0;top:0;right:0;">
<div id="wm-ipp-inside">
  <div style="position:relative;">
    <div id="wm-logo" style="float:left;width:130px;padding-top:10px;">
      <a href="/web/" title="Wayback Machine home page"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wayback-toolbar-logo.png" alt="Wayback Machine" width="110" height="39" border="0" /></a>
    </div>
    <div class="r" style="float:right;">
      <div id="wm-btns" style="text-align:right;height:25px;">
                  <div id="wm-save-snapshot-success">success</div>
          <div id="wm-save-snapshot-fail">fail</div>
          <a href="#"
             onclick="__wm.saveSnapshot('https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-11009?contentType=xml', '20180712231348')"
             title="Share via My Web Archive"
             id="wm-save-snapshot-open"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-web"></span>
          </a>
          <a href="https://archive.org/account/login.php"
             title="Sign In"
             id="wm-sign-in"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-person"></span>
          </a>
          <span id="wm-save-snapshot-in-progress" class="iconochive-web"></span>
        	<a href="http://faq.web.archive.org/" title="Get some help using the Wayback Machine" style="top:-6px;"><span class="iconochive-question" style="color:rgb(87,186,244);font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a id="wm-tb-close" href="#close" onclick="__wm.h(event);return false;" style="top:-2px;" title="Close the toolbar"><span class="iconochive-remove-circle" style="color:#888888;font-size:240%;"></span></a>
      </div>
      <div id="wm-share" style="text-align:right;">
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://web.archive.org/web/20180712231348/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-11009?contentType=xml', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Facebook" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-facebook" style="color:#3b5998;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=https://web.archive.org/web/20180712231348/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-11009?contentType=xml&amp;via=internetarchive', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Twitter" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-twitter" style="color:#1dcaff;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
      </div>
    </div>
    <table class="c" style="">
      <tbody>
	<tr>
	  <td class="u" colspan="2">
	    <form target="_top" method="get" action="/web/submit" name="wmtb" id="wmtb"><input type="text" name="url" id="wmtbURL" value="https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-11009?contentType=xml" onfocus="this.focus();this.select();" /><input type="hidden" name="type" value="replay" /><input type="hidden" name="date" value="20180712231348" /><input type="submit" value="Go" /></form>
	  </td>
	  <td class="n" rowspan="2" style="width:110px;">
	    <table>
	      <tbody>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV MONTH NAV AND MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="m">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180610061026/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-11009?contentType=xml" title="10 Jun 2018"><strong>Jun</strong></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayMonthEl" title="You are here: 23:13:48 Jul 12, 2018">JUL</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">Aug</td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV CAPTURE NAV AND DAY OF MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="d">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180610061026/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-11009?contentType=xml" title="06:10:26 Jun 10, 2018"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_prv_on.png" alt="Previous capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayDayEl" style="width:34px;font-size:24px;white-space:nowrap;" title="You are here: 23:13:48 Jul 12, 2018">12</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_nxt_off.png" alt="Next capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV YEAR NAV AND YEAR INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="y">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap">2017</td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayYearEl" title="You are here: 23:13:48 Jul 12, 2018">2018</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">2019</td>
		</tr>
	      </tbody>
	    </table>
	  </td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td class="s">
	    	    <div id="wm-nav-captures">
	      	      <a class="t" href="/web/20180712231348*/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-11009?contentType=xml" title="See a list of every capture for this URL">5 captures</a>
	      <div class="r" title="Timespan for captures of this URL">02 Oct 2017 - 12 Jul 2018</div>
	      </div>
	  </td>
	  <td class="k">
	    <a href="" id="wm-graph-anchor">
	      <div id="wm-ipp-sparkline" title="Explore captures for this URL" style="position: relative">
		<canvas id="wm-sparkline-canvas" width="575" height="27" border="0"></canvas>
	      </div>
	    </a>
	  </td>
	</tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <div style="position:absolute;bottom:0;right:2px;text-align:right;">
      <a id="wm-expand" class="wm-btn wm-closed" href="#expand" onclick="__wm.ex(event);return false;"><span id="wm-expand-icon" class="iconochive-down-solid"></span> <span style="font-size:80%">About this capture</span></a>
    </div>
  </div>
    <div id="wm-capinfo" style="border-top:1px solid #777;display:none; overflow: hidden">
            <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center">COLLECTED BY</div>
    <div style="padding:3px;position:relative" id="wm-collected-by-content">
            <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:50%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/archiveteam);"></span>
		Organization: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/archiveteam" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">Archive Team</span></a>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  <img align=right src="http://archiveteam.org/images/e/e6/Archiveteam.jpg" width=200> Formed in 2009, the Archive Team (not to be confused with the archive.org Archive-It Team) is a rogue archivist collective dedicated to saving copies of rapidly dying or deleted websites for the sake of history and digital heritage. The group is 100% composed of volunteers and interested parties, and has expanded into a large amount of related projects for saving online and digital history.
<p>
History is littered with hundreds of conflicts over the future of a community, group, location or business that were "resolved" when one of the parties stepped ahead and destroyed what was there. With the original point of contention destroyed, the debates would fall to the wayside. Archive Team believes that by duplicated condemned data, the conversation and debate can continue, as well as the richness and insight gained by keeping the materials. Our projects have ranged in size from a single volunteer downloading the data to a small-but-critical site, to over 100 volunteers stepping forward to acquire terabytes of user-created data to save for future generations.
<p>
The main site for Archive Team is at <a href="http://www.archiveteam.org">archiveteam.org</a> and contains up to the date information on various projects, manifestos, plans and walkthroughs.
<p>
This collection contains the output of many Archive Team projects, both ongoing and completed. Thanks to the generous providing of disk space by the Internet Archive, multi-terabyte datasets can be made available, as well as in use by the <a href="http://archive.org/web/web.php">Wayback Machine</a>, providing a path back to lost websites and work. 
<p>
Our collection has grown to the point of having sub-collections for the type of data we acquire. If you are seeking to browse the contents of these collections, the Wayback Machine is the best first stop. Otherwise, you are free to dig into the stacks to see what you may find.
<p>
<b>The Archive Team Panic Downloads</b> are full pulldowns of currently extant websites, meant to serve as emergency backups for needed sites that are in danger of closing, or which will be missed dearly if suddenly lost due to hard drive crashes or server failures. 
<p>
	</div>
	      </div>
      <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:49%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/archivebot)"></span>
		<div>Collection: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/archivebot" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">ArchiveBot: The Archive Team Crowdsourced Crawler</span></a></div>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  ArchiveBot is an IRC bot designed to automate the archival of smaller websites (e.g. up to a few hundred thousand URLs). You give it a URL to start at, and it grabs all content under that URL, records it in a WARC, and then uploads that WARC to ArchiveTeam servers for eventual injection into the Internet Archive (or other archive sites).
<p>
To use ArchiveBot, drop by #archivebot on EFNet. To interact with ArchiveBot, you issue commands by typing it into the channel. Note you will need channel operator permissions in order to issue archiving jobs. The dashboard shows the sites being downloaded currently.
<p>
There is a dashboard running for the archivebot process at <a href="http://www.archivebot.com">http://www.archivebot.com</a>.
<p>
ArchiveBot's source code can be found at <a href="https://github.com/ArchiveTeam/ArchiveBot">https://github.com/ArchiveTeam/ArchiveBot</a>.
	</div>
	      </div>
    </div>
    <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center" title="Timestamps for the elements of this page">TIMESTAMPS</div>
    <div>
      <div id="wm-capresources" style="margin:0 5px 5px 5px;max-height:250px;overflow-y:scroll !important"></div>
      <div id="wm-capresources-loading" style="text-align:left;margin:0 20px 5px 5px;display:none"><img src="/static/images/loading.gif" alt="loading" /></div>
    </div>
  </div></div></div></div><script type="text/javascript">
__wm.bt(575,27,25,2,"web","https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-11009?contentType=xml","2018-07-12",1996);
</script>
<!-- END WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT --><version>
  <xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource>
  <section secid="390" ordby="100" name="General">
    <field fieldid="161" ordby="105" id="391" name="Guideline Title" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_title&quot;>Selection of optimal adjuvant chemotherapy regimens for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative and adjuvant targeted therapy for HER2-positive breast cancers: an American Society of Clinical Oncology guideline adaptation of the Cancer Care Ontario clinical practice guideline.</div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="110" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Denduluri N, Somerfield MR, Eisen A, Holloway JN, Hurria A, King TA, Lyman GH, Partridge AH, Telli ML, Trudeau ME, Wolff AC. Selection of optimal adjuvant chemotherapy regimens for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative and adjuvant targeted therapy for HER2-positive breast cancers: an American Society of Clinical Oncology guideline adaptation of the Cancer Care Ontario clinical practice guideline. J Clin Oncol. 2016 Jul 10;34(20):2416-27. [32 references] <a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=27091714&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;>PubMed</a></td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="115" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p>
<p>This guideline meets NGC's 2013 (revised) inclusion criteria.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="420" ordby="300" name="Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="151" ordby="310" id="421" name="Major Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The following sections present the recommendations adapted from the Cancer Care Ontario (CCO) Program in Evidence-based Care guideline on optimal systemic therapy for early female breast cancer. Recommendations identified by an asterisk are taken verbatim from the CCO guideline. Otherwise, recommendations have been substantively adapted or reworded for clarity by the American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Panel.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Recommendations for Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor 2 (HER2)-Negative Breast Cancer</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>Use of an Anthracycline-Taxane Regimen</strong></p>
<p>In patients who can tolerate it, use of a regimen containing anthracycline-taxane is considered the optimal strategy for adjuvant chemotherapy, particularly for patients deemed to be at high risk.*</p>
<p><strong>Optimal-Dose Anthracycline Regimen for Patients with High-Risk Breast Cancer Who Will Not Receive a Taxane</strong></p>
<p>For patients with high-risk disease who will not receive a taxane, an optimal-dose anthracycline three-drug regimen (cumulative dose of doxorubicin &amp;ge;240 mg/m<sup>2</sup> or epirubicin &amp;ge;600 mg/m<sup>2</sup> but no higher than 720 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) that contains cyclophosphamide is recommended. The cumulative dose of doxorubicin in two-drug regimens should not exceed 240 mg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>The Oxford Overview showed that anthracycline-based three-drug regimens, such as six cycles of cyclophosphamide-doxorubicin-fluorouracil (300 mg/m<sup>2</sup> of doxorubicin) or cyclophosphamide-epirubicin-fluorouracil (&amp;ge;360 mg/m<sup>2</sup> of epirubicin), were superior to cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil. However, studies of anthracycline-based two-drug regimens (versus single-agent paclitaxel) testing a cumulative dose of doxorubicin of more than 240 mg/m<sup>2</sup> in the form of doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide given for six cycles instead of four cycles or for four cycles with a doxorubicin dose of more than 60 mg/m<sup>2</sup> per cycle demonstrated greater toxicity and no improvement in survival. In light of these data, the ASCO Panel modified the CCO recommendation to indicate that the cumulative dose of doxorubicin in two-drug regimens should not exceed 240 mg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p><strong>Adding Gemcitabine or Capecitabine to an Anthracycline-Taxane Regimen</strong></p>
<p>The addition of gemcitabine or capecitabine to an anthracycline-taxane regimen is not recommended for adjuvant chemotherapy.*</p>
<p><strong>Capecitabine in Patients Age 65 Years or Older</strong></p>
<p>In patients age 65 years or older, capecitabine is not recommended as an adjuvant chemotherapy option in lieu of standard regimens such as doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide or cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil (oral cyclophosphamide).</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>The ASCO Panel modified the CCO recommendation to reflect that patients in the clinical trial reported by Muss et al. were age 65 years or older.</p>
<p><strong>Cyclophosphamide-Methotrexate-Fluorouracil as an Alternative to Doxorubicin-Cyclophosphamide</strong></p>
<p>For patients in whom anthracycline-taxane is contraindicated, cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil (with oral cyclophosphamide) is an acceptable chemotherapy alternative to doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide. Of note, the ASCO Panel recommends classic cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil (oral cyclophosphamide days 1 to 14 with intravenous [IV] methotrexate-fluorouracil days 1 and 8, repeated once every 28 days for six cycles) as the default adjuvant cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil regimen. However, the Panel also recognizes that an all-IV cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil regimen once every 21 days is often used in clinical practice and was accepted by some clinical trials (e.g., TAILORx [Trial Assigning Individualized Options for Treatment (Rx)]) on the basis of convenience and tolerability despite the absence of efficacy data from randomized controlled trials.</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>In the Oxford Overview, trials that had controls treated with cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil showed that standard doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 once every 3 weeks and standard cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil were equivalent. However, single-agent taxane regimens such as paclitaxel given for four or six cycles are not acceptable alternatives because they were not shown to be not inferior to doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide. The ASCO Panel modified the CCO recommendation to include a comment on the use of an all-IV cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil regimen.</p>
<p><strong>Acceptable Adjuvant Chemotherapy Regimens for Patients with Higher-Risk Early-Stage Breast Cancer</strong></p>
<p>These adjuvant chemotherapy regimens can be used for patients with higher-risk early-stage breast cancer (see also the next recommendation regarding non-anthracycline regimens):</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Fluorouracil-epirubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 3 &amp;rarr; docetaxel &amp;times; 3 (superior to fluorouracil-epirubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 6) </li>
    <li>Doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 &amp;rarr; docetaxel &amp;times; 4 (superior to doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide x 4) </li>
    <li>Docetaxel-doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 6 (superior to fluorouracil-doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 6) </li>
    <li>Doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 &amp;rarr; paclitaxel administered once per week </li>
    <li>Dose-dense doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;rarr; paclitaxel (once every 2 weeks) </li>
</ul>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>The ASCO Panel modified the CCO list of acceptable adjuvant chemotherapy regimens to remove the &quot;dose-dense, dose-intense epirubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;rarr; paclitaxel&quot; regimen because of higher toxicity and lack of overall survival benefit.</p>
<p><strong>Adjuvant Regimen When an Anthracycline Is Not Preferred</strong></p>
<p>Docetaxel-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 is recommended as an alternative to doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4. Docetaxel-cyclophosphamide offers improved disease-free survival (DFS) and overall survival (OS) compared with four cycles of doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide. Classic cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil with cyclophosphamide for six cycles is another option. Of note, the ASCO Panel recommends classic cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil (oral cyclophosphamide days 1 to 14 with IV methotrexate-fluorouracil days 1 and 8, repeated once every 28 days for six cycles) as the default adjuvant cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil regimen. However, the Panel also recognizes that an all-IV cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil regimen once every 21 days is often used in clinical practice and was accepted by some clinical trials (e.g., TAILORx) on the basis of convenience and tolerability despite the absence of efficacy data from randomized controlled trials.</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>The US Oncology Trial 9735 showed that docetaxel-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 offers improved DFS and OS when compared with doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4. However, docetaxel-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 is associated with a higher risk of infection, and use of granulocyte colony-stimulating factor is recommended. Docetaxel-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 has not been compared against an anthracycline and taxane regimen (in sequence or in combination). Ongoing trials NCT00493870 (Phase III Trial of Taxotere [Docetaxel]-Cytoxan [Cyclophosphamide] [TC] versus taxotere-doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide [TAC] in HER2-Negative Early Stage Breast Cancer Patients), NCT01547741 (Docetaxel and Cyclophosphamide Compared to Anthracycline-Based Chemotherapy in Treating Women with HER2-Negative Breast Cancer), and NCT00887536 (A Clinical Trial Comparing the Combination of TC Plus Bevacizumab to TC Alone and to TAC for Women with Node-Positive or High-Risk Node-Negative, HER2-Negative Breast Cancer) are testing the efficacy (and safety) of docetaxel-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; six cycles versus three-drug anthracycline- and taxane-containing regimens in high-risk HER2-negative, node-negative or node-positive breast cancer.</p>
<p>The ASCO Panel modified the CCO recommendation to specify that docetaxel-cyclophosphamide should be administered for four cycles and added the statement to the recommendation that, on the basis of the Oxford Overview, cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil for six cycles offers &quot;equivalent&quot; outcomes and is an alternative to doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide once every 3 weeks &amp;times; 4. The ASCO Panel also modified the CCO recommendation to include a comment on the use of an all-IV cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil regimen.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Recommendations for HER2-Positive Breast Cancer</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>Patient Selection and Adjuvant Trastuzumab Therapy</strong></p>
<p>Only patients with HER2-positive breast cancer (overexpressed based on immunohistochemistry [3+] or amplified based on in situ hybridization [ratio &amp;ge;2.0 or average <em>HER2</em> copy number &amp;ge;6.0]) should be offered adjuvant trastuzumab.</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>The ASCO Panel modified the CCO patient selection recommendation slightly from CCO's original language of &quot;6+ HER2 gene copies per cell nucleus&quot; to make this one criterion consistent with the ASCO-College of American Pathologists guideline definition of &quot;positive for HER2&quot; as an average <em>HER2</em> gene copy number of &amp;ge;6.0 per cell nucleus.</p>
<p><strong>Trastuzumab Plus Chemotherapy in Patients with Higher-Risk HER2-Positive</strong></p>
<p>Trastuzumab plus chemotherapy is recommended for all patients with HER2-positive, node-positive breast cancer and for patients with HER2-positive, node-negative breast cancer tumors (&amp;ge;1 cm).*</p>
<p><strong>Trastuzumab Plus Chemotherapy in Patients with HER2-Positive T1a-b N0 Disease</strong></p>
<p>Trastuzumab plus chemotherapy may be considered in small (&amp;le;1 cm), node-negative tumors.</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>The ASCO Panel adapted the CCO recommendation in light of data published since completion of the CCO guideline to make the recommendation more definitive regarding the use of trastuzumab plus chemotherapy in patients with small, node-negative tumors. There are limited phase III data on the efficacy of trastuzumab in patients with small (&amp;le;1 cm), node-negative tumors. In a recent meta-analysis of five of six randomized trials that evaluated the benefit of trastuzumab in tumors &amp;le;2 cm, only 75 patients had T1a-b node-negative disease, but the proportional benefit offered by adjuvant trastuzumab seemed to be the same regardless of tumor size or node status. Two single-arm phase II trials in the node-negative, HER2-positive population suggest an excellent short-term outcome for patients treated with trastuzumab and paclitaxel (49.5% had T1b disease or smaller; two-thirds had estrogen receptor [ER]-positive disease) or with trastuzumab and docetaxel-cyclophosphamide (21.7% of patients had T1b disease or smaller; 64.9% had ER-positive disease). Although data from these single-arm studies are encouraging, they do not support a blanket recommendation for the use of trastuzumab-based chemotherapy for all patients with T1N0 HER2-positive tumors. Historical outcomes suggest excellent outcomes for some patients with T1a-b HER2-positive tumors that were not treated with trastuzumab, particularly those with ER-positive disease treated with optimal endocrine therapy. Therefore, the decision to offer trastuzumab-based chemotherapy for patients with small, node-negative tumors needs to be individualized.</p>
<p><strong>Selection of Chemotherapy Regimens in Patients Receiving Trastuzumab</strong></p>
<p>Trastuzumab can be administered with any acceptable adjuvant chemotherapy regimen.*</p>
<p><strong>Use of Trastuzumab and an Anthracycline-Containing Regimen</strong></p>
<p>The administration of trastuzumab concurrently with the anthracycline component of a chemotherapy regimen is not recommended because of the potential for increased cardiotoxicity.</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>Because of a lack of clinical outcomes benefit and increased cardiotoxicity, concurrent administration of anthracyclines and trastuzumab is not recommended; the ASCO Panel adapted the CCO recommendation to omit the word &quot;generally&quot; from the CCO recommendation.</p>
<p><strong>Concurrent Administration of Adjuvant Trastuzumab and Non-Anthracycline Chemotherapy Regimens</strong></p>
<p>Trastuzumab should be preferentially administered concurrently (not sequentially) with a non-anthracycline chemotherapy regimen.</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>On the basis of data from North Central Cancer Treatment Group NCCTG-N9831 (Combination Chemotherapy with or without Trastuzumab in Treating Women with HER2-Overexpressing Breast Cancer) trial and on informal panel consensus, the ASCO Panel adapted the CCO recommendation to indicate a preference for concurrent versus sequential administration of trastuzumab and non-anthracycline chemotherapy. One study reported a strong trend toward improved DFS with initiation of trastuzumab concurrent with taxane chemotherapy compared with the sequential administration of taxane followed by trastuzumab once per week for 52 weeks (hazard ratio, 0.77; 99.9% confidence interval [CI], 0.53 to 1.11).</p>
<p><strong>Trastuzumab-Based Chemotherapy/Trastuzumab Regimens for Patients at Higher Risk of Cardiotoxicity</strong></p>
<p>Less cardiotoxicity is seen with docetaxel-carboplatin-trastuzumab than with doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide followed by docetaxel-trastuzumab, and docetaxel-carboplatin-trastuzumab is recommended for patients at higher risk for cardiotoxicity.*</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>Although the efficacy of docetaxel-carboplatin-trastuzumab was not directly tested against doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide followed by docetaxel-trastuzumab in the Breast Cancer International Research Group (BCIRG) 006 (Combination Chemotherapy with or without Trastuzumab in Treating Women with Breast Cancer) trial, lower rates of cardiotoxicity were observed with docetaxel-carboplatin-trastuzumab. These data support preferential use of docetaxel-carboplatin-trastuzumab, particularly for patients who might be at greater risk for cardiac dysfunction, on the basis of factors such as older age, low baseline ejection fraction, and pre-existing hypertension. Of note, BCIRG 006 did not include patients older than age 70 years. Another option for patients with lower-risk node-negative disease who might have a higher risk for cardiotoxicity is trastuzumab-paclitaxel once per week followed by trastuzumab alone on the basis of a single-arm phase II trial in which rates of symptomatic heart failure were low and the observed asymptomatic decreases in ejection fraction improved with trastuzumab interruption and/or cessation.</p>
<p><strong>Addition of Trastuzumab to Chemotherapy Regimens Not Evaluated in a Phase III Trial</strong></p>
<p>No phase III evidence exists for the addition of trastuzumab to some chemotherapy regimens, such as docetaxel-cyclophosphamide. However, those regimens might be in use and are reasonable options, particularly to mitigate cardiotoxicity in certain patients.*</p>
<p><em>ASCO Panel Rationale and Discussion</em></p>
<p>Since publication of the CCO guideline, data from two phase II studies have assessed the concomitant administration of taxanes and trastuzumab. The APT (Adjuvant Paclitaxel and Trastuzumab) trial of paclitaxel-trastuzumab once per week for 12 weeks followed by trastuzumab reported excellent short-term (3-year) DFS of 98.7% in a node-negative, lower-risk HER2-positive population. Another phase II study that assessed the concomitant administration of four cycles of docetaxel-cyclophosphamide with trastuzumab followed by trastuzumab alone reported a 3-year DFS of 96.9% for women with early-stage HER2-amplified breast cancer. Given data from these phase II trials and data from the HERA (Herceptin Adjuvant Trial) trial, in which systemic therapy was given per investigator choice, paclitaxel, docetaxel-cyclophosphamide, or any of the regimens used in HERA can be considered a reasonable systemic option in combination with trastuzumab, particularly for patients who are perceived to be at increased risk for cardiotoxicity.</p>
<p><strong>Duration of Trastuzumab Therapy and Cardiac Function Assessment</strong></p>
<p>Patients should be offered 1 year total of adjuvant trastuzumab, with regular assessments of cardiac function during that period.*</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="138" ordby="330" id="423" name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>None provided</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="396" ordby="400" name="Scope">
    <field fieldid="140" ordby="405" id="397" name="Disease/Condition(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Early invasive breast cancer, including human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-positive and HER2-negative breast cancers</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="103" ordby="410" id="398" name="Guideline Category" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Management"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Risk Assessment"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Treatment"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="113" ordby="415" id="399" name="Clinical Specialty" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Oncology"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Pathology"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="114" ordby="420" id="400" name="Intended Users" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Advanced Practice Nurses"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Nurses"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Patients"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Physician Assistants"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Physicians"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="129" ordby="425" id="401" name="Guideline Objective(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>To present practice recommendations adapted from the Cancer Care Ontario (CCO) Program in Evidence-based Care guideline on the selection of optimal adjuvant chemotherapy regimens for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative and adjuvant targeted therapy for HER2-positive breast cancers</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="132" ordby="430" id="402" name="Target Population" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Female patients who are being considered for, or who are receiving, systemic therapy after definitive surgery for early-stage invasive breast cancer, defined largely as invasive cancer stages I to IIA (T1N0-1, T2N0)</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="133" ordby="435" id="403" name="Interventions and Practices Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;>
    <li>Adjuvant chemotherapy for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative cancers
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Use of an anthracycline-taxane regimen </li>
        <li>Optimal-dose anthracycline regimen for patients with high-risk breast cancer who will not receive a taxane </li>
        <li>Adding gemcitabine or capecitabine to an anthracycline-taxane regimen (not recommended) </li>
        <li>Capecitabine in patients 65 years of age and older (not recommended as an adjuvant chemotherapy option in lieu of standard regimens) </li>
        <li>Cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil (CMF) as an alternative to doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide (AC) </li>
        <li>Acceptable adjuvant chemotherapy regimens for patients with higher risk early-stage breast cancer
        <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
            <li>Fluorouracil-epirubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 3 &amp;rarr; docetaxel &amp;times; 3 </li>
            <li>Doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 &amp;rarr; docetaxel &amp;times; 4 </li>
            <li>Docetaxel-doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 6 </li>
            <li>Doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 &amp;rarr; paclitaxel administered once per week </li>
            <li>Dose-dense doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide &amp;rarr; paclitaxel (once every 2 weeks) </li>
        </ul>
        </li>
        <li>Adjuvant regimen when an anthracycline is not preferred
        <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
            <li>Docetaxel-cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 4 </li>
            <li>Cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil with oral cyclophosphamide &amp;times; 6 </li>
            <li>Use of an all-intravenous (IV) cyclophosphamide-methotrexate-fluorouracil regimen </li>
        </ul>
        </li>
    </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Adjuvant targeted therapy for HER2-positive cancers
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Patient selection and adjuvant trastuzumab therapy </li>
        <li>Trastuzumab plus chemotherapy in patients with higher risk HER2-positive disease </li>
        <li>Trastuzumab plus chemotherapy in patients with HER2-positive disease if T1a/b N0 </li>
        <li>Selection of chemotherapy regimens in patients receiving trastuzumab </li>
        <li>Use of trastuzumab and an anthracycline-containing regimen (not recommended) </li>
        <li>Concurrent administration of adjuvant trastuzumab and non-anthracycline chemotherapy regimens </li>
        <li>Trastuzumab-based chemotherapy-trastuzumab regimens for patients at higher risk of cardiotoxicity (docetaxel-carboplatin-trastuzumab) </li>
        <li>Addition of trastuzumab to chemotherapy regimens not evaluated in a phase III trial </li>
        <li>Duration of trastuzumab therapy and cardiac function assessment </li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ol>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="134" ordby="440" id="404" name="Major Outcomes Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Disease-free survival (DFS) </li>
    <li>Overall survival (OS) </li>
    <li>Adverse effects of treatment </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="405" ordby="500" name="Methodology">
    <field fieldid="109" ordby="505" id="406" name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Searches of Electronic Databases"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="135" ordby="510" id="407" name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The adaptation process usually starts with a literature search to identify candidate guidelines for adaptation on a given topic. For this adaptation, however, the target guideline was identified through an informal collaboration between the Cancer Care Ontario (CCO) Program in Evidence-based Care and the American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) guidelines program, which is designed to reduce duplication of effort in oncology practice guideline development across organizations. As part of this collaboration, CCO guidelines staff made ASCO aware that CCO's comprehensive practice guideline on optimal systemic therapy for early breast cancer in women was nearing completion.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Summary of the CCO Guideline Development Methodology</span></strong></p>
<p>CCO guideline recommendations were developed by a panel that included experts in medical oncology. The literature searches of MEDLINE and EMBASE that were completed for the broad systematic review spanned the period from January 2008 through March 2012; the search was updated in May 2014. Additional practice guidelines were identified from a search of the SAGE Directory of Cancer Guidelines. Details of the search strategies, the study inclusion criteria, the outcomes of interest, and the search yield are available at the CCO Web site at <a href=&quot;https://www.cancercare.on.ca/toolbox/qualityguidelines/diseasesite/breast-ebs&quot; title=&quot;CCO Web site&quot;>https://www.cancercare.on.ca/toolbox/qualityguidelines/diseasesite/breast-ebs</a>.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Methods and Results of ASCO Updated Literature Search</span></strong></p>
<p>A search for new evidence was conducted by ASCO guidelines staff to identify relevant randomized controlled trials, systematic reviews, and meta-analyses published since the CCO guideline was completed. MEDLINE and EMBASE were searched from January 2014 to July 2015 by following the strategies described in the CCO guideline. The search was restricted to articles published in English and to systematic reviews, meta-analyses, and randomized controlled trials. The CCO guideline inclusion criteria were applied to a review of the literature search results. The updated search and review were guided by the signals approach, which is designed to identify only new, potentially practice-changing data&amp;mdash;signals that might translate into revised practice recommendations. This approach relied on targeted routine literature searching and the expertise of ASCO Guideline Panel members to help identify potential signals. Panel members also provided additional relevant references from personal files. The Methodology Supplement (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field) provides additional information about the signals approach. The updated search yielded 4,018 records.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="136" ordby="515" id="408" name="Number of Source Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>From the 4018 records, 20 potentially relevant abstracts were identified. None of the publications provided new evidence that would warrant substantive modification of the Cancer Care Ontario (CCO) practice recommendations. Two of the publications informed the American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Panel's comments, and are referenced in the guideline manuscript.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="115" ordby="520" id="409" name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Not stated"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="149" ordby="525" id="410" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not applicable</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="116" ordby="530" id="411" name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Systematic Review"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="150" ordby="535" id="412" name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Methodologic review of the comprehensive Cancer Care Ontario (CCO) guideline on optimal systemic therapy was completed independently by two American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) guideline staff members using the Rigour of Development subscale from the Appraisal of Guidelines for Research and Evaluation II (AGREE II) instrument. Detailed results of the scoring for these assessments are available in the Methodology Supplement (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). Overall, the more comprehensive CCO guideline scored 98% in rigor of guideline development.</p>
<p>The content review is completed by an Adaptation Panel convened by ASCO that includes multidisciplinary representation. The Panel members are asked to complete an eight item Guideline Endorsement Content Review Form (see Figure 2 in the Methodology Supplement) that assesses the perceived clarity and clinical utility of the recommendations, and the degree to which the recommendations are consistent with the content reviewers' interpretation of the available data on the topic in question. This form was adapted by ASCO from the Cancer Care Ontario Program in Evidence-based Care Practitioner Feedback instrument.</p>
<p>The Adaptation Panel is led by two Co-Chairs who have the primary responsibility for the development and timely completion of the guideline adaptation. Recommendations from the source guidelines are extracted into a summary matrix.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="112" ordby="540" id="413" name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Expert Consensus (Delphi)"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="145" ordby="545" id="414" name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Summary of the Cancer Care Ontario (CCO) Guideline Development Methodology</span></strong></p>
<p>A working group composed of six medical oncologists and a methodologist drafted guideline recommendations. These draft recommendations were subsequently circulated to the Early Breast Cancer Systemic Therapy Consensus Panel, which included the working group members and 14 additional medical oncologists from Ontario as part of a modified Delphi consensus development technique for which consensus was defined as 80% agreement and no strong disagreement. By using a 5-point point Likert scale (strongly disagree to strongly agree), Consensus Panel members from CCO rated the draft recommendations in advance of a consensus meeting held in November 2012. Selected recommendations for which consensus was not achieved were discussed and voted on at the 2012 consensus meeting.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>The American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Guideline Adaptation Process</span></strong></p>
<p>This guideline adaptation was informed by the ADAPTE methodology, which was used as an alternative to de novo guideline development. Adaptation of guidelines is considered by ASCO in selected circumstances, when one or more quality guidelines on the same topic from other organizations already exist. The objective of the ADAPTE process (<a href=&quot;http://www.g-i-n.net/working-groups/adaptation&quot; title=&quot;G-I-N Web site&quot;>http://www.g-i-n.net/working-groups/adaptation</a>) is to take advantage of existing guidelines to enhance efficient production, reduce duplication, and promote the local uptake of quality guideline recommendations.</p>
<p>ASCO's adaptation process typically begins with a literature search to identify candidate guidelines for adaptation. Adapted guideline manuscripts are reviewed and approved by the ASCO Clinical Practice Guidelines Committee (CPGC). The review includes two parts: methodologic review and content review. The methodologic review is completed by a member of the Clinical Practice Guidelines Committee's Methodology Subcommittee and/or by ASCO senior guideline staff. The content review is completed by an ad hoc panel convened by ASCO that includes representatives of several disciplines. Further details of the methods used for the development of this guideline adaptation are reported in Methodology Supplement (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Results of Guideline Search and ASCO Topic Priority-Setting Process</span></strong></p>
<p>On the basis of a preliminary content review of the draft CCO guideline by two members of ASCO's Breast Cancer Advisory Group, the CCO recommendations on the selection of optimal adjuvant chemotherapy regimens and the selection of adjuvant targeted therapy for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-positive cancers were selected as a possible adaptation opportunity. The Advisory Group subsequently ranked the adaptation of the CCO recommendations on chemotherapy and targeted therapy as one of its top three priorities for breast cancer guideline development.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Final Recommendations</span></strong></p>
<p>On the basis of a formal content review of the CCO guideline, the ASCO Panel agreed that, in general, the recommendations were clear and thorough, were based on the most relevant scientific evidence, and presented options that will be acceptable to patients. However, for some topics, the ASCO Panel formulated a set of adapted recommendations on the basis of local context and practice beliefs of the ad hoc panel members and new information.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="146" ordby="550" id="415" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not applicable</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="148" ordby="565" id="417" name="Cost Analysis" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="104" ordby="570" id="418" name="Method of Guideline Validation" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Internal Peer Review"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="130" ordby="575" id="419" name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Final review and approval are completed by the American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Clinical Practice Guidelines Committee (CPGC) after approval by the ASCO Adaptation Panel. The CPGC approved this guideline on January 25, 2016.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="424" ordby="600" name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="139" ordby="610" id="426" name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The type of evidence supporting the recommendations is not specifically stated.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="427" ordby="700" name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="152" ordby="705" id="428" name="Potential Benefits" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Adjuvant chemotherapy improves disease-free survival (DFS) and overall survival (OS) of patients with early breast cancer independent of age, nodal status, and estrogen receptor (ER) status. However, those with triple-negative and human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)&amp;ndash;positive breast cancer seem to derive the greatest proportional benefit from systemic chemotherapy and biologic therapy.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="153" ordby="710" id="429" name="Potential Harms" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Decisions regarding adjuvant chemotherapy regimens should take into account baseline recurrence risk, toxicities, likelihood of benefit, and host factors such as comorbidities. </li>
    <li>In the Breast Cancer International Research Group (BCIRG) 006 (Combination Chemotherapy with or without Trastuzumab in Treating Women with Breast Cancer) trial, lower rates of cardiotoxicity were observed with docetaxel-carboplatin-trastuzumab than with doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide followed by docetaxel-trastuzumab. These data support preferential use of docetaxel-carboplatin-trastuzumab, particularly for patients who might be at greater risk for cardiac dysfunction, on the basis of factors such as older age, low baseline ejection fraction, and pre-existing hypertension. Another option for patients with lower-risk node-negative disease who might have a higher risk for cardiotoxicity is trastuzumab-paclitaxel once per week followed by trastuzumab alone on the basis of a single-arm phase II trial in which rates of symptomatic heart failure were low and the observed asymptomatic decreases in ejection fraction improved with trastuzumab interruption and/or cessation. </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="432" ordby="900" name="Qualifying Statements">
    <field fieldid="137" ordby="905" id="433" name="Qualifying Statements" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The clinical practice guidelines and other guidance published herein are provided by American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) to assist providers in clinical decision making. The information herein should not be relied upon as being complete or accurate, nor should it be considered as inclusive of all proper treatments or methods of care or as a statement of the standard of care. With the rapid development of scientific knowledge, new evidence may emerge between the time information is developed and when it is published or read. The information is not continually updated and may not reflect the most recent evidence. The information addresses only the topics specifically identified herein and is not applicable to other interventions, diseases, or stages of diseases. This information does not mandate any particular course of medical care. Further, the information is not intended to substitute for the independent professional judgment of the treating provider, because the information does not account for individual variation among patients. Recommendations reflect high, moderate, or low confidence that the recommendation reflects the net effect of a given course of action. The use of words like &quot;must,&quot; &quot;must not,&quot; &quot;should,&quot; and &quot;should not&quot; indicate that a course of action is recommended or not recommended for either most or many patients, but there is latitude for the treating physician to select other courses of action in individual cases. In all cases, the selected course of action should be considered by the treating provider in the context of treating the individual patient. Use of the information is voluntary. ASCO provides this information on an &quot;as is&quot; basis and makes no warranty, expressed or implied, regarding the information. ASCO specifically disclaims any warranties of merchantability or fitness for a particular use or purpose. ASCO assumes no responsibility for any injury or damage to persons or property arising out of or related to any use of this information or for any errors or omissions.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="434" ordby="1000" name="Implementation of the Guideline">
    <field fieldid="131" ordby="1010" id="436" name="Description of Implementation Strategy" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>For information on the American Society for Clinical Oncology (ASCO) implementation strategy, please see the <a href=&quot;http://www.asco.org/node/5376/&quot; title=&quot;ASCO Web site&quot;>ASCO Web site</a>.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="117" ordby="1015" id="437" name="Implementation Tools" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Patient Resources"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Slide Presentation"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="439" ordby="1100" name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories">
    <field fieldid="50" ordby="1105" id="440" name="IOM Care Need" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Living with Illness"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="51" ordby="1110" id="441" name="IOM Domain" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Effectiveness"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Patient-centeredness"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="442" ordby="1200" name="Identifying Information and Availability">
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="1201" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Denduluri N, Somerfield MR, Eisen A, Holloway JN, Hurria A, King TA, Lyman GH, Partridge AH, Telli ML, Trudeau ME, Wolff AC. Selection of optimal adjuvant chemotherapy regimens for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative and adjuvant targeted therapy for HER2-positive breast cancers: an American Society of Clinical Oncology guideline adaptation of the Cancer Care Ontario clinical practice guideline. J Clin Oncol. 2016 Jul 10;34(20):2416-27. [32 references] <a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=27091714&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;>PubMed</a></td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="124" ordby="1205" id="443" name="Adaptation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This guideline is an adaptation of:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Eisen A, Fletcher GG, Gandhi S, et al: Optimal systemic therapy for early breast cancer in women: a clinical practice guideline. Curr Oncol 22:S67-81, 2015. </li>
</ul></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="128" ordby="1215" id="445" name="Date Released" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="2016 Jul 10"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="158" ordby="1225" id="447" name="Guideline Developer(s)" type="orglist-p">
      <fieldvalue value="American Society of Clinical Oncology - Medical Specialty Society"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="125" ordby="1235" id="449" name="Source(s) of Funding" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>American Society of Clinical Oncology</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="126" ordby="1240" id="450" name="Guideline Committee" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Expert Panel for Adaptation of Guideline on Selection of Optimal Adjuvant Chemotherapy Regimens for Early Breast Cancer and Adjuvant Targeted Therapy for Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor 2&amp;ndash;Positive Breast Cancers</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="127" ordby="1245" id="451" name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><em>Panel Members</em>: Neelima Denduluri, MD (<em>co-chair</em>), The US Oncology Network, Virginia Cancer Specialists, Arlington, VA; Antonio C. Wolff, MD (<em>co-chair</em>), The Johns Hopkins Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center, Baltimore, MD; Andrea Eisen, MD, Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre, and Cancer Care Ontario, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Jamie N. Holloway, PhD, Patient representative, Arlington, VA; Arti Hurria, MD, City of Hope, Duarte, CA; Tari A. King, MD, Dana-Farber/Brigham and Women's Cancer Center, Boston, MA; Gary H. Lyman, MD, MPH, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, WA; Ann H. Partridge, MD, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA; Melinda L. Telli, MD, Stanford University, Palo Alto, CA; Maureen E. Trudeau, MD, MA, Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre, and Cancer Care Ontario, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="147" ordby="1250" id="452" name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The Expert Panel was assembled in accordance with American Society of Clinical Oncology's (ASCO's) Conflict of Interest Policy Implementation for Clinical Practice Guidelines (<a href=&quot;http://www.asco.org/rwc&quot; title=&quot;ASCO Web site&quot;>http://www.asco.org/rwc</a>). All members of the Panel completed ASCO's disclosure form, which requires disclosure of financial and other interests, including relationships with commercial entities that are reasonably likely to experience direct regulatory or commercial impact as a result of promulgation of the guideline. Categories for disclosure include employment; leadership; stock or other ownership; honoraria; consulting or advisory role; speaker's bureau; research funding; patents, royalties, other intellectual property; expert testimony; travel, accommodations, expenses; and other relationships. In accordance with the Policy, the majority of the Panel members did not disclose any relationships constituting a conflict under the Policy.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Authors' Disclosures of Potential Conflicts of Interest</span></strong></p>
<p>The following represents disclosure information provided by authors of this manuscript. All relationships are considered compensated. Relationships are self-held unless noted. I = Immediate Family Member, Inst = My Institution. Relationships may not relate to the subject matter of this manuscript. For more information about ASCO's conflict of interest policy, please refer to <a href=&quot;http://www.asco.org/rwc&quot; title=&quot;ASCO Web site&quot;>www.asco.org/rwc</a> or <a href=&quot;http://jco.ascopubs.org/site/ifc&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Clinical Oncology Web site&quot;>jco.ascopubs.org/site/ifc</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Neelima Denduluri</strong><br />
<strong>Research Funding</strong>: Amgen (Inst), Novartis (Inst), Genentech (Inst)</p>
<p><strong>Mark R. Somerfield</strong><br />
No relationship to disclose</p>
<p><strong>Andrea Eisen</strong><br />
<strong>Research Funding</strong>: Genomic Health (Inst)<br />
<strong>Travel, Accommodations, Expenses</strong>: AstraZeneca</p>
<p><strong>Jamie N. Holloway</strong><br />
<strong>Stock or Other Ownership</strong>: Merck</p>
<p><strong>Arti Hurria</strong><br />
<strong>Consulting or Advisory Role</strong>: GTx, Seattle Genetics, Boehringer Ingelheim, On Q Health, Sanofi<br />
<strong>Research Funding</strong>: GlaxoSmithKline (Inst), Celgene (Inst), Novartis (Inst)</p>
<p><strong>Tari A. King</strong><br />
No relationship to disclose</p>
<p><strong>Gary H. Lyman</strong><br />
<strong>Research Funding</strong>: Amgen (Inst)</p>
<p><strong>Ann H. Partridge</strong><br />
<strong>Consulting or Advisory Role</strong>: Pfizer</p>
<p><strong>Melinda L. Telli</strong><br />
<strong>Consulting or Advisory Role</strong>: Vertex Pharmaceuticals<br />
<strong>Research Funding</strong>: Sanofi (Inst), Novartis (Inst), PharmaMar (Inst), BioMarin Pharmaceutical (Inst), AbbVie (Inst), Calithera Biosciences (Inst), Genentech (Inst), Medivation (Inst), OncoSec Medical (Inst)<br />
<strong>Travel, Accommodations, Expenses</strong>: BioMarin Pharmaceutical, Myriad Genetics</p>
<p><strong>Maureen E. Trudeau</strong><br />
<strong>Stock or Other Ownership</strong>: Rna Diagnostics<br />
<strong>Honoraria</strong>: Pfizer<br />
<strong>Consulting or Advisory Role</strong>: Rna Diagnostics<br />
<strong>Research Funding</strong>: Roche Canada (Inst), Novartis (Inst), Pfizer (Inst), Eisai (Inst), AstraZeneca (Inst), Astellas Pharma (Inst), Genomic Health (Inst)</p>
<p><strong>Antonio C. Wolff</strong><br />
<strong>Research Funding</strong>: Myriad Genetics<br />
<strong>Patents, Royalties, Other Intellectual Property: </strong>Johns Hopkins University Reference C12014: A Quantitative Multiplex Methylation Specific PCR Method-cMethDNA, Reagents, and Its Use</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="1256" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p>
<p>This guideline meets NGC's 2013 (revised) inclusion criteria.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="118" ordby="1260" id="454" name="Guideline Availability" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Available from the <a href=&quot;http://jco.ascopubs.org/content/34/20/2416.full.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Clinical Oncology Web site&quot;>Journal of Clinical Oncology Web site</a>.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="119" ordby="1265" id="455" name="Availability of Companion Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The following are available:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Selection of optimal adjuvant chemotherapy regimens for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative and adjuvant targeted therapy for HER2-positive breast cancers: an American Society of Clinical Oncology guideline adaptation of the Cancer Care Ontario clinical practice guideline. Methodology supplement. Alexandria (VA): American Society of Clinical Oncology; 2016. 17 p. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://ascopubs.org/doi/suppl/10.1200/jco.2016.67.0182/suppl_file/MS_2016.670182.docx&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Clinical Oncology Web site&quot;>Journal of Clinical Oncology Web site</a>. </li>
    <li>Selection of optimal adjuvant chemotherapy regimens for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative and adjuvant targeted therapy for HER2-positive breast cancers: an American Society of Clinical Oncology guideline adaptation of the Cancer Care Ontario clinical practice guideline. Data supplement. Alexandria (VA): American Society of Clinical Oncology; 2016. 6 p. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://ascopubs.org/doi/suppl/10.1200/jco.2016.67.0182/suppl_file/DS_2016.670182-1.docx&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Clinical Oncology Web site&quot;>Journal of Clinical Oncology Web site</a>. </li>
    <li>Selection of optimal adjuvant chemotherapy regimens for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative and adjuvant targeted therapy for HER2-positive breast cancers: an American Society of Clinical Oncology guideline adaptation of the Cancer Care Ontario clinical practice guideline. Slide set. Alexandria (VA): American Society of Clinical Oncology; 2016. 18 p. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.asco.org/sites/new-www.asco.org/files/content-files/practice-and-guidelines/documents/2016-Breast-Systemic-Therapy-Adaptation-Slides-1.pdf&quot; title=&quot;ASCO Web site&quot;>American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Web site</a>. </li>
    <li>Selection of optimal adjuvant chemotherapy regimens for human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative and adjuvant targeted therapy for HER2-positive breast cancers: an American Society of Clinical Oncology guideline adaptation of the Cancer Care Ontario clinical practice guideline. Summary of recommendations table. Alexandria (VA): American Society of Clinical Oncology; 2016. 4 p. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.instituteforquality.org/sites/instituteforquality.org/files/2016-Breast-Systemic-Therapy-Adaptation-Summary-Table.pdf&quot; title=&quot;ASCO Web site&quot;>ASCO Web site</a>. </li>
</ul></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="143" ordby="1275" id="457" name="Patient Resources" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The following is available:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Breast cancer. Treatment options. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.cancer.net/cancer-types/breast-cancer/treatment-options&quot; title=&quot;Cancer.Net Web site&quot;>Cancer.Net Web site</a>. </li>
</ul>
<p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;>Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="142" ordby="1280" id="458" name="NGC Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on October 20, 2016.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="141" ordby="1290" id="460" name="Copyright Statement" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the American Society of Clinical Oncology's copyright restrictions.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="99999" ordby="99999" name="Disclaimer">
    <field fieldid="99999" ordby="99999" id="99999" name="NGC Disclaimer" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<p>The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.</p> 
<p>All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.</p> 
<p>Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the <a href=&quot;/help-and-about/summaries/inclusion-criteria&quot;>NGC Inclusion Criteria</a>.</p> 
<p>NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.</p> 
<p>Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.</p>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
</version><!--
     FILE ARCHIVED ON 23:13:48 Jul 12, 2018 AND RETRIEVED FROM THE
     INTERNET ARCHIVE ON 18:19:20 Jul 15, 2018.
     JAVASCRIPT APPENDED BY WAYBACK MACHINE, COPYRIGHT INTERNET ARCHIVE.

     ALL OTHER CONTENT MAY ALSO BE PROTECTED BY COPYRIGHT (17 U.S.C.
     SECTION 108(a)(3)).
-->
<!--
playback timings (ms):
  LoadShardBlock: 164.226 (3)
  esindex: 0.006
  captures_list: 179.934
  CDXLines.iter: 12.352 (3)
  PetaboxLoader3.datanode: 189.18 (4)
  exclusion.robots: 0.257
  exclusion.robots.policy: 0.246
  RedisCDXSource: 0.602
  load_resource: 231.93
-->