<script src="//archive.org/includes/analytics.js?v=cf34f82" type="text/javascript"></script>
<script type="text/javascript">window.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded',function(){var v=archive_analytics.values;v.service='wb';v.server_name='wwwb-app40.us.archive.org';v.server_ms=308;archive_analytics.send_pageview({});});</script><script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/wbhack.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<script type="text/javascript">
__wbhack.init('https://web.archive.org/web');
</script>
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/banner-styles.css?v=1531166943.0" />
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/iconochive.css?v=1531166943.0" />

<!-- End Wayback Rewrite JS Include --><!-- BEGIN WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT -->
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/timestamp.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/graph-calc.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/auto-complete.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/toolbar.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<style type="text/css">
body {
  margin-top:0 !important;
  padding-top:0 !important;
  /*min-width:800px !important;*/
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestions {
    text-align: left; cursor: default; border: 1px solid #ccc; border-top: 0; background: #fff; box-shadow: -1px 1px 3px rgba(0,0,0,.1);
    position: absolute; display: none; z-index: 2147483647; max-height: 254px; overflow: hidden; overflow-y: auto; box-sizing: border-box;
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion { position: relative; padding: 0 .6em; line-height: 23px; white-space: nowrap; overflow: hidden; text-overflow: ellipsis; font-size: 1.02em; color: #333; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion b { font-weight: bold; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion.selected { background: #f0f0f0; }
</style>
<div id="wm-ipp" lang="en" style="display:none;direction:ltr;">
<div style="position:fixed;left:0;top:0;right:0;">
<div id="wm-ipp-inside">
  <div style="position:relative;">
    <div id="wm-logo" style="float:left;width:130px;padding-top:10px;">
      <a href="/web/" title="Wayback Machine home page"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wayback-toolbar-logo.png" alt="Wayback Machine" width="110" height="39" border="0" /></a>
    </div>
    <div class="r" style="float:right;">
      <div id="wm-btns" style="text-align:right;height:25px;">
                  <div id="wm-save-snapshot-success">success</div>
          <div id="wm-save-snapshot-fail">fail</div>
          <a href="#"
             onclick="__wm.saveSnapshot('https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10327?contentType=xml', '20180712214337')"
             title="Share via My Web Archive"
             id="wm-save-snapshot-open"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-web"></span>
          </a>
          <a href="https://archive.org/account/login.php"
             title="Sign In"
             id="wm-sign-in"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-person"></span>
          </a>
          <span id="wm-save-snapshot-in-progress" class="iconochive-web"></span>
        	<a href="http://faq.web.archive.org/" title="Get some help using the Wayback Machine" style="top:-6px;"><span class="iconochive-question" style="color:rgb(87,186,244);font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a id="wm-tb-close" href="#close" onclick="__wm.h(event);return false;" style="top:-2px;" title="Close the toolbar"><span class="iconochive-remove-circle" style="color:#888888;font-size:240%;"></span></a>
      </div>
      <div id="wm-share" style="text-align:right;">
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://web.archive.org/web/20180712214337/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10327?contentType=xml', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Facebook" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-facebook" style="color:#3b5998;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=https://web.archive.org/web/20180712214337/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10327?contentType=xml&amp;via=internetarchive', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Twitter" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-twitter" style="color:#1dcaff;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
      </div>
    </div>
    <table class="c" style="">
      <tbody>
	<tr>
	  <td class="u" colspan="2">
	    <form target="_top" method="get" action="/web/submit" name="wmtb" id="wmtb"><input type="text" name="url" id="wmtbURL" value="https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10327?contentType=xml" onfocus="this.focus();this.select();" /><input type="hidden" name="type" value="replay" /><input type="hidden" name="date" value="20180712214337" /><input type="submit" value="Go" /></form>
	  </td>
	  <td class="n" rowspan="2" style="width:110px;">
	    <table>
	      <tbody>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV MONTH NAV AND MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="m">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180610053603/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10327?contentType=xml" title="10 Jun 2018"><strong>Jun</strong></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayMonthEl" title="You are here: 21:43:37 Jul 12, 2018">JUL</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">Aug</td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV CAPTURE NAV AND DAY OF MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="d">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180610053603/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10327?contentType=xml" title="05:36:03 Jun 10, 2018"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_prv_on.png" alt="Previous capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayDayEl" style="width:34px;font-size:24px;white-space:nowrap;" title="You are here: 21:43:37 Jul 12, 2018">12</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_nxt_off.png" alt="Next capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV YEAR NAV AND YEAR INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="y">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160930191039/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10327?contentType=xml" title="30 Sep 2016"><strong>2016</strong></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayYearEl" title="You are here: 21:43:37 Jul 12, 2018">2018</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">2019</td>
		</tr>
	      </tbody>
	    </table>
	  </td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td class="s">
	    	    <div id="wm-nav-captures">
	      	      <a class="t" href="/web/20180712214337*/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10327?contentType=xml" title="See a list of every capture for this URL">6 captures</a>
	      <div class="r" title="Timespan for captures of this URL">30 Sep 2016 - 12 Jul 2018</div>
	      </div>
	  </td>
	  <td class="k">
	    <a href="" id="wm-graph-anchor">
	      <div id="wm-ipp-sparkline" title="Explore captures for this URL" style="position: relative">
		<canvas id="wm-sparkline-canvas" width="575" height="27" border="0"></canvas>
	      </div>
	    </a>
	  </td>
	</tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <div style="position:absolute;bottom:0;right:2px;text-align:right;">
      <a id="wm-expand" class="wm-btn wm-closed" href="#expand" onclick="__wm.ex(event);return false;"><span id="wm-expand-icon" class="iconochive-down-solid"></span> <span style="font-size:80%">About this capture</span></a>
    </div>
  </div>
    <div id="wm-capinfo" style="border-top:1px solid #777;display:none; overflow: hidden">
            <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center">COLLECTED BY</div>
    <div style="padding:3px;position:relative" id="wm-collected-by-content">
            <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:50%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/archiveteam);"></span>
		Organization: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/archiveteam" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">Archive Team</span></a>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  <img align=right src="http://archiveteam.org/images/e/e6/Archiveteam.jpg" width=200> Formed in 2009, the Archive Team (not to be confused with the archive.org Archive-It Team) is a rogue archivist collective dedicated to saving copies of rapidly dying or deleted websites for the sake of history and digital heritage. The group is 100% composed of volunteers and interested parties, and has expanded into a large amount of related projects for saving online and digital history.
<p>
History is littered with hundreds of conflicts over the future of a community, group, location or business that were "resolved" when one of the parties stepped ahead and destroyed what was there. With the original point of contention destroyed, the debates would fall to the wayside. Archive Team believes that by duplicated condemned data, the conversation and debate can continue, as well as the richness and insight gained by keeping the materials. Our projects have ranged in size from a single volunteer downloading the data to a small-but-critical site, to over 100 volunteers stepping forward to acquire terabytes of user-created data to save for future generations.
<p>
The main site for Archive Team is at <a href="http://www.archiveteam.org">archiveteam.org</a> and contains up to the date information on various projects, manifestos, plans and walkthroughs.
<p>
This collection contains the output of many Archive Team projects, both ongoing and completed. Thanks to the generous providing of disk space by the Internet Archive, multi-terabyte datasets can be made available, as well as in use by the <a href="http://archive.org/web/web.php">Wayback Machine</a>, providing a path back to lost websites and work. 
<p>
Our collection has grown to the point of having sub-collections for the type of data we acquire. If you are seeking to browse the contents of these collections, the Wayback Machine is the best first stop. Otherwise, you are free to dig into the stacks to see what you may find.
<p>
<b>The Archive Team Panic Downloads</b> are full pulldowns of currently extant websites, meant to serve as emergency backups for needed sites that are in danger of closing, or which will be missed dearly if suddenly lost due to hard drive crashes or server failures. 
<p>
	</div>
	      </div>
      <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:49%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/archivebot)"></span>
		<div>Collection: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/archivebot" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">ArchiveBot: The Archive Team Crowdsourced Crawler</span></a></div>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  ArchiveBot is an IRC bot designed to automate the archival of smaller websites (e.g. up to a few hundred thousand URLs). You give it a URL to start at, and it grabs all content under that URL, records it in a WARC, and then uploads that WARC to ArchiveTeam servers for eventual injection into the Internet Archive (or other archive sites).
<p>
To use ArchiveBot, drop by #archivebot on EFNet. To interact with ArchiveBot, you issue commands by typing it into the channel. Note you will need channel operator permissions in order to issue archiving jobs. The dashboard shows the sites being downloaded currently.
<p>
There is a dashboard running for the archivebot process at <a href="http://www.archivebot.com">http://www.archivebot.com</a>.
<p>
ArchiveBot's source code can be found at <a href="https://github.com/ArchiveTeam/ArchiveBot">https://github.com/ArchiveTeam/ArchiveBot</a>.
	</div>
	      </div>
    </div>
    <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center" title="Timestamps for the elements of this page">TIMESTAMPS</div>
    <div>
      <div id="wm-capresources" style="margin:0 5px 5px 5px;max-height:250px;overflow-y:scroll !important"></div>
      <div id="wm-capresources-loading" style="text-align:left;margin:0 20px 5px 5px;display:none"><img src="/static/images/loading.gif" alt="loading" /></div>
    </div>
  </div></div></div></div><script type="text/javascript">
__wm.bt(575,27,25,2,"web","https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10327?contentType=xml","2018-07-12",1996);
</script>
<!-- END WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT --><version>
  <xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource>
  <section secid="390" ordby="100" name="General">
    <field fieldid="161" ordby="105" id="391" name="Guideline Title" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_title&quot;>UK national guideline for the management of chancroid 2014.</div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="110" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Clinical Effectiveness Group. UK national guideline for the management of chancroid. London (UK): British Association for Sexual Health and HIV (BASHH); 2014 Mar. 22 p.  [63 references]</td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="115" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p>
<p>This guideline updates a previous version: Association for Genitourinary Medicine (AGUM), Medical Society for the Study of Venereal Disease (MSSVD). 2002 national guideline for the management of chancroid. London: Association for Genitourinary Medicine (AGUM), Medical Society for the Study of Venereal Disease (MSSVD); 2002. Various p. [51 references]</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="420" ordby="300" name="Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="151" ordby="310" id="421" name="Major Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Levels of evidence (<strong>I-IV</strong>) and grades of recommendation (<strong>A-C</strong>) are defined at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Diagnosis</span></strong></p>
<p>A number of papers have summarised the current approach to diagnosis. The main methods revolve around the identification of <em>Haemophilus ducreyi</em> (<em>H ducreyi</em>) by:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Detection of nucleic acid (DNA) by amplification techniques such as polymerase chain reaction (PCR), using nested techniques. There are no commercial assays available, but a number of specialised or research laboratories have published their in-house methods. </li>
    <li>Culture of material obtained from the ulcer base, or the undermined edges of the ulcer, after removing superficial pus with a cotton-tipped swab, or from pus aspirated from the bubo. The material can be plated directly onto culture medium incubated at 33&amp;deg;C in high humidity with 5% carbon dioxide for a minimum of 48 to 72 hours. </li>
</ul>
<p>Culture media include:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li><em>Gonococci</em> (GC) agar supplemented with 1% to 2% bovine haemoglobin, 5% fetal calf-serum </li>
    <li>Mueller-Hinton agar enriched with 5% chocolatised horse blood
    <p>Both of these also require supplements of 1% IsoVitaleX, and 3mg/L vancomycin to prevent overgrowth of Gram positive organisms.</p>
    </li>
    <li>Modification of these techniques by substitution of 0.2% activated charcoal instead of fetal calf serum has proven equally effective and is much cheaper. </li>
</ul>
<p>The use of more than one medium increases sensitivity, which is still low (&amp;lt;80%). Since <em>H ducreyi</em> is a fastidious organism, specimens should be plated out directly at the clinic or sent rapidly (within 4 hours) to the laboratory; calcium alginate or plastic swabs should be used for sample collection; special transport medium may be helpful if culture media are not readily available. Confirmatory testing for oxidase, alkaline phosphatase, nitrate reduction and porphyrins can be used.</p>
<p>Microscopy of a Gram stained smear (or other stains) of material from the ulcer base or of pus aspirate from the bubo may show characteristic gram-negative coccobacilli, with occasional characteristic chaining. The test has low sensitivity and is not recommended as a diagnostic test.</p>
<p>Expert opinion has estimated that, in endemic areas, a positive <em>H ducreyi</em> culture is achievable in 60% to 80% of patients considered to have chancroid on clinical grounds. Microscopy is only 50% sensitive compared to culture, and prone to multiple errors, given the polymicrobial flora of many ulcers. PCR is the most sensitive technique, and has been demonstrated to be 95% sensitive compared to culture; conversely culture may be only 75% sensitive relative to PCR. However, PCR may be negative in a number of culture-proven chancroid cases owing to the presence of Taq polymerase inhibitors in the DNA preparations extracted from genital ulcer specimens. Multiple PCR assays have also been developed for the simultaneous amplification of DNA targets from <em>H ducreyi</em>, <em>Treponema pallidum</em> and herpes simplex virus (HSV) types 1 and 2.</p>
<p><strong>Other Diagnostic Methods</strong></p>
<p>Other diagnostic tests have included various antigen-detection techniques involving immunofluorescence or radio-isotopic probes but these are not used currently in the United Kingdom (UK).</p>
<p><strong>Serology</strong></p>
<p>The detection of antibody to <em>H ducreyi</em> as a marker of chancroid has been effective in a number of epidemiological studies with enzyme-linked immunoassays (EIAs) using either lysed whole cell, lipo-oligosaccharide (LOS) or outer membrane proteins (OMPs) as antigen sources. However, for the individual patient, the method lacks sensitivity, specificity (cross-reaction with other Haemophilus species) and cannot distinguish between remote and recent infection.</p>
<p>To circumvent the many problems of confirming a positive diagnosis of chancroid, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) in the United States of America (USA) have proposed that a &quot;probable diagnosis&quot;, for both clinical and surveillance purposes be made if the patient has one or more painful genital ulcers, and (a) no evidence of <em>T pallidum</em> infection by dark field examination of ulcer exudate or by a serologic test for syphilis performed at least 7 days after onset of ulcers, and (b) the clinical presentation, appearance of the genital ulcers and regional lymphadenopathy, if present, is typical for chancroid and a test for HSV performed on the ulcer exudate is negative.</p>
<p><strong>Clinical Diagnosis</strong></p>
<p>A number of studies have found that the clinical diagnosis of genital ulcers is often unreliable with an accuracy ranging from 33% to 80%, even in areas of high prevalence and good clinical expertise. However, the true accuracy may be higher. Some of these studies suffered because of the low sensitivity of culture methods used. Previously this would not have mattered too much as syndromic management would cover the significant prevalence of mixed infections - co-infections of <em>H ducreyi</em> with <em>T pallidum</em> or HSV were frequent, occurring in over 10% of patients in many African studies. However, now that the prevalence of chancroid has decreased it is likely that the use of syndromic management too will decrease and clinical diagnosis may assume increased importance.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Management</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>General Advice</strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;>
    <li>Patients should be advised to avoid sexual intercourse until they and their partner(s) have completed treatment and follow-up. </li>
    <li>Patients should be given a detailed explanation of their condition with particular emphasis on the long-term implications both for their health and that of their partner(s). This should be reinforced by giving them clear and accurate written information. </li>
</ol>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Further Investigations</span></strong></p>
<p>Screening for other possible causes of genital ulcerative disease should be undertaken, particularly for syphilis, genital herpes, lymphogranuloma venereum (LGV) or donovanosis. Full sexually transmitted disease (STD) screening should be offered. Biopsy of lymph nodes may be required to exclude neoplasia, if lymphadenopathy does not resolve following treatment.</p>
<p><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;><strong>Treatment</strong></span></p>
<p>Successful treatment of chancroid should cure infection, resolve clinical symptoms, and prevent transmission to sexual partners.</p>
<p>It should be noted that no comparative treatments have been published since 1999 in which chancroid has been confirmed by culture or PCR. The main treatment options are presented in Table 1 in the original guideline document (summarised below) and most are similar to the 2010 CDC guidelines from the USA. Evidence of their clinical efficacy has been obtained in randomised controlled trials for some (<strong>level of evidence Ib</strong>). However, grading of recommendation also takes account of ease of administration, side effects and compliance.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Recommended Regimens</span></strong></p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Azithromycin 1 g orally in a single dose (<strong>Ib, A</strong>)
    <p>or</p>
    </li>
    <li>Ceftriaxone 250 mg intramuscularly (IM) in a single dose (<strong>Ib, B</strong>)
    <p>or </p>
    </li>
    <li>Ciprofloxacin 500 mg orally in a single dose (<strong>Ib, B</strong>)
    <p>or</p>
    </li>
    <li>Ciprofloxacin 500 mg orally two times a day for 3 days (<strong>Ib, B/A</strong>)
    <p>or</p>
    </li>
    <li>Erythromycin base 500 mg orally four times a day for 7 days (<strong>Ib, B/A</strong>). This is also recommended for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive patients rather than the single dose regimens. </li>
</ul>
<p>Azithromycin and ceftriaxone offer the advantage of single-dose therapy. They have excellent in vitro activity against <em>H ducreyi</em> with no reported resistance. However, a study comparing single dose treatment of chancroid using thiamphenicol versus azithromycin found that all 4 HIV positive cases treated with azithromycin failed therapy. Moreover, in this study chancroid was diagnosed after exclusion of syphilis by clinical characterisation of genital necrotic and painful sores and positive Gram stains and not by culture or PCR.</p>
<p>Erythromycin given at high doses for 7 days is the World Health Organization (WHO)-recommended first line treatment for chancroid. Although efficacious (with cure rates of 93% noted in Kenya and India) poor compliance and gastrointestinal intolerance make alternative therapy desirable (<strong>Ib, B</strong>). Lower dosage and simpler regimens of erythromycin have been evaluated in two separate trials in Kenya. Cure rates of 91% were achieved in a randomised double blind trial of erythromycin 500 mg three times daily for 7 days (versus a single dose of ciprofloxacin) (<strong>Ib, B</strong>). The efficacy of an even shorter regimen (250 mg three times daily for 5 days) was reportedly high in a small trial conducted by the same team, but this was not a randomised comparative trial (<strong>III, C</strong>).</p>
<p>Worldwide, several isolates with intermediate resistance to either ciprofloxacin or erythromycin have been reported, thus single dose ciprofloxacin and the shorter (5-day) regimen of erythromycin may not be effective, as has been reported by teams in Rwanda and Malawi. However, a double-blind randomised-controlled trial conducted in Nairobi showed comparable cure rates for single dose ciprofloxacin (92%) and the standard 7-day course of erythromycin (91%).</p>
<p>Widespread resistance to trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole (TMP-SMX) renders this cheap and once effective alternative virtually useless.</p>
<p><strong>Alternative Regimens</strong></p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Oral single dose fluoroquinolones such as fleroxacin 400 mg, or norfloxacin 800 mg (<strong>Ib, B</strong>) </li>
    <li>Single dose aminoglycoside such as spectinomycin 2 g IM (<strong>IIa, B</strong>). </li>
</ul>
<p>Single dose thiamphenicol 5 grams dissolved in 50 ml of water in a single oral dose was effective in presumed cases of chancroid in Brazil.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Allergy</span></strong></p>
<p>Patients allergic to quinolones or cephalosporins should be treated with the erythromycin regimen.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Special Considerations</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>Treatment for Pregnant or Lactating Mothers and Treatment for Children</strong></p>
<p>The safety of azithromycin for pregnant and lactating women has not been established. Ciprofloxacin is contraindicated for pregnant and lactating women, children, and adolescents less than 18 years of age in which case erythromycin or ceftriaxone regimens should be used. No adverse effects of chancroid on pregnancy outcome or on the fetus have been reported.</p>
<p><strong>HIV Infection</strong></p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Probable increased incidence of delayed healing and treatment failures though evidence is conflicting. </li>
    <li>Treatment of choice is erythromycin 500 mg 4 times a day (qds) for 7 days. </li>
</ul>
<p>Patients co-infected with HIV should be closely monitored. There have been concerns that healing may be slower among HIV-infected people and treatment failures have been frequently recorded in Kenya using azithromycin, ceftriaxone, or single dose fleroxacin and in Malawi using low dose erythromycin or ciprofloxacin. A higher treatment failure rate among HIV-infected patients has, however, not been observed by the same Kenyan team in a study using low dose erythromycin or single dose ciprofloxacin. In Rwanda, researchers found that HIV and the degree of immunosuppression as measured by CD4 counts had no effect on bacteriologic and clinical outcomes, and that treatment failures were entirely attributable to resistance of <em>H ducreyi</em> to TMP-SMX. Dosage and duration of the fleroxacin regimen also needed to be increased to treat HIV-infected patients in Nairobi. CDC recommends that &quot;since data on therapeutic efficacy with the recommended ceftriaxone and azithromycin regimens among patients infected with HIV are limited, those regimens should be used among persons known to be infected with HIV only if follow-up can be assured.&quot; Others have concluded that azithromycin should be avoided in co-infected patients. The case for using erythromycin was borne out by the acceptable response to syndromic management that was not related to HIV-1 infection when this drug was used in a study in Durban.</p>
<p>A Cochrane review done to investigate whether genital ulcer disease treatment reduced sexual acquisition of HIV identified 3 studies, 2 of which involved treatment of chancroid in Nairobi involving HIV negative men. The former trial compared fleroxacin to TMP-SMX and the latter investigated 2 different doses of fleroxacin. The cure rates for chancroid were both very high. Not surprisingly HIV acquisition was not reduced given the short follow up - presumably seroconverters would have acquired chancroid and HIV from an untreated HIV positive contact at the same time prior to any treatment. However, the conclusion of the Cochrane review was that there was insufficient evidence that treatment of genital ulcer disease reduces sexual acquisition of HIV infection. The results of this review once again demonstrate both the difficulties in designing trials that might be capable of investigating the link between sexually transmitted infections (STIs) and HIV transmission amongst casual sex acts - one of the main determinants in the spread of HIV, and the need to undertake reviews in areas where there is significant biological plausibility in the question asked.</p>
<p><strong>Management of Fluctuant Buboes</strong></p>
<p>The classic strategy has been to needle-aspirate fluctuant buboes from adjacent healthy skin. The procedure is simpler and safer than incision, which is prone to complications (sinus formations). A randomised study conducted during an outbreak of chancroid in the USA has shown that careful incision and drainage was also an effective and safe method for treating fluctuant buboes and avoided frequent needle re-aspirations. This procedure should always be performed under effective antibiotic cover.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Follow-Up</span></strong></p>
<p>Patients should be re-examined 3 to 7 days after initiation of therapy. If treatment is successful, ulcers improve symptomatically within 3 days and substantial re-epithelization occurs within 7 days after onset of therapy. The time required for complete healing is related to the size of the ulcer (and perhaps HIV-related immunosuppression; large ulcers may require more than 2 weeks). Clinical resolution of fluctuant lymphadenopathy is slower than that of ulcers and may require frequent needle aspiration (or drainage).</p>
<p>A test of cure is not recommended.</p>
<p>Treatment failures should warrant: (i) investigation of possible coinfections with <em>T pallidum</em> or HSV; or (ii) determination of possible resistance by isolation of <em>H ducreyi</em> and susceptibility testing by the agar dilution technique to determine minimal inhibitory concentrations but this requires a specialised laboratory.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Sexual Partner(s) Management</span></strong></p>
<p>Persons who have had sexual contact with a patient who has chancroid within the 10 days before onset of the patient's symptoms should be examined, and treated even in the absence of symptoms, as asymptomatic carriage of <em>H ducreyi</em> has been proven to occur, but screening is not recommended.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Definitions</span></strong>:</p>
<p><strong>Levels of Evidence</strong></p>
<table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Levels of Evidence&quot;>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th width=&quot;5%&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>Level</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Type of Evidence</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>Ia</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>Ib</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from at least one randomised controlled trial </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>IIa</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from at least one well-designed controlled study without randomisation </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>IIb</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from at least one type of well-designed quasi-experimental study</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>III</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from well-designed, non-experimental descriptive studies, such as comparative studies, correlation studies and case control studies</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>IV</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from expert committee reports or opinions and/or clinical experience of respected authorities</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Grading of Recommendations</strong></p>
<table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Grades of Recommendation&quot;>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Grade</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Recommendation</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;><strong>A</strong> (Evidence levels Ia, Ib) </td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Requires at least one randomised controlled trial as part of the body of literature of overall good quality and consistency addressing the specific recommendation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;><strong>B</strong> (Evidence levels IIa, IIb, III)</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Requires availability of well-conducted clinical studies but no randomised clinical trials on the topic of recommendation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;><strong>C</strong> (Evidence level IV)</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Requires evidence from expert committee reports or opinions and/or clinical experience of respected authorities. Indicates absence of directly applicable studies of good quality</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="138" ordby="330" id="423" name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>None provided</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="396" ordby="400" name="Scope">
    <field fieldid="140" ordby="405" id="397" name="Disease/Condition(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Chancroid</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="103" ordby="410" id="398" name="Guideline Category" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Diagnosis"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Evaluation"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Management"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Treatment"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="113" ordby="415" id="399" name="Clinical Specialty" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Infectious Diseases"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Urology"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="114" ordby="420" id="400" name="Intended Users" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Advanced Practice Nurses"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Nurses"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Physician Assistants"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Physicians"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Public Health Departments"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="129" ordby="425" id="401" name="Guideline Objective(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>To offer recommendations on the diagnosis, treatment and health promotion principles for the effective management of chancroid</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="132" ordby="430" id="402" name="Target Population" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>People aged 16 years and older presenting to services offering Level 3 care in sexually transmitted infection (STI) management within the United Kingdom (UK)</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="133" ordby="435" id="403" name="Interventions and Practices Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>Diagnosis/Evaluation</strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;>
    <li>Identification of <em>Haemophilus ducreyi</em> (<em>H ducreyi</em>)
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Detection of nucleic acid (DNA) by amplification techniques such as polymerase chain reaction (PCR) </li>
        <li>Culture of material from the ulcer base or of pus aspirate from the bubo </li>
        <li>Microscopy of Gram stained smear of material from the ulcer base or of pus aspirate from the bubo (not recommended) </li>
    </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Criteria for making a &quot;probable diagnosis&quot; </li>
    <li>Further investigations
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Screening for other possible causes of genital ulcer disease </li>
        <li>Full sexually transmitted disease (STD) screening </li>
        <li>Biopsy of lymph nodes to exclude neoplasia </li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Management/Treatment</strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;>
    <li>Providing patients with information about their condition and advice to avoid sexual intercourse until treatment completion and follow-up </li>
    <li>Pharmacological interventions
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Azithromycin </li>
        <li>Ceftriaxone </li>
        <li>Ciprofloxacin </li>
        <li>Erythromycin </li>
        <li>Fleroxacin or norfloxacin </li>
        <li>Spectinomycin </li>
        <li>Thiamphenicol </li>
    </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Management of fluctuant buboes
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Needle aspiration from adjacent healthy skin </li>
        <li>Incision and drainage </li>
    </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Special treatment considerations for pregnant women, lactating mothers, children and individuals with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection </li>
    <li>Sexual partner management </li>
    <li>Follow-up
    <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
        <li>Examination 3 to 7 days after initiation of therapy </li>
        <li>Needle aspiration or drainage (fluctuant lymphadenopathy) </li>
        <li>Treatment failures
        <ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
            <li>Investigation of possible co-infections with <em>Treponema pallidum</em> (<em>T pallidum</em>) or herpes simplex virus (HSV) </li>
            <li>Determination of possible resistance by isolation of <em>H ducreyi</em> and susceptibility testing by the agar dilution technique </li>
        </ul>
        </li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ol></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="134" ordby="440" id="404" name="Major Outcomes Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Accuracy, sensitivity, and specificity of diagnostic tests </li>
    <li>Clinical efficacy of treatment (cure rate) </li>
    <li>Treatment failure </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="405" ordby="500" name="Methodology">
    <field fieldid="109" ordby="505" id="406" name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Searches of Electronic Databases"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="135" ordby="510" id="407" name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The review has been updated by searching PubMed from 1999 to 2013 using the search terms/medical subject headings (MeSH) headings: &quot;Chancroid&quot;; &quot;Chancroid and diagnosis&quot;; &quot;Chancroid and treatment&quot;; &quot;<em>Haemophilus ducreyi</em> diagnosis&quot;; &quot;<em>Haemophilus ducreyi</em> treatment&quot;; and &quot;Chancroid and randomized trial&quot;. The Cochrane Library was searched from 1957 to 2013 using the MeSH headings &quot;chancroid&quot; and &quot;<em>Haemophilus ducreyi</em>&quot; as were the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Sexually Transmitted Disease (STD) guidelines of 2010, World Health Organization (WHO) STD guidelines and the 2011 European Guideline for the Management of Chancroid. In addition, abstracts and proceedings from the most recent International Conferences on Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS), Meetings of the International Society for STD Research (ISSTDR) and British Association for Sexual Health and HIV (BASHH) Spring Meeting were reviewed.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="136" ordby="515" id="408" name="Number of Source Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not stated</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="115" ordby="520" id="409" name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="149" ordby="525" id="410" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>Levels of Evidence</strong></p>
<table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Levels of Evidence&quot;>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th width=&quot;5%&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>Level</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Type of Evidence</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>Ia</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>Ib</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from at least one randomised controlled trial </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>IIa</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from at least one well-designed controlled study without randomisation </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>IIb</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from at least one type of well-designed quasi-experimental study</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>III</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from well-designed, non-experimental descriptive studies, such as comparative studies, correlation studies and case control studies</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>IV</th>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Evidence obtained from expert committee reports or opinions and/or clinical experience of respected authorities</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="116" ordby="530" id="411" name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Systematic Review"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="150" ordby="535" id="412" name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not stated</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="112" ordby="540" id="413" name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Expert Consensus"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="145" ordby="545" id="414" name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Guideline development is undertaken by a multi-disciplinary writing committee with membership determined in a transparent manner. The chair is chosen by the Clinical Effectiveness Group (CEG). The CEG lead then discusses with the chair what suggestions they might have for members from other disciplines. The additional members of the group are then invited by the CEG. Writing committee membership includes relevant professional groups (for example genitourinary medicine physicians, nurses, health advisors, pharmacists, microbiologists and other professionals from allied specialties as appropriate) and when relevant this will involve working with the appropriate British Association for Sexual Health and HIV (BASHH) Special Interest Group (SIG) and the BASHH audit group.</p>
<p>Patients' views and preferences are sought and considered and the process documented. This may include patient representative involvement in the writing committee, information obtained from patient interview or surveys during the writing and/or piloting process, reviewing published work on patient experiences or involving patient associations. The chair of the writing group identifies an appropriate member such as the Health Advisor to get patient feedback on the guideline. BASHH is currently developing a public panel to assist with its work and in the future this group could be approached to assist in guideline development.</p>
<p>Recommendations are formulated with consideration of their health benefits, side effects and risks, with evidence presented in the guideline that these issues have been addressed. Each recommendation is linked to the supporting evidence with a list of relevant references.</p>
<p>Consideration is given to pragmatic and organisational issues relevant to the guideline. This is sought during and may emerge from the piloting of the guideline.</p>
<p>The authors consider the financial cost implications of recommendations made. Where disagreement arises within the writing committee with regard to recommendations the chair attempts to resolve these (for example by a voting system or formal consensus method). The process is documented and reported to the CEG editor. When this is not possible the CEG will review the evidence themselves and invite the chair and possibly other members of the writing committee to a meeting to agree a resolution and final recommendations.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="146" ordby="550" id="415" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>Grading of Recommendations</strong></p>
<table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Grades of Recommendation&quot;>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Grade</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Recommendation</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;><strong>A</strong> (Evidence levels Ia, Ib) </td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Requires at least one randomised controlled trial as part of the body of literature of overall good quality and consistency addressing the specific recommendation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;><strong>B</strong> (Evidence levels IIa, IIb, III)</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Requires availability of well-conducted clinical studies but no randomised clinical trials on the topic of recommendation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;><strong>C</strong> (Evidence level IV)</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Requires evidence from expert committee reports or opinions and/or clinical experience of respected authorities. Indicates absence of directly applicable studies of good quality</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="148" ordby="565" id="417" name="Cost Analysis" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="104" ordby="570" id="418" name="Method of Guideline Validation" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Clinical Validation-Pilot Testing"/>
      <fieldvalue value="External Peer Review"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Internal Peer Review"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="130" ordby="575" id="419" name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The initial draft of the guideline, including the patient information leaflet (PIL) was piloted for validation by the Clinical Effectiveness Group (CEG).</p>
<p>The final guideline was then reviewed by the CEG using the Appraisal of Guidelines for Research and Evaluation (AGREE) instrument before posting it on the British Association for Sexual Health and HIV (BASHH) website for external peer review for a two month period. Comments received were collated by the CEG editor and sent to the guideline chair for review and action. The final guideline was approved by the CEG and a review date agreed before publication on the BASHH website.</p>
<p>The rare nature of this disease precluded the review of this guideline by a patient suffering from chancroid. However, the guideline was reviewed by the BASHH <em>Patient and Public Engagement</em> panel which includes members of the public, representatives of sexual health voluntary sector organisations, young people's groups and sexual health professionals.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="424" ordby="600" name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="139" ordby="610" id="426" name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The type of supporting evidence is graded and identified for select recommendations (see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field).</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="427" ordby="700" name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="152" ordby="705" id="428" name="Potential Benefits" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Appropriate management of individuals with chancroid</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="153" ordby="710" id="429" name="Potential Harms" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Although erythromycin is efficacious (with cure rates of 93% noted in Kenya and India), poor compliance and gastrointestinal intolerance make alternative therapy desirable.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="430" ordby="800" name="Contraindications">
    <field fieldid="144" ordby="805" id="431" name="Contraindications" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Ciprofloxacin is contraindicated for pregnant and lactating women, children, and adolescents less than 18 years of age.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="432" ordby="900" name="Qualifying Statements">
    <field fieldid="137" ordby="905" id="433" name="Qualifying Statements" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Suggestions for diagnostic approaches made in this guideline should be tailored to local resources. This guideline recommends the use of nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) and culture tests to diagnose <em>Haemophilus ducreyi</em> infection. However, these tests may not be routinely available except in specialised laboratories.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="434" ordby="1000" name="Implementation of the Guideline">
    <field fieldid="131" ordby="1010" id="436" name="Description of Implementation Strategy" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>An implementation strategy was not provided.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="117" ordby="1015" id="437" name="Implementation Tools" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Audit Criteria/Indicators"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="439" ordby="1100" name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories">
    <field fieldid="50" ordby="1105" id="440" name="IOM Care Need" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Getting Better"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="51" ordby="1110" id="441" name="IOM Domain" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Effectiveness"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Patient-centeredness"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="442" ordby="1200" name="Identifying Information and Availability">
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="1201" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Clinical Effectiveness Group. UK national guideline for the management of chancroid. London (UK): British Association for Sexual Health and HIV (BASHH); 2014 Mar. 22 p.  [63 references]</td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="124" ordby="1205" id="443" name="Adaptation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="128" ordby="1215" id="445" name="Date Released" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="1999 Aug (revised 2014 Mar)"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="158" ordby="1225" id="447" name="Guideline Developer(s)" type="orglist-p">
      <fieldvalue value="British Association for Sexual Health and HIV - Medical Specialty Society"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="125" ordby="1235" id="449" name="Source(s) of Funding" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This guideline was commissioned, edited and endorsed by the British Association for Sexual Health and HIV (BASHH) Clinical Effectiveness Group (CEG) without external funding being sought or obtained.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="126" ordby="1240" id="450" name="Guideline Committee" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Clinical Effectiveness Group (CEG)</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="127" ordby="1245" id="451" name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><em>Authors</em>: Dr Nigel O'Farrell, Pasteur Suite, Ealing Hospital, London, UK; Dr Neil Lazaro, Dept of Genitourinary (GU) Medicine, Royal Preston Hospital, Preston, Lancashire, UK</p>
<p><em>Clinical Effectiveness Group (CEG) Members</em>: Dr Keith Radcliffe (<em>Chair</em>); Dr Mark FitzGerald; Dr Deepa Grover; Dr Stephen Higgins; Dr Margaret Kingston; Dr Neil Lazaro; Dr Louise Melvin; Dr Ann Sullivan</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="147" ordby="1250" id="452" name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>None declared</p>
<p>All members of the guideline writing committee completed the British Association for Sexual Health and HIV (BASHH) conflict of interest declaration at the time the guideline's final draft was submitted to the Clinical Effectiveness Group (CEG).</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="1256" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p>
<p>This guideline updates a previous version: Association for Genitourinary Medicine (AGUM), Medical Society for the Study of Venereal Disease (MSSVD). 2002 national guideline for the management of chancroid. London: Association for Genitourinary Medicine (AGUM), Medical Society for the Study of Venereal Disease (MSSVD); 2002. Various p. [51 references]</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="118" ordby="1260" id="454" name="Guideline Availability" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Electronic copies: Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.bashh.org/documents/Chancroid%202014%20.pdf&quot; title=&quot;British Association for Sexual Health and HIV Web site&quot;>British Association for Sexual Health and HIV Web site</a>.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="119" ordby="1265" id="455" name="Availability of Companion Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The following is available:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Clinical Effectiveness Group. British Association for Sexual Health and HIV: framework for guideline development and assessment. London (UK): British Association for Sexual Health and HIV (BASHH); 2010. 18 p. Electronic copies: Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.bashh.org/documents/2926.pdf&quot; title=&quot;British Association for Sexual Health and HIV Web site&quot;>British Association for Sexual Health and HIV Web site</a>. </li>
</ul>
<p>In addition, auditable outcomes measures are provided in the <a href=&quot;http://www.bashh.org/documents/Chancroid%202014%20.pdf&quot; title=&quot;British Association for Sexual Health and HIV Web site&quot;>original guideline document</a>.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="143" ordby="1275" id="457" name="Patient Resources" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>None available</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="142" ordby="1280" id="458" name="NGC Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This summary was completed by ECRI on December 8, 2000. The information was verified by the guideline developer on January 12, 2001. This summary was updated on June 24, 2002. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on October 3, 2007 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) advisory on Rocephin (ceftriaxone sodium). This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on June 24, 2014. The updated information was verified by the guideline developer on July 24, 2014. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on May 18, 2016 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on Fluoroquinolone Antibacterial Drugs.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="141" ordby="1290" id="460" name="Copyright Statement" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developers and/or BMJ Publishing Group's copyright restrictions. Reproduction and use of this guideline is permitted provided that (a) the original content is not changed or edited; and, (b) any content derived from the original guideline is acknowledged as that of the author(s) and responsible organizations.</p>
<p>Readers wishing to download and reproduce material for purposes other than personal study or education should contact BMJPG to seek permission first. Contact: BMJ Publishing Group, BMA House, Tavistock Square, WC1H 9JR, UK.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="99999" ordby="99999" name="Disclaimer">
    <field fieldid="99999" ordby="99999" id="99999" name="NGC Disclaimer" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<p>The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.</p> 
<p>All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.</p> 
<p>Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the <a href=&quot;/help-and-about/summaries/inclusion-criteria&quot;>NGC Inclusion Criteria</a>.</p> 
<p>NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.</p> 
<p>Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.</p>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
</version><!--
     FILE ARCHIVED ON 21:43:37 Jul 12, 2018 AND RETRIEVED FROM THE
     INTERNET ARCHIVE ON 00:16:25 Jul 16, 2018.
     JAVASCRIPT APPENDED BY WAYBACK MACHINE, COPYRIGHT INTERNET ARCHIVE.

     ALL OTHER CONTENT MAY ALSO BE PROTECTED BY COPYRIGHT (17 U.S.C.
     SECTION 108(a)(3)).
-->
<!--
playback timings (ms):
  LoadShardBlock: 62.971 (3)
  esindex: 0.008
  captures_list: 96.786
  CDXLines.iter: 27.022 (3)
  PetaboxLoader3.datanode: 115.735 (4)
  exclusion.robots: 0.363
  exclusion.robots.policy: 0.343
  RedisCDXSource: 2.747
  PetaboxLoader3.resolve: 78.365
  load_resource: 142.048
-->