<script src="//archive.org/includes/analytics.js?v=cf34f82" type="text/javascript"></script>
<script type="text/javascript">window.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded',function(){var v=archive_analytics.values;v.service='wb';v.server_name='wwwb-app40.us.archive.org';v.server_ms=897;archive_analytics.send_pageview({});});</script><script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/wbhack.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<script type="text/javascript">
__wbhack.init('https://web.archive.org/web');
</script>
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/banner-styles.css?v=1531166943.0" />
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/iconochive.css?v=1531166943.0" />

<!-- End Wayback Rewrite JS Include --><!-- BEGIN WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT -->
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/timestamp.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/graph-calc.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/auto-complete.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/toolbar.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<style type="text/css">
body {
  margin-top:0 !important;
  padding-top:0 !important;
  /*min-width:800px !important;*/
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestions {
    text-align: left; cursor: default; border: 1px solid #ccc; border-top: 0; background: #fff; box-shadow: -1px 1px 3px rgba(0,0,0,.1);
    position: absolute; display: none; z-index: 2147483647; max-height: 254px; overflow: hidden; overflow-y: auto; box-sizing: border-box;
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion { position: relative; padding: 0 .6em; line-height: 23px; white-space: nowrap; overflow: hidden; text-overflow: ellipsis; font-size: 1.02em; color: #333; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion b { font-weight: bold; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion.selected { background: #f0f0f0; }
</style>
<div id="wm-ipp" lang="en" style="display:none;direction:ltr;">
<div style="position:fixed;left:0;top:0;right:0;">
<div id="wm-ipp-inside">
  <div style="position:relative;">
    <div id="wm-logo" style="float:left;width:130px;padding-top:10px;">
      <a href="/web/" title="Wayback Machine home page"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wayback-toolbar-logo.png" alt="Wayback Machine" width="110" height="39" border="0" /></a>
    </div>
    <div class="r" style="float:right;">
      <div id="wm-btns" style="text-align:right;height:25px;">
                  <div id="wm-save-snapshot-success">success</div>
          <div id="wm-save-snapshot-fail">fail</div>
          <a href="#"
             onclick="__wm.saveSnapshot('https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9823?contentType=xml', '20180713003145')"
             title="Share via My Web Archive"
             id="wm-save-snapshot-open"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-web"></span>
          </a>
          <a href="https://archive.org/account/login.php"
             title="Sign In"
             id="wm-sign-in"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-person"></span>
          </a>
          <span id="wm-save-snapshot-in-progress" class="iconochive-web"></span>
        	<a href="http://faq.web.archive.org/" title="Get some help using the Wayback Machine" style="top:-6px;"><span class="iconochive-question" style="color:rgb(87,186,244);font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a id="wm-tb-close" href="#close" onclick="__wm.h(event);return false;" style="top:-2px;" title="Close the toolbar"><span class="iconochive-remove-circle" style="color:#888888;font-size:240%;"></span></a>
      </div>
      <div id="wm-share" style="text-align:right;">
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://web.archive.org/web/20180713003145/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9823?contentType=xml', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Facebook" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-facebook" style="color:#3b5998;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=https://web.archive.org/web/20180713003145/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9823?contentType=xml&amp;via=internetarchive', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Twitter" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-twitter" style="color:#1dcaff;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
      </div>
    </div>
    <table class="c" style="">
      <tbody>
	<tr>
	  <td class="u" colspan="2">
	    <form target="_top" method="get" action="/web/submit" name="wmtb" id="wmtb"><input type="text" name="url" id="wmtbURL" value="https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9823?contentType=xml" onfocus="this.focus();this.select();" /><input type="hidden" name="type" value="replay" /><input type="hidden" name="date" value="20180713003145" /><input type="submit" value="Go" /></form>
	  </td>
	  <td class="n" rowspan="2" style="width:110px;">
	    <table>
	      <tbody>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV MONTH NAV AND MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="m">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180610072721/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9823?contentType=xml" title="10 Jun 2018"><strong>Jun</strong></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayMonthEl" title="You are here: 00:31:45 Jul 13, 2018">JUL</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">Aug</td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV CAPTURE NAV AND DAY OF MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="d">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180610072721/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9823?contentType=xml" title="07:27:21 Jun 10, 2018"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_prv_on.png" alt="Previous capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayDayEl" style="width:34px;font-size:24px;white-space:nowrap;" title="You are here: 00:31:45 Jul 13, 2018">13</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_nxt_off.png" alt="Next capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV YEAR NAV AND YEAR INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="y">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160930173803/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9823?contentType=xml" title="30 Sep 2016"><strong>2016</strong></a></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayYearEl" title="You are here: 00:31:45 Jul 13, 2018">2018</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">2019</td>
		</tr>
	      </tbody>
	    </table>
	  </td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td class="s">
	    	    <div id="wm-nav-captures">
	      	      <a class="t" href="/web/20180713003145*/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9823?contentType=xml" title="See a list of every capture for this URL">6 captures</a>
	      <div class="r" title="Timespan for captures of this URL">30 Sep 2016 - 13 Jul 2018</div>
	      </div>
	  </td>
	  <td class="k">
	    <a href="" id="wm-graph-anchor">
	      <div id="wm-ipp-sparkline" title="Explore captures for this URL" style="position: relative">
		<canvas id="wm-sparkline-canvas" width="575" height="27" border="0"></canvas>
	      </div>
	    </a>
	  </td>
	</tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <div style="position:absolute;bottom:0;right:2px;text-align:right;">
      <a id="wm-expand" class="wm-btn wm-closed" href="#expand" onclick="__wm.ex(event);return false;"><span id="wm-expand-icon" class="iconochive-down-solid"></span> <span style="font-size:80%">About this capture</span></a>
    </div>
  </div>
    <div id="wm-capinfo" style="border-top:1px solid #777;display:none; overflow: hidden">
            <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center">COLLECTED BY</div>
    <div style="padding:3px;position:relative" id="wm-collected-by-content">
            <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:50%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/archiveteam);"></span>
		Organization: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/archiveteam" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">Archive Team</span></a>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  <img align=right src="http://archiveteam.org/images/e/e6/Archiveteam.jpg" width=200> Formed in 2009, the Archive Team (not to be confused with the archive.org Archive-It Team) is a rogue archivist collective dedicated to saving copies of rapidly dying or deleted websites for the sake of history and digital heritage. The group is 100% composed of volunteers and interested parties, and has expanded into a large amount of related projects for saving online and digital history.
<p>
History is littered with hundreds of conflicts over the future of a community, group, location or business that were "resolved" when one of the parties stepped ahead and destroyed what was there. With the original point of contention destroyed, the debates would fall to the wayside. Archive Team believes that by duplicated condemned data, the conversation and debate can continue, as well as the richness and insight gained by keeping the materials. Our projects have ranged in size from a single volunteer downloading the data to a small-but-critical site, to over 100 volunteers stepping forward to acquire terabytes of user-created data to save for future generations.
<p>
The main site for Archive Team is at <a href="http://www.archiveteam.org">archiveteam.org</a> and contains up to the date information on various projects, manifestos, plans and walkthroughs.
<p>
This collection contains the output of many Archive Team projects, both ongoing and completed. Thanks to the generous providing of disk space by the Internet Archive, multi-terabyte datasets can be made available, as well as in use by the <a href="http://archive.org/web/web.php">Wayback Machine</a>, providing a path back to lost websites and work. 
<p>
Our collection has grown to the point of having sub-collections for the type of data we acquire. If you are seeking to browse the contents of these collections, the Wayback Machine is the best first stop. Otherwise, you are free to dig into the stacks to see what you may find.
<p>
<b>The Archive Team Panic Downloads</b> are full pulldowns of currently extant websites, meant to serve as emergency backups for needed sites that are in danger of closing, or which will be missed dearly if suddenly lost due to hard drive crashes or server failures. 
<p>
	</div>
	      </div>
      <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:49%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/archivebot)"></span>
		<div>Collection: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/archivebot" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">ArchiveBot: The Archive Team Crowdsourced Crawler</span></a></div>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  ArchiveBot is an IRC bot designed to automate the archival of smaller websites (e.g. up to a few hundred thousand URLs). You give it a URL to start at, and it grabs all content under that URL, records it in a WARC, and then uploads that WARC to ArchiveTeam servers for eventual injection into the Internet Archive (or other archive sites).
<p>
To use ArchiveBot, drop by #archivebot on EFNet. To interact with ArchiveBot, you issue commands by typing it into the channel. Note you will need channel operator permissions in order to issue archiving jobs. The dashboard shows the sites being downloaded currently.
<p>
There is a dashboard running for the archivebot process at <a href="http://www.archivebot.com">http://www.archivebot.com</a>.
<p>
ArchiveBot's source code can be found at <a href="https://github.com/ArchiveTeam/ArchiveBot">https://github.com/ArchiveTeam/ArchiveBot</a>.
	</div>
	      </div>
    </div>
    <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center" title="Timestamps for the elements of this page">TIMESTAMPS</div>
    <div>
      <div id="wm-capresources" style="margin:0 5px 5px 5px;max-height:250px;overflow-y:scroll !important"></div>
      <div id="wm-capresources-loading" style="text-align:left;margin:0 20px 5px 5px;display:none"><img src="/static/images/loading.gif" alt="loading" /></div>
    </div>
  </div></div></div></div><script type="text/javascript">
__wm.bt(575,27,25,2,"web","https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-9823?contentType=xml","2018-07-13",1996);
</script>
<!-- END WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT --><version>
  <xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource>
  <section secid="390" ordby="100" name="General">
    <field fieldid="161" ordby="105" id="391" name="Guideline Title" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_title&quot;>Screening for prostate cancer: a guidance statement from the Clinical Guidelines Committee of the American College of Physicians.</div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="110" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Qaseem A, Barry MJ, Denberg TD, Owens DK, Shekelle P. Screening for prostate cancer: a guidance statement from the Clinical Guidelines Committee of the American College of Physicians. Ann Intern Med. 2013 May 21;158(10):761-9. [25 references] <a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=23567643&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;>PubMed</a></td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="115" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="420" ordby="300" name="Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="151" ordby="310" id="421" name="Major Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>On the basis of the review of the available guidelines, the American College of Physicians (ACP) concludes:</p>
<p><em><strong>Guidance Statement 1</strong>: ACP recommends that clinicians inform men between the age of 50 and 69 years about the limited potential benefits and substantial harms of screening for prostate cancer. ACP recommends that clinicians base the decision to screen for prostate cancer using the prostate-specific antigen test on the risk for prostate cancer, a discussion of the benefits and harms of screening, the patient's general health and life expectancy, and patient preferences. ACP recommends that clinicians should not screen for prostate cancer using the prostate-specific antigen test in patients who do not express a clear preference for screening.</em></p>
<p><strong>Benefits and Harms of Screening (Prostate-Specific Antigen [PSA] Test and Digital Rectal Examination [DRE])</strong></p>
<p>The modest potential mortality benefit in 1 prostate cancer screening trial with the PSA test was limited to men between the age of 55 and 69 years. Data were insufficient to reach a conclusion about the benefits or harms of screening in men aged 50 to 54 years. However, because this group has a longer life expectancy, they have more potential for long-term net benefit. The European Randomized Study of Screening for Prostate Cancer (ERSPC) study, which screened men mostly with the PSA test, showed that 1410 men would need to be screened to prevent 1 death from prostate cancer. Evidence for the benefit of DRE screening is limited, and the Prostate, Lung, Colorectal, and Ovarian (PLCO) trial, which included both PSA testing and DRE, showed no benefit. As far as mortality benefit is concerned, the evidence is inconsistent about whether screening reduces cancer-related death, and any absolute mortality risk reduction is probably small to none.</p>
<p>The harms of prostate cancer screening are substantial and include false alarms (suggesting that a patient may have cancer when he does not) related to high false-positive rates associated with DRE and especially the PSA test, overdiagnosis (that is, detecting cancer that will not cause future morbidity and mortality), high false-negative rates, anxiety, and discomfort. Positive screening results may lead to further testing, such as biopsies, which not only can be painful but can also lead to complications, such as infections, as well as overtreatment and the harms associated with it. In addition, currently available treatments are associated with harms, such as urinary, gastrointestinal, and sexual problems, as well as potential cardiovascular events and death. Data from Prostate Cancer Intervention Versus Observation Trial (PIVOT) showed that men who had radical prostatectomy had an 11% increased risk for urinary incontinence and a 37% increased risk for erectile dysfunction. Harms specific to DRE include discomfort and rectal bleeding.</p>
<p><strong>Shared Decision-Making Approach</strong></p>
<p>Clinicians should not screen for prostate cancer in men who do not wish to make the screening decision or do not express a clear preference about screening. However, some men would still prefer to be screened because they may put more value on the possible small benefit and less value on the harms. In these circumstances, shared decision-making is important in making choices about prostate cancer screening. Clinicians should elicit patient preferences for screening during the shared decision-making process and document them in the medical record. It is important to educate the patient about the following points and document the conversation in the medical record:</p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;>
    <li>Prostate cancer screening with the PSA test is controversial. </li>
    <li>Screening with the PSA test can detect prostate cancer, but for most men, the chances of harm from screening with the PSA test outweigh the chances of benefit. </li>
    <li>A small number of prostate cancer cases are serious and can cause death; however, the vast majority of prostate cancer is slow-growing and does not cause death. </li>
    <li>Most men who choose not to do PSA testing will not be diagnosed with prostate cancer and will die of something else. </li>
    <li>Patients who choose PSA testing are much more likely than those who decline PSA testing to be diagnosed with prostate cancer. </li>
    <li>The PSA test often does not distinguish between serious cancer and nonserious cancer. However, men with markedly elevated PSA levels (&amp;gt;10 &amp;micro;g/L) may have a reduced chance of dying from prostate cancer by having surgical treatment. </li>
    <li>The small potential benefit of prostate cancer screening corresponds to preventing, at most, 1 death caused by prostate cancer per 1000 men screened after 11 years of follow-up. </li>
    <li>There are many potential harms of screening. There may be problems in interpreting test results: The PSA test result may be high because of an enlarged prostate but not because of cancer, or it may be low even though cancer is present. Prostate biopsy, if needed, is also not free from risk. It involves multiple needles being inserted into the prostate under local anesthesia, and there is risk for infection or clinically significant bleeding and hospitalization (1.4%). If cancer is diagnosed, it will often be treated with surgery or radiation, which are associated with risks. There is a small risk for death with surgery, loss of sexual function (approximately 37% higher risk), and loss of control of urination (approximately 11% higher risk) compared with no surgery. These risks may vary depending on patient and surgeon characteristics and treatment method. </li>
    <li>The PSA test is not &quot;just a blood test.&quot; It is a test that can open the door to more testing and treatment that a man may not actually want and that may actually harm him. A man's chances of being harmed are much greater than his chances of benefiting from the PSA test. Thus, each man should have the opportunity to decide for himself whether to have the PSA screening test. </li>
    <li>Studies are ongoing, so clinicians expect to learn more about the benefits and harms of screening, and recommendations may change over time. Men are also welcome to change their minds at any time by asking for screening that they have previously declined or discontinue screening that they have previously requested. </li>
</ol>
<p>Although ACP did not evaluate the evidence on the reliability, validity, or benefits of using available decision aids, some examples are listed in Table 2 in the original guideline document.</p>
<p>It is important for clinicians to convey to patients who may want to be screened that evidence indicates, at best, small benefits as well as substantial harms. Men who do not have a clear preference for screening should not be screened, and this should be documented. Clinicians should help men judge the balance of benefits and harms and discuss whether the harms outweigh the potential reduction in prostate cancer mortality in their particular cases. To frame the discussion, clinicians can inform patients that the PSA test will increase their lifetime risk for prostate cancer from approximately 9% to 16%. Currently, the tradeoff between harms and benefits beyond 11 to 13 years of follow-up is unknown. Alternatively, although 3 in 100 men will die of prostate cancer (or 5 in 100 for African American men), this means that 97 in 100 men (or 95 in 100 African American men) will die of something else. Finally, although some men may avoid pain and discomfort commonly associated with advanced disease, this must be balanced against the possibility of incontinence, erectile dysfunction, and other side effects that result from certain forms of aggressive treatment.</p>
<p>The goal of screening for any disease is to identify an undiagnosed condition for which an effective treatment is available, and timely treatment can lead to improved clinical outcomes. Although the best treatment approach for prostate cancer is unknown, current management for prostate cancer includes active surveillance, radical prostatectomy, external beam radiation therapy, and brachytherapy. Research is needed to better identify cancer that is more likely to benefit from curative treatments, in which case, benefits are more likely to outweigh harms.</p>
<p><strong>High-Risk Patients</strong></p>
<p>Screening in high-risk men has not been demonstrated to be associated with different outcomes than screening in average-risk men. Risks for prostate cancer include African American race and a first-degree relative diagnosed with prostate cancer, especially before age 65 years. Patients with such risks should receive information about the uncertainties, risks, and potential benefits associated with prostate cancer screening beginning at age 45 years. Shared decision making is important in making choices about prostate cancer screening in high-risk men as well. Men at appreciably higher risk (multiple family members diagnosed with prostate cancer before age 65 years) should receive this information beginning at age 40 years.</p>
<p><strong>Frequency of Screening</strong></p>
<p>Currently, no clear evidence is available to guide decisions about the periodicity or frequency of the evaluation of risk for prostate cancer or discussion about the benefits and harms. Considering the harms of screening and modest mortality benefit, increasing the interval between screening tests may reduce harms. The PLCO trial, which screened annually, found no benefit, whereas the ERSPC trial, in which most participants were screened every 4 years (range, 2 to 7 years), did find benefit, suggesting that longer intervals may be indicated.</p>
<p><em><strong>Guidance Statement 2</strong>: ACP recommends that clinicians should not screen for prostate cancer using the prostate-specific antigen test in average-risk men under the age of 50 years, men over the age of 69 years, or men with a life expectancy of less than 10 to 15 years.</em></p>
<p>Increasing age or the presence of a chronic comorbid illness that affects life expectancy substantially limits the potential benefits of prostate cancer screening compared with harms. Evidence presented in the guidelines shows substantial harms associated with prostate cancer screening and treatment relative to questionable benefits. Any benefit is even smaller in men older than 69 years because the cancer may not become clinically significant in a person's lifetime. For men younger than 50 years, the harms, such as erectile dysfunction and urinary incontinence, carry even more weight relative to any potential benefit. Hence, the harms of screening for prostate cancer outweigh the benefits in average-risk men younger than 50 years, men older than 69 years, or men who have a life expectancy less than 10 to 15 years. Therefore, clinicians should not screen men younger than 50 years, those aged 70 years or older, or men with substantial comorbid conditions and a life expectancy less than 10 to 15 years.</p>
<p>The figure in the original guideline document summarizes the guidance statements and clinical considerations for prostate cancer screening.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="138" ordby="330" id="423" name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>None provided</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="396" ordby="400" name="Scope">
    <field fieldid="140" ordby="405" id="397" name="Disease/Condition(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Prostate cancer</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="103" ordby="410" id="398" name="Guideline Category" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Counseling"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Risk Assessment"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Screening"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="113" ordby="415" id="399" name="Clinical Specialty" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Family Practice"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Internal Medicine"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Oncology"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Preventive Medicine"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Urology"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="114" ordby="420" id="400" name="Intended Users" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Physicians"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="129" ordby="425" id="401" name="Guideline Objective(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>To critically review the available guidelines developed in the United States to help guide internists and other clinicians in making decisions about screening for prostate cancer</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="132" ordby="430" id="402" name="Target Population" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Adult men</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="133" ordby="435" id="403" name="Interventions and Practices Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Screening for prostate cancer using the prostate-specific antigen (PSA) test:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Informing men between the ages of 50 and 69 years about the benefits/harms of screening for prostate cancer </li>
    <li>Basing the decision to screen for prostate cancer on the risk for prostate cancer, a discussion of the benefits and harms of screening, the patient's general health and life expectancy, and patient preferences </li>
</ul></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="134" ordby="440" id="404" name="Major Outcomes Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Sensitivity and specificity of diagnostic tests (prostate-specific antigen [PSA] and digital rectal examination [DRE]) </li>
    <li>Morbidity and mortality due to prostate cancer </li>
    <li>Harms of prostate cancer screening and related treatments </li>
    <li>Benefits and risks of prostate cancer screening in selected age groups </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="405" ordby="500" name="Methodology">
    <field fieldid="109" ordby="505" id="406" name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Searches of Electronic Databases"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="135" ordby="510" id="407" name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The Clinical Guidelines Committee of the American College of Physicians (ACP) began by searching the National Guideline Clearinghouse for guidelines on screening for prostate cancer (August 2012). They reviewed the titles and abstracts of each document. The committee excluded those that were obviously restating guidelines from other organizations. Four prostate cancer screening guidelines developed in the United States were selected: American College of Preventive Medicine (ACPM), American Cancer Society (ACS), American Urological Association (AUA), and U.S. Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF).</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="136" ordby="515" id="408" name="Number of Source Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This guideline is adapted from 4 U.S. prostate cancer screening guideline sources.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="115" ordby="520" id="409" name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Not stated"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="149" ordby="525" id="410" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not applicable</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="116" ordby="530" id="411" name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Review"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="150" ordby="535" id="412" name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The selected prostate cancer screening guidelines were reviewed independently by 4 coauthors. The authors followed the Appraisal of Guidelines Research and Evaluation (AGREE) II collaboration method to produce this guidance statement. The AGREE II instrument asks 23 questions in 6 domains: scope and purpose, stakeholder involvement, rigor of development, clarity and presentation, applicability, and editorial independence. The authors selected 1 guideline to calibrate their scores on the 6 domains of the AGREE II instrument. The authors then scored each guideline independently, and the scores were compared (see Table 1 in the original guideline document). Although total quantitative scores varied, the qualitative assessment of guideline quality was consistent among the 4 reviewers; indeed, the overall rankings of the quality of the guidelines were similar.</p>
<p>Details of the American College of Physicians (ACP) guidance statement development process can be found in ACP's methods paper (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="112" ordby="540" id="413" name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Expert Consensus"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="145" ordby="545" id="414" name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>When several guidelines are available on a topic or existing guidelines conflict, the American College of Physicians (ACP) believes that it is more useful to provide clinicians with a rigorous review of the available guidelines rather than develop a new guideline on the same topic. Thus, the ACP Clinical Guidelines Committee developed this guidance statement for clinicians by assessing current guidelines developed by other organizations on screening for prostate cancer.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="146" ordby="550" id="415" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not applicable</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="148" ordby="565" id="417" name="Cost Analysis" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>American College of Physicians High-Value Care Advice</strong></p>
<p>High-value care reflects care for which the benefits are likely to outweigh the harms and costs associated with delivering such care. Screening with the prostate-specific antigen (PSA) test is low-value care. The value of screening for prostate cancer in most cases is low, given that the chances of harm with screening outweigh the chances of benefit for most men and that the direct and indirect costs associated with biopsy, repeated testing, aggressive therapy, patient anxiety, and missed work are significant.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="104" ordby="570" id="418" name="Method of Guideline Validation" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Internal Peer Review"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="130" ordby="575" id="419" name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Approved by the American College of Physicians (ACP) Board of Regents on April 16, 2012.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="424" ordby="600" name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="139" ordby="610" id="426" name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The guidance statements are derived from other organizations' guidelines and are based on an evaluation of strengths and limitations of the available guidelines (see the &quot;Adaption&quot; field for full citations).</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="427" ordby="700" name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="152" ordby="705" id="428" name="Potential Benefits" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The small potential benefit of prostate cancer screening corresponds to preventing, at most, 1 death caused by prostate cancer per 1000 men screened after 11 years of follow-up.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="153" ordby="710" id="429" name="Potential Harms" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>The harms of prostate cancer screening are substantial and include false alarms (suggesting that a patient may have cancer when he does not) related to high false-positive rates associated with digital rectal examination (DRE) and especially the prostate-specific antigen (PSA) test, overdiagnosis (that is, detecting cancer that will not cause future morbidity and mortality), high false-negative rates, anxiety, and discomfort. </li>
    <li>Positive screening results may lead to further testing, such as biopsies, which not only can be painful but can also lead to complications, such as infections, as well as overtreatment and the harms associated with it. In addition, currently available treatments are associated with harms, such as urinary, gastrointestinal, and sexual problems, as well as potential cardiovascular events and death. Data from Prostate Cancer Intervention Versus Observation Trial (PIVOT) showed that men who had radical prostatectomy had an 11% increased risk for urinary incontinence and a 37% increased risk for erectile dysfunction. Harms specific to DRE include discomfort and rectal bleeding. </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="432" ordby="900" name="Qualifying Statements">
    <field fieldid="137" ordby="905" id="433" name="Qualifying Statements" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Clinical guidance statements are &quot;guides&quot; only and may not apply to all patients and clinical situations. Thus, they are not intended to override clinicians' judgment. All American College of Physicians (ACP) clinical guidance statements are considered automatically withdrawn or invalid 5 years after publication, or once an update has been issued. </li>
    <li>The authors of this article are responsible for its contents, including any clinical or treatment recommendations. </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="434" ordby="1000" name="Implementation of the Guideline">
    <field fieldid="131" ordby="1010" id="436" name="Description of Implementation Strategy" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>An implementation strategy was not provided.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="117" ordby="1015" id="437" name="Implementation Tools" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Foreign Language Translations"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Mobile Device Resources"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Patient Resources"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Resources"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Staff Training/Competency Material"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="439" ordby="1100" name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories">
    <field fieldid="50" ordby="1105" id="440" name="IOM Care Need" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Staying Healthy"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="51" ordby="1110" id="441" name="IOM Domain" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Effectiveness"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Patient-centeredness"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="442" ordby="1200" name="Identifying Information and Availability">
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="1201" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Qaseem A, Barry MJ, Denberg TD, Owens DK, Shekelle P. Screening for prostate cancer: a guidance statement from the Clinical Guidelines Committee of the American College of Physicians. Ann Intern Med. 2013 May 21;158(10):761-9. [25 references] <a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=23567643&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;>PubMed</a></td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="124" ordby="1205" id="443" name="Adaptation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This guideline is adapted from the following primary sources:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Lim LS, Sherin K; American College of Preventive Medicine (ACPM) Prevention Practice Committee. Screening for prostate cancer in U.S. men ACPM position statement on preventive practice. <em>Am J Prev Med</em>. 2008;34:164-70. </li>
    <li>Wolf AM, Wender RC, Etzioni RB, Thompson IM, D'Amico AV, Volk RJ, et al; American Cancer Society Prostate Cancer Advisory Committee. American Cancer Society guideline for the early detection of prostate cancer: update 2010. <em>CA Cancer J Clin</em>. 2010;60:70-98. </li>
    <li>Greene KL, Albertsen PC, Babaian RJ, Carter HB, Gann PH, Han M, et al. Prostate specific antigen best practice statement: 2009 update. <em>J Urol</em>. 2009;182: 2232-41. </li>
    <li>U.S. Preventive Services Task Force. Screening for prostate cancer: U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommendation statement. <em>Ann Intern Med</em>. 2008;149:185-91. </li>
</ul></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="128" ordby="1215" id="445" name="Date Released" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="2013 May 21"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="158" ordby="1225" id="447" name="Guideline Developer(s)" type="orglist-p">
      <fieldvalue value="American College of Physicians - Medical Specialty Society"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="125" ordby="1235" id="449" name="Source(s) of Funding" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Financial support for the development of this guideline comes exclusively from the American College of Physicians (ACP) operating budget.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="126" ordby="1240" id="450" name="Guideline Committee" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>American College of Physicians (ACP) Clinical Guidelines Committee</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="127" ordby="1245" id="451" name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><em>Primary Authors</em>: Amir Qaseem, MD, PhD, MHA; Michael J. Barry, MD; Thomas D. Denberg, MD, PhD; Douglas K. Owens, MD, MS; and Paul Shekelle, MD, PhD</p>
<p><em>Clinical Guidelines Committee of the American College of Physicians</em>: Paul Shekelle, MD, PhD (<em>Chair</em>); Roger Chou, MD; Molly Cooke, MD; Paul Dallas, MD; Thomas D. Denberg, MD, PhD; Nick Fitterman, MD; Mary Ann Forciea, MD; Robert H. Hopkins Jr., MD; Linda L. Humphrey, MD, MPH; Tanveer P. Mir, MD; Douglas K. Owens, MD, MS; Holger J. Sch&amp;uuml;nemann, MD, PhD; Donna E. Sweet, MD; David S. Weinberg, MD, MSc; and Timothy Wilt, MD, MPH</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="147" ordby="1250" id="452" name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Dr. Barry: <em>Board membership and employment</em>: Informed Medical Decisions Foundation; <em>Royalties</em>: Health Dialog. Dr. Owens: <em>Support for travel to meetings</em>: ACP. Dr. Shekelle: <em>Consultancy</em>: ECRI Institute; <em>Employment</em>: Veterans Affairs; <em>Grants/grants pending (money to institution)</em>: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, Veterans Affairs, Centers for Medicare &amp;amp; Medicaid Services, National Institute of Nursing Research, Office of the National Coordinator; Royalties: UpToDate.</p>
<p>All other authors have no disclosures.</p>
<p>Disclosures can also be viewed at <a href=&quot;https://www.acponline.org/authors/icmje/ConflictOfInterestForms.do?msNum=M12-2408&quot; title=&quot;ACP Web site&quot;>www.acponline.org/authors/icmje/ConflictOf InterestForms.do?msNum=M12-2408</a>. A record of conflicts of interest is kept for each Clinical Guidelines Committee meeting and conference call and can be viewed at <a href=&quot;http://www.acponline.org/clinical_information/guidelines/guidelines/conflicts_cgc.htm&quot; tilte=&quot;ACP Web site&quot;>www.acponline.org/clinical_information/guidelines/guidelines/conflicts_cgc.htm</a>.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="1256" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="118" ordby="1260" id="454" name="Guideline Availability" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Available from the <a href=&quot;http://annals.org/article.aspx?articleid=1676183&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;>Annals of Internal Medicine Web site</a>.</p>
<p>Print copies: Available from the American College of Physicians (ACP), 190 N. Independence Mall West, Philadelphia PA 19106-1572.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="119" ordby="1265" id="455" name="Availability of Companion Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The following are available:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Qaseem A, Snow V, Owens DK, Shekelle P. The development of clinical practice guidelines and guidance statements of the American College of Physicians: summary of methods. Ann Intern Med. 2010 Aug 3;153(3):194-199. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.annals.org/content/153/3/194.full&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;>Annals of Internal Medicine Web site</a>. </li>
    <li>Screening for prostate cancer. Continuing Medical Education. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://annals.org/article.aspx?articleid=1676183&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;>Annals of Internal Medicine Web site</a>. </li>
    <li>Prostate cancer screening recommendations. Video. Available from the <a href=&quot;http://annals.org/article.aspx?articleid=1676183&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;>Annals of Internal Medicine Web site</a>. </li>
</ul>
<p>Print copies: Available from the American College of Physicians (ACP), 190 N. Independence Mall West, Philadelphia PA 19106-1572.</p>
<p>A summary version of the guideline is available in Chinese from the <a href=&quot;http://www.acponline.org/journals/annals/abstracts/china/0000605-201305210-00011_chinese.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;>Annals of Internal Medicine Web site</a>.</p>
<p>A collection of Recommendation Summaries for all current American College of Physicians Clinical Guidelines is now available for Personal Digital Assistant (PDA) download from the <a href=&quot;http://www.acponline.org/clinical_information/guidelines/current/#acg&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;>American College of Physicians Web site</a>.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="143" ordby="1275" id="457" name="Patient Resources" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The following is available:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Summaries for patients. Screening for prostate cancer: a guidance statement from the Clinical Guidelines Committee of the American College of Physicians. Electronic copies: Available from the <a href=&quot;http://annals.org/article.aspx?articleID=1676184&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;>Annals of Internal Medicine Web site</a>. </li>
</ul>
<p>Print copies: Available from the American College of Physicians (ACP), 190 N. Independence Mall West, Philadelphia PA 19106-1572.</p>
<p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;>Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="142" ordby="1280" id="458" name="NGC Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This NGC summary was completed by ECRI institute on July 3, 2013.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="141" ordby="1290" id="460" name="Copyright Statement" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="99999" ordby="99999" name="Disclaimer">
    <field fieldid="99999" ordby="99999" id="99999" name="NGC Disclaimer" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<p>The National Guideline Clearinghouse™ (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.</p> 
<p>All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.</p> 
<p>Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the <a href=&quot;/help-and-about/summaries/inclusion-criteria&quot;>NGC Inclusion Criteria</a>.</p> 
<p>NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.</p> 
<p>Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.</p>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
</version><!--
     FILE ARCHIVED ON 00:31:45 Jul 13, 2018 AND RETRIEVED FROM THE
     INTERNET ARCHIVE ON 01:19:17 Jul 16, 2018.
     JAVASCRIPT APPENDED BY WAYBACK MACHINE, COPYRIGHT INTERNET ARCHIVE.

     ALL OTHER CONTENT MAY ALSO BE PROTECTED BY COPYRIGHT (17 U.S.C.
     SECTION 108(a)(3)).
-->
<!--
playback timings (ms):
  LoadShardBlock: 599.82 (3)
  esindex: 0.013
  captures_list: 633.286
  CDXLines.iter: 18.079 (3)
  PetaboxLoader3.datanode: 313.661 (4)
  exclusion.robots: 0.364
  exclusion.robots.policy: 0.349
  RedisCDXSource: 10.843
  PetaboxLoader3.resolve: 240.297 (2)
  load_resource: 223.953
-->