<script src="//archive.org/includes/analytics.js?v=cf34f82" type="text/javascript"></script>
<script type="text/javascript">window.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded',function(){var v=archive_analytics.values;v.service='wb';v.server_name='wwwb-app57.us.archive.org';v.server_ms=1299;archive_analytics.send_pageview({});});</script><script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/wbhack.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<script type="text/javascript">
__wbhack.init('https://web.archive.org/web');
</script>
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/banner-styles.css?v=1531166943.0" />
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/static/css/iconochive.css?v=1531166943.0" />

<!-- End Wayback Rewrite JS Include --><!-- BEGIN WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT -->
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/timestamp.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/graph-calc.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/auto-complete.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="/static/js/toolbar.js?v=1531166943.0" charset="utf-8"></script>

<style type="text/css">
body {
  margin-top:0 !important;
  padding-top:0 !important;
  /*min-width:800px !important;*/
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestions {
    text-align: left; cursor: default; border: 1px solid #ccc; border-top: 0; background: #fff; box-shadow: -1px 1px 3px rgba(0,0,0,.1);
    position: absolute; display: none; z-index: 2147483647; max-height: 254px; overflow: hidden; overflow-y: auto; box-sizing: border-box;
}
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion { position: relative; padding: 0 .6em; line-height: 23px; white-space: nowrap; overflow: hidden; text-overflow: ellipsis; font-size: 1.02em; color: #333; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion b { font-weight: bold; }
.wb-autocomplete-suggestion.selected { background: #f0f0f0; }
</style>
<div id="wm-ipp" lang="en" style="display:none;direction:ltr;">
<div style="position:fixed;left:0;top:0;right:0;">
<div id="wm-ipp-inside">
  <div style="position:relative;">
    <div id="wm-logo" style="float:left;width:130px;padding-top:10px;">
      <a href="/web/" title="Wayback Machine home page"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wayback-toolbar-logo.png" alt="Wayback Machine" width="110" height="39" border="0" /></a>
    </div>
    <div class="r" style="float:right;">
      <div id="wm-btns" style="text-align:right;height:25px;">
                  <div id="wm-save-snapshot-success">success</div>
          <div id="wm-save-snapshot-fail">fail</div>
          <a href="#"
             onclick="__wm.saveSnapshot('https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10517?contentType=xml', '20160930221139')"
             title="Share via My Web Archive"
             id="wm-save-snapshot-open"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-web"></span>
          </a>
          <a href="https://archive.org/account/login.php"
             title="Sign In"
             id="wm-sign-in"
          >
            <span class="iconochive-person"></span>
          </a>
          <span id="wm-save-snapshot-in-progress" class="iconochive-web"></span>
        	<a href="http://faq.web.archive.org/" title="Get some help using the Wayback Machine" style="top:-6px;"><span class="iconochive-question" style="color:rgb(87,186,244);font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a id="wm-tb-close" href="#close" onclick="__wm.h(event);return false;" style="top:-2px;" title="Close the toolbar"><span class="iconochive-remove-circle" style="color:#888888;font-size:240%;"></span></a>
      </div>
      <div id="wm-share" style="text-align:right;">
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://web.archive.org/web/20160930221139/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10517?contentType=xml', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Facebook" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-facebook" style="color:#3b5998;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
	<a href="#" onclick="window.open('https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=https://web.archive.org/web/20160930221139/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10517?contentType=xml&amp;via=internetarchive', '', 'height=400,width=600'); return false;" title="Share on Twitter" style="margin-right:5px;" target="_blank"><span class="iconochive-twitter" style="color:#1dcaff;font-size:160%;"></span></a>
      </div>
    </div>
    <table class="c" style="">
      <tbody>
	<tr>
	  <td class="u" colspan="2">
	    <form target="_top" method="get" action="/web/submit" name="wmtb" id="wmtb"><input type="text" name="url" id="wmtbURL" value="https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10517?contentType=xml" onfocus="this.focus();this.select();" /><input type="hidden" name="type" value="replay" /><input type="hidden" name="date" value="20160930221139" /><input type="submit" value="Go" /></form>
	  </td>
	  <td class="n" rowspan="2" style="width:110px;">
	    <table>
	      <tbody>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV MONTH NAV AND MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="m">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap">Aug</td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayMonthEl" title="You are here: 22:11:39 Sep 30, 2016">SEP</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">Oct</td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV CAPTURE NAV AND DAY OF MONTH INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="d">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_prv_off.png" alt="Previous capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayDayEl" style="width:34px;font-size:24px;white-space:nowrap;" title="You are here: 22:11:39 Sep 30, 2016">30</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap"><img src="/static/images/toolbar/wm_tb_nxt_off.png" alt="Next capture" width="14" height="16" border="0" /></td>
		</tr>
		<!-- NEXT/PREV YEAR NAV AND YEAR INDICATOR -->
		<tr class="y">
		  <td class="b" nowrap="nowrap">2015</td>
		  <td class="c" id="displayYearEl" title="You are here: 22:11:39 Sep 30, 2016">2016</td>
		  <td class="f" nowrap="nowrap">2017</td>
		</tr>
	      </tbody>
	    </table>
	  </td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td class="s">
	    	    <div id="wm-nav-captures">
	      	      <a class="t" href="/web/20160930221139*/https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10517?contentType=xml" title="See a list of every capture for this URL">1 capture</a>
	      <div class="r" title="Timespan for captures of this URL">30 Sep 2016</div>
	      </div>
	  </td>
	  <td class="k">
	    <a href="" id="wm-graph-anchor">
	      <div id="wm-ipp-sparkline" title="Explore captures for this URL" style="position: relative">
		<canvas id="wm-sparkline-canvas" width="575" height="27" border="0"></canvas>
	      </div>
	    </a>
	  </td>
	</tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <div style="position:absolute;bottom:0;right:2px;text-align:right;">
      <a id="wm-expand" class="wm-btn wm-closed" href="#expand" onclick="__wm.ex(event);return false;"><span id="wm-expand-icon" class="iconochive-down-solid"></span> <span style="font-size:80%">About this capture</span></a>
    </div>
  </div>
    <div id="wm-capinfo" style="border-top:1px solid #777;display:none; overflow: hidden">
            <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center">COLLECTED BY</div>
    <div style="padding:3px;position:relative" id="wm-collected-by-content">
            <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:50%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/ArchiveIt-Partner-593);"></span>
		Organization: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/ArchiveIt-Partner-593" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">Government Printing Office</span></a>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  Archive-It Partner 593: Government Printing Office
	</div>
	      </div>
      <div style="display:inline-block;vertical-align:top;width:49%;">
			<span class="c-logo" style="background-image:url(https://archive.org/services/img/ArchiveIt-Collection-5265)"></span>
		<div>Collection: <a style="color:#33f;" href="https://archive.org/details/ArchiveIt-Collection-5265" target="_new"><span class="wm-title">National Guideline Clearinghouse</span></a></div>
		<div style="max-height:75px;overflow:hidden;position:relative;">
	  <div style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:75px;background:linear-gradient(to bottom,rgba(255,255,255,0) 0%,rgba(255,255,255,0) 90%,rgba(255,255,255,255) 100%);"></div>
	  NGC is an initiative of the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) External Web Site Policy, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. NGC was originally created by AHRQ in partnership with the American Medical Association and the American Association of Health Plans (now America's Health Insurance Plans [AHIP]).

The NGC mission is to provide physicians and other health professionals, health care providers, health plans, integrated delivery systems, purchasers, and others an accessible mechanism for obtaining objective, detailed information on clinical practice guidelines and to further their dissemination, implementation, and use.
	</div>
	      </div>
    </div>
    <div style="background-color:#666;color:#fff;font-weight:bold;text-align:center" title="Timestamps for the elements of this page">TIMESTAMPS</div>
    <div>
      <div id="wm-capresources" style="margin:0 5px 5px 5px;max-height:250px;overflow-y:scroll !important"></div>
      <div id="wm-capresources-loading" style="text-align:left;margin:0 20px 5px 5px;display:none"><img src="/static/images/loading.gif" alt="loading" /></div>
    </div>
  </div></div></div></div><script type="text/javascript">
__wm.bt(575,27,25,2,"web","https://www.guideline.gov/summaries/downloadcontent/ngc-10517?contentType=xml","2016-09-30",1996);
</script>
<!-- END WAYBACK TOOLBAR INSERT --><version>
  <xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource>
  <section secid="390" ordby="100" name="General">
    <field fieldid="161" ordby="105" id="391" name="Guideline Title" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_title&quot;>The care of patients with varicose veins and associated chronic venous diseases: clinical practice guidelines of the Society for Vascular Surgery and the American Venous Forum.</div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="110" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Gloviczki P, Comerota AJ, Dalsing MC, Eklof BG, Gillespie DL, Gloviczki ML, Lohr JM, McLafferty RB, Meissner MH, Murad MH, Padberg FT, Pappas PJ, Passman MA, Raffetto JD, Vasquez MA, Wakefield TW, Society for Vascular Surgery, American Venous Forum. The care of patients with varicose veins and associated chronic venous diseases: clinical practice guidelines of the Society for Vascular Surgery and the American Venous Forum. J Vasc Surg. 2011 May;53(5 Suppl):2S-48S. [375 references] <a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=21536172&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;>PubMed</a></td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="115" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p>
<p>This guideline meets NGC's 2013 (revised) inclusion criteria.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="420" ordby="300" name="Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="151" ordby="310" id="421" name="Major Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Definitions of the strength of the recommendations (<strong>Grade 1</strong> or <strong>2</strong>) and quality of the evidence (<strong>Level A&amp;ndash;C</strong>) are provided at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Diagnostic Evaluation</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>Clinical Examination</strong></p>
<p>For clinical examination of the lower limbs for chronic venous disease (CVD), the Guideline Committee recommends inspection (telangiectasia, varicosity, edema, skin discoloration, corona phlebectatica, lipodermatosclerosis, ulcer), palpation (cord, varicosity, tenderness, induration, reflux, pulses, thrill, groin or abdominal masses), auscultation (bruit), and examination of ankle mobility. Patients should be asked for symptoms of CVD, which may include tingling, aching, burning, pain, muscle cramps, swelling, sensations of throbbing or heaviness, itching skin, restless legs, leg tiredness, and fatigue (<strong>Grade 1A</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Duplex Scanning</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that in patients with CVD, a complete history and detailed physical examination are complemented by duplex scanning of the deep and superficial veins. The test is safe, noninvasive, cost-effective, and reliable (<strong>Grade 1A</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that the four components of a complete duplex scanning examination for chronic venous disease should be visualization, compressibility, venous flow, including measurement of duration of reflux, and augmentation (<strong>Grade 1A</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that reflux to confirm valvular incompetence in the upright position of the patients be elicited in one of two ways: either with increased intra-abdominal pressure using a Valsalva maneuver to assess the common femoral vein and the saphenofemoral junction, or for the more distal veins, use of manual or cuff compression and release of the limb distal to the point of examination (<strong>Grade 1A</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends a cutoff value of 1 second for abnormally reversed flow (reflux) in the femoral and popliteal veins and of 500 ms for the great saphenous vein, the small saphenous vein, the tibial, deep femoral, and the perforating veins (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that in patients with chronic venous insufficiency, duplex scanning of the perforating veins is performed selectively. The Guideline Committee recommends that the definition of &quot;pathologic&quot; perforating veins includes those with an outward flow of duration of &amp;ge;500 ms, with a diameter of &amp;ge;3.5 mm and a location beneath healed or open venous ulcers (clinical, etiology, anatomy, and pathophysiology [CEAP] class C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>) (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>). See Table II in the original guideline document for definitions of CEAP classes.</p>
<p><strong>Plethysmography</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee suggests that venous plethysmography be used selectively for the noninvasive evaluation of the venous system in patients with simple varicose veins (CEAP class C<sub>2</sub>) (<strong>Grade 2C</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that venous plethysmography be used for the noninvasive evaluation of the venous system in patients with advanced CVD if duplex scanning does not provide definitive information on pathophysiology (CEAP class C<sub>3</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>) (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Imaging Studies</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that in patients with varicose veins and more advanced CVD, computed tomography venography, magnetic resonance venography, ascending and descending contrast venography, and intravascular ultrasonography are used selectively, including but not limited to post-thrombotic syndrome, thrombotic or nonthrombotic iliac vein obstruction (May-Thurner syndrome), pelvic congestion syndrome, nutcracker syndrome, vascular malformations, venous trauma, tumors, and planned open or endovascular venous interventions (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Laboratory Evaluation</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that in patients with CVD, evaluation for thrombophilia is needed selectively for those with recurrent deep vein thrombosis, thrombosis at a young age, or thrombosis in an unusual site. Laboratory examination is needed in patients with longstanding venous stasis ulcers (blood cell count and metabolic panel) and in selected patients who undergo general anesthesia for the treatment of CVD. (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Classification</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that CEAP classification be used for patients with CVD. The basic CEAP classification is used for clinical practice, and the full CEAP classification system is used for clinical research (<strong>Grade 1A</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that primary venous disorders, including simple varicose veins, be differentiated from secondary venous insufficiency and from congenital venous disorders because the three conditions differ in pathophysiology and management (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Treatment</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>Outcome Assessment</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that the revised Venous Clinical Severity Score is used for assessment of clinical outcome after therapy for varicose veins and more advanced chronic CVD (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends that a quality-of-life assessment is performed with a disease-specific instrument to evaluate patient-reported outcome and the severity of CVD. (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends duplex scanning for follow-up of patients after venous procedures who have symptoms or recurrence of varicose veins (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends reporting procedure-related minor and major complications after therapy (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Medical Treatment</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee suggests venoactive drugs (diosmin, hesperidin, rutosides, sulodexide, micronized purified flavonoid fraction, or horse chestnut seed extract [aescin]) for patients with pain and swelling due to CVD, in countries where these drugs are available (<strong>Grade 2B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee suggests using pentoxifylline or micronized purified flavonoid fraction, if available, in combination with compression, to accelerate healing of venous ulcers (<strong>Grade 2B</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Compression Treatment</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee suggests compression therapy using moderate pressure (20 to 30 mm Hg) for patients with symptomatic varicose veins (<strong>Grade 2C</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends against compression therapy as the primary treatment of symptomatic varicose veins in patients who are candidates for saphenous vein ablation (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends compression as the primary therapeutic modality for healing venous ulcers (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends compression as an adjuvant treatment to superficial vein ablation for the prevention of ulcer recurrence (<strong>Grade 1A</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Open Venous Surgery</strong></p>
<p>For treatment of the incompetent great saphenous vein, the Guideline Committee suggests high ligation and inversion stripping of the saphenous vein to the level of the knee (<strong>Grade 2B</strong>).</p>
<p>To reduce hematoma formation, pain, and swelling, the Guideline Committee recommends postoperative compression. The recommended period of compression in C<sub>2</sub> patients is 1 week (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>For treatment of small saphenous vein incompetence, the Guideline Committee recommends high ligation of the vein at the knee crease, about 3 to 5 cm distal to the saphenopopliteal junction, with selective invagination stripping of the incompetent portion of the vein (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>To decrease recurrence of venous ulcers, the Guideline Committee recommends ablation of the incompetent superficial veins in addition to compression therapy (<strong>Grade 1A</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee suggests preservation of the saphenous vein using the ambulatory conservative hemodynamic treatment of varicose veins (CHIVA) technique only selectively in patients with varicose veins, when performed by trained venous interventionists (<strong>Grade 2B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee suggests preservation of the saphenous vein using the ambulatory selective varicose vein ablation under local anesthesia (ASVAL) procedure only selectively in patients with varicose veins (<strong>Grade 2C</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends ambulatory phlebectomy for treatment of varicose veins, performed with saphenous vein ablation, either during the same procedure or at a later stage. If general anesthesia is required for phlebectomy, the Guideline Committee suggests concomitant saphenous ablation (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee suggests transilluminated powered phlebectomy using lower oscillation speeds and extended tumescence as an alternative to traditional phlebectomy for extensive varicose veins (<strong>Grade 2C</strong>).</p>
<p>For treatment of recurrent varicose veins, the Guideline Committee suggests ligation of the saphenous stump, ambulatory phlebectomy, sclerotherapy, or endovenous thermal ablation, depending on the etiology, source, location, and extent of varicosity (<strong>Grade 2C</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Endovenous Thermal Ablation</strong></p>
<p>Endovenous thermal ablations (laser and radiofrequency ablations) are safe and effective, and the Guideline Committee recommends them for treatment of saphenous incompetence (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>Because of reduced convalescence and less pain and morbidity, the Guideline Committee recommends endovenous thermal ablation of the incompetent saphenous vein over open surgery (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Sclerotherapy of Varicose Veins</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends liquid or foam sclerotherapy for telangiectasia, reticular veins, and varicose veins (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>For treatment of the incompetent saphenous vein, the Guideline Committee recommends endovenous thermal ablation over chemical ablation with foam (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Special Venous Problems</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>Treatment of Perforating Veins</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends against selective treatment of incompetent perforating veins in patients with simple varicose veins (CEAP class C<sub>2</sub>) (<strong>Grade 1B</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee suggests treatment of &quot;pathologic&quot; perforating veins that includes those with an outward flow duration of &amp;ge;500 ms, with a diameter of &amp;ge;3.5 mm, located beneath a healed or open venous ulcer (CEAP class C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>) (<strong>Grade 2B</strong>).</p>
<p>For treatment of &quot;pathologic&quot; perforating veins, the Guideline Committee suggests subfascial endoscopic perforating vein surgery, ultrasonographically guided sclerotherapy, or thermal ablations (<strong>Grade 2C</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Treatment of Pelvic Varicose Veins</strong></p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends noninvasive imaging with transabdominal and/or transvaginal ultrasonography, computed tomography, or magnetic resonance venography in selected patients with symptoms of pelvic congestion syndrome or symptomatic varices in the distribution of the pubis, labia, perineum, or buttocks (<strong>Grade 1C</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee recommends retrograde ovarian and internal iliac venography in patients with pelvic venous disease, confirmed or suspected by noninvasive imaging studies, in whom an intervention is planned (<strong>Grade 1C</strong>).</p>
<p>The Guideline Committee suggests treatment of pelvic congestion syndrome and pelvic varices with coil embolization, plugs, or transcatheter sclerotherapy, used alone or together (<strong>Grade 2B</strong>).</p>
<p>If less invasive treatment is not available or has failed, the Guideline Committee suggests surgical ligation and excision of ovarian veins to treat reflux (<strong>Grade 2B</strong>).</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Definitions</span></strong>:</p>
<p><strong>Ratings of Quality of Evidence</strong></p>
<table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Ratings of Quality of Evidence&quot;>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Quality of Evidence</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Rating</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Description</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>High</td>
            <td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>A</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Further research unlikely to change confidence in estimate of effect.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Moderate</td>
            <td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>B</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Further research likely to impact confidence in estimate of effect and may change estimate.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Low</td>
            <td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>C</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Further research very likely to impact confidence in estimate of effect and likely to change estimate.</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Strength of Recommendation</strong></p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Grade 1 recommendations (&quot;strong&quot;) are those in which the benefits of an intervention clearly outweigh its risk and burdens. All well-informed patients would choose such a treatment, and the physician can securely recommend it without a detailed knowledge of the underlying data. </li>
    <li>Grade 2 recommendations (&quot;weak&quot;) are weaker and reflect therapies where the benefits and risks are uncertain or are more closely balanced. For such interventions, patients may choose different options based on their underlying values. </li>
</ul>
<p>The words &quot;the Guideline Committee recommends&quot; are used for Grade 1&amp;mdash;strong recommendations&amp;mdash;if the benefits clearly outweigh risks and burdens, or vice versa; the words &quot;the Guideline Committee suggests&quot; are used for Grade 2&amp;mdash;weak recommendations&amp;mdash;when the benefits are closely balanced with risks and burdens.</p>
<p><strong>Grading Recommendations According to Evidence</strong></p>
<table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Grading Recommendations According to Evidence&quot;>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Recommendation</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Description of Recommendation</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits vs Risks and Burdens</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Methodologic Quality of Supporting Evidence</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Comment</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>1A</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, high-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits clearly outweigh risk and burdens, or vice versa</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>RCTs without important limitations or overwhelming evidence from observational studies</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, can apply to most patients in most circumstances without reservation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>1B</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, moderate-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits clearly outweigh risk and burdens, or vice versa</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>RCTs with important limitations (inconsistent results, methodologic flaws, indirect, or imprecise) or exceptionally strong evidence from observational studies</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, can apply to most patients in most circumstances without reservation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>1C</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, low-quality or very lower-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits clearly outweigh risk and burdens, or vice versa</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Observational studies or case series</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation but may change when higher quality evidence becomes available</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>2A</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, high-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits closely balanced with risks and burden</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>RCTs without important limitations or overwhelming evidence from observational studies</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, best action may differ depending on circumstances or patients' or societal values</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>2B</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, moderate-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits closely balanced with risks and burden</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>RCTs with important limitations (inconsistent results, methodologic flaws, indirect, or imprecise) or exceptionally strong evidence from observational studies</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, best action may differ depending on circumstances or patients' or societal values</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>2C</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, low-quality or very low-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Uncertainty in the estimates of benefits, risks, and burden; benefits, risk, and burden may be closely balanced</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Observational studies or case series</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Very weak recommendations; other alternatives may be equally reasonable</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
<p class=&quot;Note&quot;>RCT = randomized controlled trial</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="138" ordby="330" id="423" name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>None provided</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="396" ordby="400" name="Scope">
    <field fieldid="140" ordby="405" id="397" name="Disease/Condition(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Varicose veins of the lower limbs and pelvis and associated chronic venous diseases (CVDs)</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="103" ordby="410" id="398" name="Guideline Category" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Assessment of Therapeutic Effectiveness"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Evaluation"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Management"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Treatment"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="113" ordby="415" id="399" name="Clinical Specialty" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Hematology"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Internal Medicine"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Surgery"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="114" ordby="420" id="400" name="Intended Users" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Physicians"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="129" ordby="425" id="401" name="Guideline Objective(s)" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>To report recently formulated current recommendations for the evaluation and treatment of patients with varicose veins of the lower limbs and pelvis </li>
    <li>To report recommendations for management of superficial and perforating vein incompetence in patients with associated, more advanced chronic venous diseases (CVDs), such as venous edema, skin changes, or ulcerations </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="132" ordby="430" id="402" name="Target Population" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Adults with varicose veins of the lower limbs and pelvis </li>
    <li>Adults with superficial and perforating vein incompetence associated with more advanced chronic venous disorders (CVDs), such as venous edema, skin changes, or ulcerations </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="133" ordby="435" id="403" name="Interventions and Practices Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>Diagnosis/Evaluation</strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;>
    <li>Clinical examination of the lower limbs for chronic venous disease (CVD) (inspection, palpation, auscultation, and examination of ankle mobility) </li>
    <li>Duplex scanning </li>
    <li>Venous plethysmography </li>
    <li>Selective use of imaging studies including computed tomography venography, magnetic resonance venography, ascending and descending contrast venography, and intravascular ultrasonography </li>
    <li>Laboratory evaluation for thrombophilia </li>
    <li>Use of the CEAP classification system: clinical class (C), etiology (E), anatomy (A), and pathophysiology (P) of chronic venous disease </li>
    <li>Outcome assessment using the revised Venous Clinical Severity score, quality of life assessment, duplex scanning for follow-up, and reporting of procedure-related complications after therapy </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Treatment/Management</strong></p>
<ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;>
    <li>Medical therapy including venoactive drugs </li>
    <li>Compression therapy </li>
    <li>Open venous surgery </li>
    <li>Endovenous thermal ablation (laser and radiofrequency ablations) </li>
    <li>Sclerotherapy of varicose veins </li>
    <li>Treatment of perforating veins </li>
    <li>Treatment of pelvic varicose veins </li>
</ol></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="134" ordby="440" id="404" name="Major Outcomes Considered" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Varicose veins recurrence </li>
    <li>Patient satisfaction </li>
    <li>Esthetics </li>
    <li>Time to return to work </li>
    <li>Pain </li>
    <li>Procedurally related complications, including local wound complications, such as infection and hematoma, and systemic complications, including deep vein thrombosis (DVT), pulmonary embolism (PE), air embolism, and pulmonary fibrosis </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="405" ordby="500" name="Methodology">
    <field fieldid="109" ordby="505" id="406" name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Searches of Electronic Databases"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="135" ordby="510" id="407" name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse</strong>: To assist in venous guideline development, the Society for Vascular Surgery (SVS) and the American Venous Forum (AVF) commissioned reviewers at the Knowledge and Evaluation Research Unit, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, to conduct a systematic review and meta-analysis to summarize the best available evidence about the benefits and harms of the different treatments of varicose veins (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).</p>
<p><strong>Eligibility Criteria</strong></p>
<p>Eligible studies were randomized controlled trials (RCTs) and cohort studies that enrolled participants with primary varicose veins who were treated with surgery, sclerotherapy, foam sclerotherapy, percutaneous endovenous thermal interventions (ablation with radiofrequency or laser), or conservative management with compression stockings. Reviewers included studies that measured any of the outcomes of varicose veins recurrence, patient satisfaction, esthetics, time to return to work, pain, and procedurally related complications, including local wound complications, such as infection and hematoma, and systemic complications, including deep vein thrombosis (DVT), pulmonary embolism (PE), air embolism, and pulmonary fibrosis. Studies were included regardless of their language, sample size, surgical technique, or duration of patient follow-up. Single-cohort studies (i.e., studies in which all patients received the same treatment without concurrent comparison groups) were excluded.</p>
<p><strong>Study Identification and Data Collection</strong></p>
<p>An expert reference librarian designed and conducted the electronic search strategy with input from study investigators with expertise in conducting systematic reviews. To identify eligible studies, electronic databases (MEDLINE, EMBASE, Cochrane CENTRAL, Web of Science, and Scopus) were searched through February 2008 and monitored the literature for new publications thereafter. References from experts, bibliographies of included trials, and the Institute for Scientific Information Science Citation Index for publications that cited included studies were also sought. A combination of subject headings and text words were used as needed to define varicosities and the various procedures. Results were limited to comparative studies. The detailed search strategy is available from the authors upon request.</p>
<p>References were uploaded in a Web-based software package developed for systematic review data management (SRS, TrialStat Corp, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada). Paired reviewers working independently screened all titles and abstracts for eligibility. References that were deemed potentially relevant were retrieved in full text and uploaded for full text evaluation against eligibility criteria. The chance-adjusted inter-reviewer agreement (&amp;kappa; statistic) for study eligibility was 0.79 (95% confidence interval [CI], 0.66-0.93). Disagreements were resolved by consensus (the two reviewers discussed the study and reached a consensus), and when disagreement continued, by arbitration (a third reviewer adjudicated the study). Teams of two reviewers working independently and using a standardized form extracted data in duplicate from all eligible studies, including study description, methodologic quality, and outcome data.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="136" ordby="515" id="408" name="Number of Source Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The initial search yielded 1185 references, from which were found 44 eligible articles representing 39 unique studies. Figure 1 in the systematic review companion document (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field) depicts the search and selection procedures.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="115" ordby="520" id="409" name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="149" ordby="525" id="410" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>Ratings of Quality of Evidence</strong></p>
<table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Ratings of Quality of Evidence&quot;>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Quality of Evidence</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Rating</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Description</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>High</td>
            <td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>A</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Further research unlikely to change confidence in estimate of effect.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Moderate</td>
            <td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>B</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Further research likely to impact confidence in estimate of effect and may change estimate.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Low</td>
            <td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;>C</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Further research very likely to impact confidence in estimate of effect and likely to change estimate.</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="116" ordby="530" id="411" name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Meta-Analysis"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="150" ordby="535" id="412" name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse</strong>: To assist in venous guideline development, the Society for Vascular Surgery (SVS) and the American Venous Forum (AVF) commissioned reviewers at the Knowledge and Evaluation Research Unit, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, to conduct a systematic review and meta-analysis to summarize the best available evidence about the benefits and harms of the different treatments of varicose veins (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).</p>
<p><strong><span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;>Statistical Analysis</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>Meta-analyses</strong></p>
<p>When appropriate, the reviewers pooled relative risks (RR) for dichotomous outcomes from each trial using the DerSimonian-Laird random effects model and estimated the 95% confidence interval (CI) for each outcome to reflect the uncertainty of point estimates of effect. A RR of 1.0 indicates no difference between the two interventions in association with a particular outcome. A RR &amp;gt;1.0 indicates that compared with the control intervention, the procedure increased the risk of outcome occurrence. For continuous outcomes, reviewers planned to estimate the weighted effect size and the 95% CI, and for outcomes assessed with multiple scales, the Guideline Committee planned to estimate the standardized mean difference. The reviewers used the <em>I</em><sup>2</sup> statistic, which estimates the percentage of total variation across studies that is due to heterogeneity rather than chance (i.e., the percentage of variability in treatment effects across trials that is not due to chance or random error, but rather due to real differences in study patients, design or interventions). The<em> I</em><sup>2</sup> values of &amp;le;25%, 50%, and &amp;ge;75% represent low, moderate, and high inconsistency, respectively. Statistical analysis was conducted using StatsDirect 2.5.4 software (StatsDirect Ltd, Cheshire, United Kingdom).</p>
<p><strong>Subgroup and Sensitivity Analyses</strong></p>
<p>The a priori hypotheses to explore subgroup interactions and explain inconsistencies in the direction and magnitude of effect among studies included variation in bias protection measures and patient characteristics such as sex. Reviewers also planned to stratify results according to severity of chronic venous disease using the clinical, etiology, anatomy, pathophysiology (CEAP) classification, when reported (published in 1994 and revised in 2004). Reviewers planned to test the hypotheses of a subgroup effect using a test of interaction and to conduct meta-regression to assess the correlation between the effect size and the length of study follow-up. Sensitivity analysis to exclude short-term studies that were unlikely to evaluate outcome of interest was also conducted.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="112" ordby="540" id="413" name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Expert Consensus"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="145" ordby="545" id="414" name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Evidence-based medicine is the conscientious, explicit, and judicious use of the current best evidence in making decisions about the care of individual patients. Guidelines for the care of patients with varicose veins, as recommended in the original guideline document, are based on scientific evidence. The need for adopting evidence-based guidelines and reporting standards for venous diseases has long been recognized by international experts and by leaders of the Society for Vascular Surgery (SVS) and American Venous Forum (AVF). To define current guidelines, members of the Venous Guideline Committee reviewed the relevant literature, including previously published consensus documents and guidelines, meta-analyses, the AVF reports on the Venous Summit at the 2006 and 2009 Pacific Vascular Symposiums and considered the recommendations published in the third edition of the <em>Handbook of Venous Disorders, Guidelines of the American Venous Forum</em>.</p>
<p>The guidelines are based on the Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) system, as it was described by Guyatt et al. (see the &quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations&quot; field). For each guideline, the letter A, B, or C marks the level of current evidence. The grade of recommendation of a guideline can be strong (1) or weak (2), depending on the risk and burden of a particular diagnostic test or a therapeutic procedure to the patient vs the expected benefit.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="146" ordby="550" id="415" name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><strong>Strength of Recommendation</strong></p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Grade 1 recommendations (&quot;strong&quot;) are those in which the benefits of an intervention clearly outweigh its risk and burdens. All well-informed patients would choose such a treatment, and the physician can securely recommend it without a detailed knowledge of the underlying data. </li>
    <li>Grade 2 recommendations (&quot;weak&quot;) are weaker and reflect therapies where the benefits and risks are uncertain or are more closely balanced. For such interventions, patients may choose different options based on their underlying values. </li>
</ul>
<p>The words &quot;the Guideline Committee recommends&quot; are used for Grade 1&amp;mdash;strong recommendations&amp;mdash;if the benefits clearly outweigh risks and burdens, or vice versa; the words &quot;the Guideline Committee suggests&quot; are used for Grade 2&amp;mdash;weak recommendations&amp;mdash;when the benefits are closely balanced with risks and burdens.</p>
<p><strong>Grading Recommendations According to Evidence</strong></p>
<table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Grading Recommendations According to Evidence&quot;>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Recommendation</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Description of Recommendation</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits vs Risks and Burdens</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Methodologic Quality of Supporting Evidence</th>
            <th valign=&quot;top&quot;>Comment</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>1A</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, high-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits clearly outweigh risk and burdens, or vice versa</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>RCTs without important limitations or overwhelming evidence from observational studies</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, can apply to most patients in most circumstances without reservation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>1B</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, moderate-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits clearly outweigh risk and burdens, or vice versa</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>RCTs with important limitations (inconsistent results, methodologic flaws, indirect, or imprecise) or exceptionally strong evidence from observational studies</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, can apply to most patients in most circumstances without reservation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>1C</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation, low-quality or very lower-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits clearly outweigh risk and burdens, or vice versa</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Observational studies or case series</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Strong recommendation but may change when higher quality evidence becomes available</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>2A</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, high-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits closely balanced with risks and burden</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>RCTs without important limitations or overwhelming evidence from observational studies</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, best action may differ depending on circumstances or patients' or societal values</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>2B</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, moderate-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Benefits closely balanced with risks and burden</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>RCTs with important limitations (inconsistent results, methodologic flaws, indirect, or imprecise) or exceptionally strong evidence from observational studies</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, best action may differ depending on circumstances or patients' or societal values</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>2C</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Weak recommendation, low-quality or very low-quality evidence</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Uncertainty in the estimates of benefits, risks, and burden; benefits, risk, and burden may be closely balanced</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Observational studies or case series</td>
            <td valign=&quot;top&quot;>Very weak recommendations; other alternatives may be equally reasonable</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
<p class=&quot;Note&quot;>RCT = randomized controlled trial</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="148" ordby="565" id="417" name="Cost Analysis" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The cost-effectiveness of conservative vs surgical therapy or sclerotherapy in patients with varicose veins was studied in the REACTIV trial. Cost-effectiveness analysis showed that surgery was significantly more cost-effective than both sclerotherapy and conservative management; sclerotherapy was less cost-effective than surgery but was still significantly more cost-effective than conservative treatment.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="104" ordby="570" id="418" name="Method of Guideline Validation" type="picklist-choice">
      <fieldvalue value="Internal Peer Review"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="130" ordby="575" id="419" name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The Document Oversight Committee of the Society for Vascular Surgery (SVS) conducts peer reviews of the guidelines documents. This committee consists of a panel of eight experts not involved in the aforementioned steps. Committee members who participated in writing the guidelines manuscript are excused from the review process.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="424" ordby="600" name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="139" ordby="610" id="426" name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The type of supporting evidence is identified and graded for each recommendation (see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field).</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="427" ordby="700" name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations">
    <field fieldid="152" ordby="705" id="428" name="Potential Benefits" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Appropriate management of patients with varicose veins and associated chronic venous diseases (CVD)</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="153" ordby="710" id="429" name="Potential Harms" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>The risk of perioperative deep vein thrombosis (DVT) is increased in patients with thrombophilia, in those with a history of DVT or thrombophlebitis, and in obese patients. </li>
    <li>Wound complications usually occur in 3% to 10% of patients undergoing open venous surgery, with reported wound infection rates as low as 1.5% and as high as 16%. </li>
    <li>DVT and pulmonary embolism (PE) are rare but occasionally serious complications of superficial vein surgery. </li>
    <li>Reported complications after transilluminated powered phlebectomy (TIPP) have varied considerably and include ecchymosis and hematoma in 4.9% to 95%, paresthesias and nerve injury in 9.5% to 39%, skin perforation in 1.2% to 5%, superficial phlebitis in 2.4% to 13%, swelling in 5% to 17.5%, hyperpigmentation in 1.2% to 3.3%, residual or recurrent varicose veins in 9.1% to 21.2%, and DVT in &amp;lt;1%. </li>
    <li>Complications associated with endovenous laser ablation (EVLA) include bruising, paresthesia, thrombophlebitis, skin burns, DVT and PE. </li>
    <li>Complications associated with radiofrequency ablation (RFA) include paresthesia, thrombophlebitis, ecchymosis along the course of the great saphenous vein (GSV), and skin pigmentation. </li>
    <li>Severe complications after sclerotherapy, such as death, anaphylactic reaction, pulmonary emboli, stroke, and large areas of skin necrosis, are very rare (&amp;lt;0.01%). Severe but rare complications also include thrombophlebitis, nerve damage (saphenous, sural), DVT, or inadvertent arterial injection of the solution. Transient neurologic adverse effects such as visual disturbance, migraine-like headache, or confusional state may occur and are more frequent in patients with a patent foramen ovale. Most complications are minor, and include matting, pigmentation, pain, allergy, and skin urticaria. The higher the concentration of the agent, the higher the likelihood of hyperpigmentation, a minor complication that can be observed in up to 30% of the cases. Between 70% and 95% of the pigmentations, however, resolve by 1 year after therapy. The incidence of major neurologic events after foam injection is rare; instances of stroke were reported by several authors. Immediate treatment with 100% oxygen and possibly hyperbaric oxygen therapy should be considered. Factors implicated in the risk of stroke after foam sclerotherapy include the use of air instead of carbon dioxide to prepare the foam, large bubble size, a patent foramen ovale, failure to elevate the limb after treatment, prolonged immobility after therapy, and an excessive amount of foam used during one session. Refer to the original guideline document for additional discussion of complications of sclerotherapy. </li>
    <li>Wound infection and saphenous neuralgia each occurred in 6% of patients undergoing subfascial endoscopic perforator surgery (SEPS). </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="430" ordby="800" name="Contraindications">
    <field fieldid="144" ordby="805" id="431" name="Contraindications" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Inappropriate vein size (&amp;lt;2 mm and &amp;gt;15 mm for radiofrequency ablation [RFA]), a history of superficial thrombophlebitis resulting in a partially obstructed saphenous vein, and the uncommon occurrence of a tortuous great saphenous vein (GSV) on duplex examination are potential contraindications to endovenous thermal ablation. </li>
    <li>There are no absolute contraindications to endovenous laser ablation (EVLA), including vein diameter, although one study had recently suggested an association of central GSV diameter &amp;gt;8 mm with increased risk of extension of thrombus into the femoral vein. Other relative contraindications to EVLA or RFA include uncorrectable coagulopathy, liver dysfunction limiting local anesthetic use, immobility, pregnancy, and breastfeeding </li>
    <li>Advanced stages of chronic venous insufficiency may be associated with limitations or contraindications to surgical treatment by conventional vein stripping, including extensive dermatosclerosis, fibrosis, ulcer scarring sequelae, active ulcers, edema, or lymphedema, thus making the use of alternative methods of treatment necessary. </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="432" ordby="900" name="Qualifying Statements">
    <field fieldid="137" ordby="905" id="433" name="Qualifying Statements" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Under no circumstance should these <em>Guidelines</em> be construed in practice or legal terms as defining the &quot;standard of care,&quot; which is solely determined by the condition of the individual patient, treatment setting, and other factors. Individual factors in a given patient, such as symptom variance or combinations, comorbidities, work, and socioeconomic factors may dictate a different approach than that described in the <em>Guidelines</em>. Because technology and disease knowledge is rapidly expanding, new approaches may supersede these recommendations. As important new information on management of varicose veins and related chronic venous diseases (CVD) becomes available, these recommendations will be revised without delay. </li>
    <li>Despite the challenges and inconsistent availability of high-quality evidence, the Society for Vascular Surgery (SVS) maintains its effort to summarize, synthesize, and present all the available evidence, along with clear clinical practice recommendations, to help surgeons and their patients in decision making. Although the SVS uses state-of-the-art approaches, such as Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development and Evaluation framework (GRADE), innovations are needed to improve the quality of evidence in the field and to improve the clarity and usefulness of these guidelines, which will lead to increased confidence in the advice vascular surgeons provide to their patients. Given the limited quality of the evidence, the issues with generalizability, and the importance of patient values, practice guidelines should not be regarded as definitive or prescriptive. Consistent with the tenets of evidence-based medicine, they should be used to inform clinical decision making in the context of the physician's clinical expertise and the patient's underlying values and preferences. </li>
</ul>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="434" ordby="1000" name="Implementation of the Guideline">
    <field fieldid="131" ordby="1010" id="436" name="Description of Implementation Strategy" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>An implementation strategy was not provided.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="439" ordby="1100" name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories">
    <field fieldid="50" ordby="1105" id="440" name="IOM Care Need" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Getting Better"/>
      <fieldvalue value="Living with Illness"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="51" ordby="1110" id="441" name="IOM Domain" type="picklist-many">
      <fieldvalue value="Effectiveness"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="442" ordby="1200" name="Identifying Information and Availability">
    <field fieldid="97" ordby="1201" id="392" name="Bibliographic Source(s)" type="citation">
      <fieldvalue value="<table><tr><td>Gloviczki P, Comerota AJ, Dalsing MC, Eklof BG, Gillespie DL, Gloviczki ML, Lohr JM, McLafferty RB, Meissner MH, Murad MH, Padberg FT, Pappas PJ, Passman MA, Raffetto JD, Vasquez MA, Wakefield TW, Society for Vascular Surgery, American Venous Forum. The care of patients with varicose veins and associated chronic venous diseases: clinical practice guidelines of the Society for Vascular Surgery and the American Venous Forum. J Vasc Surg. 2011 May;53(5 Suppl):2S-48S. [375 references] <a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=21536172&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;>PubMed</a></td></tr></table>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="124" ordby="1205" id="443" name="Adaptation" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="128" ordby="1215" id="445" name="Date Released" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="2011 May"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="158" ordby="1225" id="447" name="Guideline Developer(s)" type="orglist-p">
      <fieldvalue value="Society for Vascular Surgery - Medical Specialty Society"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="125" ordby="1235" id="449" name="Source(s) of Funding" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Society for Vascular Surgery</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="126" ordby="1240" id="450" name="Guideline Committee" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Venous Guideline Committee of the Society for Vascular Surgery (SVS) and the American Venous Forum (AVF)</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="127" ordby="1245" id="451" name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p><em>Committee Members</em>: Peter Gloviczki, MD, Division of Vascular and Endovascular Surgery, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minn; Anthony J. Comerota, MD, Jobst Vascular Center, Toledo, Ohio; Michael C. Dalsing, MD, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, Ind; Bo G. Eklof, MD, University of Lund, Helsingborg, Sweden; David L. Gillespie, MD, the School of Medicine and Dentistry, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY; Monika L. Gloviczki, MD, PhD, Division of Nephrology and Hypertension, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minn; Joann M. Lohr, MD, Lohr Surgical Specialists, Cincinnati, Ohio; Robert B. McLafferty, MD, Southern Illinois University, Springfield, Ill; Mark H. Meissner, MD, the University of Washington School of Medicine, Seattle, Wash; M. Hassan Murad, MD, MPH, Division of Preventive, Occupational and Aerospace Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minn; Frank T. Padberg, MD, New Jersey Medical School, University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, Newark, NJ; Peter J. Pappas, MD, New Jersey Medical School, University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, Newark, NJ; Marc A. Passman, MD, the University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Ala; Joseph D. Raffetto, MD, VA Boston Healthcare System, West Roxbury, Mass; Michael A. Vasquez, MD, RVT, Venous Institute of Buffalo, North Tonawanda, NY; Thomas W. Wakefield, MD, the University of Michigan Medical School, Ann Arbor, Mich</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="147" ordby="1250" id="452" name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Committee members are required to provide a detailed, explicit description of their financial and intellectual conflicts of interest, consistent with the policies of the <em>Journal of Vascular Surgery</em>. Additional measures used to manage conflicts of interest include the multidisciplinary structure of guideline committees and the involvement of a methodology group in the evidence synthesis and guidelines integration.</p>
<p>Competition of interest: none.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="120" ordby="1256" id="393" name="Guideline Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This is the current release of the guideline.</p>
<p>This guideline meets NGC's 2013 (revised) inclusion criteria.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="118" ordby="1260" id="454" name="Guideline Availability" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>Electronic copies: Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.jvascsurg.org/article/S0741-5214%2811%2900327-2/fulltext&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Vascular Surgery Web site&quot;>Journal of Vascular Surgery Web site</a>.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="119" ordby="1265" id="455" name="Availability of Companion Documents" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>The following are available:</p>
<ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;>
    <li>Murad MH, Coto-Yglesias F, Zumaeta-Garcia M, Elamin MB, Duggirala MK, Erwin PJ, Montori VM, Gloviczki P. A systematic review and meta-analysis of the treatments of varicose veins. J Vasc Surg. 2011 May;53(Suppl 2):51S-67S. Electronic copies: Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.jvascsurg.org/article/S0741-5214(11)00329-6/pdf&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Vascular Surgery Web site&quot;>Journal of Vascular Surgery Web site</a>. </li>
    <li>Murad MH, Montori VM, Sidawy AN, Ascher E, Meissner MH, Gloviczki P. Guideline methodology of the Society for Vascular Surgery including the experience with the GRADE framework. J Vasc Surg. 2011 May;53:1375-80. Electronic copies: Available from the <a href=&quot;http://www.jvascsurg.org/article/S0741-5214(11)00192-3/pdf&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Vascular Surgery Web site&quot;>Journal of Vascular Surgery Web site</a>. </li>
</ul></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="143" ordby="1275" id="457" name="Patient Resources" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>None available</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="142" ordby="1280" id="458" name="NGC Status" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on October 17, 2014. The information was verified by the guideline developer on November 18, 2014.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
    <field fieldid="141" ordby="1290" id="460" name="Copyright Statement" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<div class=&quot;content_para&quot;><p>This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.</p></div>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
  <section secid="99999" ordby="99999" name="Disclaimer">
    <field fieldid="99999" ordby="99999" id="99999" name="NGC Disclaimer" type="text">
      <fieldvalue value="<p>The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.</p> 
<p>All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.</p> 
<p>Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at <a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;>http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx</a>.</p> 
<p>NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.</p> 
<p>Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.</p>"/>
    </field>
  </section>
</version><!--
     FILE ARCHIVED ON 22:11:39 Sep 30, 2016 AND RETRIEVED FROM THE
     INTERNET ARCHIVE ON 23:50:16 Jul 15, 2018.
     JAVASCRIPT APPENDED BY WAYBACK MACHINE, COPYRIGHT INTERNET ARCHIVE.

     ALL OTHER CONTENT MAY ALSO BE PROTECTED BY COPYRIGHT (17 U.S.C.
     SECTION 108(a)(3)).
-->
<!--
playback timings (ms):
  LoadShardBlock: 1155.677 (3)
  esindex: 0.01
  captures_list: 1176.041
  CDXLines.iter: 15.028 (3)
  PetaboxLoader3.datanode: 1074.567 (4)
  exclusion.robots: 0.392
  exclusion.robots.policy: 0.375
  RedisCDXSource: 1.708
  PetaboxLoader3.resolve: 152.594 (2)
  load_resource: 107.718
-->